<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Best Books on Will Cartar&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://cartar.github.io./categories/best-books/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Best Books on Will Cartar&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <managingEditor>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</webMaster>
    <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2024 12:23:06 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://cartar.github.io./categories/best-books/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Project Hail Mary</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202405projecthailmary/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2024 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202405projecthailmary/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What a rush. This review won&amp;rsquo;t be detailed to not give away the twists and turns, but from get go, this is a page turner. Our main character wakes with amnesia, allowing the reader to explore this new world alongside him. And of course, our man is a scientist (I say of course because Andy Weir is also the author of the Martian - it&amp;rsquo;s his thing)!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Successful Aging</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202311successfulaging/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2023 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202311successfulaging/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Before I had even finished it, I&amp;rsquo;d bought 2 copies of this book: one for my parents, and the other for my partner&amp;rsquo;s. I admit, some chapters review much of what I already knew; exercise is very good for our brains and body (and you don&amp;rsquo;t need to be a gym rat - just get your heart rate up!); healthy eating isn&amp;rsquo;t prescribable, but it&amp;rsquo;ll include eating a range of unprocessed food (processed food is bad), eating in moderation, less sweets, and finding a diet that works best for you (without going to the extremes). But the many reviews of the latest neuroscience and how they apply to us as we age was fascinating. For example, a reason we &amp;ldquo;always have room for dessert&amp;rdquo; is the novel flavours (sweet after salty) pique your interest even though enough was several mouthfuls ago.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mendeleyev&#39;s dream</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202308mendeleyevsdream/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2023 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202308mendeleyevsdream/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This book was the first time I came into contact with a history of chemistry, and it was absolutely fascinating. Histories of physics have been my default, due to their ongoing contributions to the origins of life, the universe and everything; but much of that history is the back and forth of military funded experiments, and intellectual genius. Chemistry, on the other hand, was funded by the wealthy in an attempt to create more wealth through transmutation (i.e., alchemy), as well as the mishaps of mad scientists tinkering with &amp;ldquo;the elements&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Death&#39;s End</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202305deathsend/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2023 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202305deathsend/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The cover of this book says: &amp;ldquo;wildly imaginative&amp;rdquo;, which is a perfect synopsys. I&amp;rsquo;ve not had my mind blow so many times over by a series, and I doubt I ever will again. It isn&amp;rsquo;t just the exotic physics of higher dimensions utilized by hyper advanced civilizations. It is the political interactions of those civilizations with one another, and a story arc that is truly captivating. I felt the full range of emotions in this book - from excitedly anticipating reunions, to battles outcomes, mind games, and love stories. This book had it all. I cannot recommend this book, or this series enough. The only downside is that the books are a little long, and take ~50-100 pages to really get into. But once you&amp;rsquo;re there, the length of the story becomes a blessing, as you&amp;rsquo;ll not want the ride to end.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Dark Forest</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202303thedarkforest/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202303thedarkforest/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With the story well underway, this second book is a masterpiece. Without giving too much away, we are transported to a future where Luo Ji is awake and well. Technology has progressed far enough to give humanity a sense of security, and that leads to some interesting plot development. We finally learn why Luo Ji had so many assassination attempts against him, and yet again, the story unfolds with unanticipated twists that make it hard to put down.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>naked statistics</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202211nakedstatistics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2022 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202211nakedstatistics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A masterpiece in fun-reading education; this book is accessible to everyone who&amp;rsquo;s goal is to learn statistics. And for those with a strong handle on the subject, it is a good reminder of the pitfalls of being too brash with the toolkit.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dopamine Nation</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202204dopaminenation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202204dopaminenation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;An insightful perspective on our society today, the author weaves stories of addiction throughout to illustrate how we&amp;rsquo;re easily prone to it, and how we might pull ourselves out.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The most insightful lesson (for me) was that pain is in fact a pleasurable time-sink, due to the pleasure-pain balance our bodies strive for. Post pain, we are often flooded with euphoric hormones to compensate. Beware of becoming addicted to pain, but, when used correctly, it is a low risk powerful stimulant.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Bomber Mafia</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202204bombermafia/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Apr 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202204bombermafia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A masterclass in storytelling. I found it hard to put this book down from start to finish. As the title says, this book follows the evolution of America&amp;rsquo;s bomber mafia, a group of pilots who helped create the Air Force. We learn about their military decisions, shortcomings, success, and the ending of WW2. An interesting story told by one of the greatest storytellers of our time.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Educated</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202202educated/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202202educated/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A gripping story of being raised without traditional education, and the impact that had on Tara as she discovers a world beyond her childhood.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I found this book hard to put down. I highly recommend it to anyone looking for a non-fiction story that&amp;rsquo;ll transport you to another world.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noise: A flaw in Human Judgment</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202110noise/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Oct 2021 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202110noise/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This book opened my eyes to the differences between bias and noise, and how they are equally proportional to disrupting our desired outcome. That is to say, imagine missing a target by some random &amp;ldquo;noisy&amp;rdquo; amount, which widens the bell curve of outcomes. The distance, on average, away from the target result would be just as bad as an equal error magnitude in bias. The only difference being that the bias is easier to see, because it is clustering away from the target. Thus, bias is often the focus in reducing error for our desired outcomes, when really, it should be considered equally with noise, if our goal is error reduction.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics of the Impossible</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202106physicsimpossible/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 May 2021 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202106physicsimpossible/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A physics book unlike any other I&amp;rsquo;ve read. Reality is distorted by the mind-bending possibilities of physics that are beyond our reach. Sometimes, the physics has been proven, but we&amp;rsquo;re missing technological advances necessary to bring it to life, other times, it&amp;rsquo;s physics that might truly be impossible. In either case, the idea&amp;rsquo;s themselves are delightful to consume. Some minds are truly special.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shoe Dog</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202103shoedog/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2021 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202103shoedog/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A novel that&amp;rsquo;ll transport you back to a decade quite unlike today. Not only was there no Nike, there wasn&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;athleisure&amp;rdquo; or jogging for fun. The story on it&amp;rsquo;s own is hard to put down, but the way it&amp;rsquo;s told makes this a truly joyful read.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atomic Habits</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202101atomichabits/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202101atomichabits/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Very engaging book. In addition to learning about the power of habits, you&amp;rsquo;ll also learn to recognize what parts of your life are good/bad habits and how to build/break them. It&amp;rsquo;s a solid framework for everyone to understand, regardless of your goals. Best of all, this book keeps you engaged from chapter 1 with well told anecdotes and analogies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Silk Roads</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202006silkroads/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2020 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202006silkroads/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This book is an epic undertaking, showcasing world history up to the early 2010&amp;rsquo;s, through the lense of the silk road. History has many authors, and this book does well to capture their ideas in a cohesive framework. The thesis presented here outlines how resource transportation routes shaped our world history. Equally important to the goods flowing through commerce were new ideas, including religions, and a massive game of political chess. Short term policies crafted to maintain power at the expense of those without it, often led to self destruction through overreach (and over spending). Worse still was the long term instability created by dying powers&amp;rsquo; abrupt departure from battleground regions. The most shocking lesson I took away is how cyclical our world history is. The fight for power, and abhorrent disregard for others by those trying to maintain it, is the saddest trait we share.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alex&#39;s Adventures in Numberland</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202004alexadventurenumberland/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Apr 2020 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202004alexadventurenumberland/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This book was truly a wonderful read! If you want to learn about math&amp;rsquo;s history, you will love this book &amp;#x1f495;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You do not need to have a strong background in math to get the full punch from this story.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-favourite-takeaways&#34;&gt;My favourite takeaways&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;regression-to-the-mean&#34;&gt;Regression to the mean&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Regression to the mean is the concept that, over time, event likelihood converges on the average result. Said another way, whenever an outlier occurs, there&amp;rsquo;s a good chance that the next event will be closer to the main outcome.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Talking to Strangers</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202003talking2strangers/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202003talking2strangers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Using a mix of data and in-depth investigations around high profile human interactions, where human behaviour is interpreted terribly, we learn some very important lessons. As usual, Malcolm Gladwell delivers these stories in a wonderful read.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-favourite-takeaways&#34;&gt;My favourite takeaways&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Defaulting to the truth is OK. It is what created our society and it would be stupid to override this companionship generating trait.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The coupling of environment and action is so strong that it should always be taken into account when interacting with strangers.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t judge a stranger, judge their environment.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;We are bad lie detectors. We expect a liar to act one way, and a truth teller another. Our snap decision lie detection is never to be trusted.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;5/5.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
