<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>


<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title type="text">Will Cartar&#39;s Blog</title>
    <subtitle type="html">MemE is a powerful and highly customizable GoHugo theme for personal blogs.</subtitle>
    <updated>2020-06-27T14:54:13-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://cartar.github.io./</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./" />
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom&#43;xml" href="https://cartar.github.io./atom.xml" />
    <author>
            <name>Will Cartar</name>
            <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
            
                <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
            </author>
    <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights>
    <generator uri="https://gohugo.io/" version="0.72.0">Hugo</generator>
        <entry>
            <title type="text">The Silk Roads</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/silkroads/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/silkroads/</id>
            <updated>2020-06-27T14:32:55-04:00</updated>
            <published>2020-06-14T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">This book is a massive undertaking that constructs the why behind our current situation. History has many authors, and this book does well to capture their idea&amp;rsquo;s in a cohesive framework. That the pipeline of resources, starting with the silk road, has been the major thread in our world history.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This book is a massive undertaking that constructs the why behind our current situation. History has many authors, and this book does well to capture their idea&amp;rsquo;s in a cohesive framework. That the pipeline of resources, starting with the silk road, has been the major thread in our world history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book starts off slow, but is worth perservering through the begging chapter&amp;rsquo;s many names, dates, regions and wars. It starts about 2000 years ago, following the quest for resource dominance. In the first millenia, these resources are luxury goods like silk, spices, or tea, along with military equiptment, horses and slaves. Sharing of the luxury goods to a select inner circle keep them content as they oversee mass inequality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-main-take-aways&#34;&gt;My main take aways&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;History lessons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How a world with hundreds of religions is reduced to a few&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why the middle east is a hotbed for endless fighting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The luck involved to create a golden era
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How quickly that era falls when the KingPin dies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The human cost required to sustain an empire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And most importantly, &lt;strong&gt;how frequently history repeats itself&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">Alex’s Adventures in Numberland</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/alexadventurenumberland/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/alexadventurenumberland/</id>
            <updated>2020-06-27T14:39:37-04:00</updated>
            <published>2020-04-25T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">In addition to this book being a wonderful read, here are my main take aways.
Regression to the mean Regression to the mean is the concept that, over time, event likihood converges on the average result. Said another way, whenever an outlier occurs, there&amp;rsquo;s a good chance that the next event will be closer to the main outcome.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In addition to this book being a wonderful read, here are my main take aways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;regression-to-the-mean&#34;&gt;Regression to the mean&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regression to the mean is the concept that, over time, event likihood converges on the average result. Said another way, whenever an outlier occurs, there&amp;rsquo;s a good chance that the next event will be closer to the main outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This idea is interesting implications within the workplace. Manager&amp;rsquo;s are stung when praising outstanding work that is followed by normal work; whereas chastising bad work is usually followed by better performance. However, neither the praise nor the reprimand likely had as large of an effect as regression to the mean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;normal-distribution&#34;&gt;Normal Distribution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The normal distribution is the result of randomness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whatever you see a normal distribution not caused by randomness, be very suspicous.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you carefully measure something, if you do not see a normal distribution where randomness should occur (i.e., measurement error), you have likely destroyed the randomness that should be present.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">Talking to Strangers</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/talking2strangers/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/talking2strangers/</id>
            <updated>2020-06-27T14:45:55-04:00</updated>
            <published>2020-03-20T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">Using a mix of data and in-depth investigations around high profile human interactions, where human behaviour is interpreted terribly, we learn some very important lessons. As usual, Malcolm Gladwell deliveries these stories in an engaging book, that was easily devoured.
My main take aways:  Defaulting to truth is OK.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Using a mix of data and in-depth investigations around high profile human interactions, where human behaviour is interpreted terribly, we learn some very important lessons. As usual, Malcolm Gladwell deliveries these stories in an engaging book, that was easily devoured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-main-take-aways&#34;&gt;My main take aways:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Defaulting to truth is OK. It is what created our society and it would be stupid to override this companionship generating trait.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The coupling of environment and action is very strong so strong that it is an aspect of interacting with strangers that should be taken into account companionship generating trait.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t judge a stranger, judge their environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are bad lies actors. We expect a liar to act one way and truth tellers another. Snap behaviour from interaction is almost impossible for us to notice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">The Personal MBA</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/mypersonalmba/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/mypersonalmba/</id>
            <updated>2020-06-27T14:53:43-04:00</updated>
            <published>2020-02-20T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">I enjoyed this book, but am hesitant to recommend it to others. The writting is only OK, and so much of the content felt somewhat common sense. However, I did find multiple nuggets worth keeping! These are my brief notes from those nuggets.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed this book, but am hesitant to recommend it to others. The writting is only OK, and so much of the content felt somewhat common sense. However, I did find multiple nuggets worth keeping! These are my brief notes from those nuggets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;prototyping&#34;&gt;Prototyping&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When developing a business, iteration and feedback are key. Offering a pre-order with full access to the witten Prototype (description of what is being offered) is ideal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If no one wants to pre-order in free prototype your offer is in valuable enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;reorgnaization&#34;&gt;Reorgnaization&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Random actions change things. Attempt to reorganize ideas is our body&amp;rsquo;s way of searching for solutions. When reference levels are violated, and we do not know what action to take next, try reorganization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simulations in your brain only works really well with a goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;environment&#34;&gt;Environment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Easiest way to change things is by changing your environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;reference-levels&#34;&gt;Reference Levels&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humans do not have easily manipulated behavior. We are too complex for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather we have reference levels, that, when out of whack, force us to make change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;reinterpretation&#34;&gt;Reinterpretation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you want to change your beliefs (or mental stimuli) simply follow:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recall that believe in as much detail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Think of alternative interpretations for that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Realize your belief is an interpretation, not fact.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discard your belief.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose an alternative interpretation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;motivation&#34;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either moving towards or away from things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We evolves to prioritize moving away, which makes sense from our ancestors point-of-view, but doesn&amp;rsquo;t serve us as well today. Understand this emotional tug-of-war when making decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we prioritize moving away, we focus on what is being lost. This can make us fearful of change, because we aren&amp;rsquo;t understanding the complete picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;selection-test&#34;&gt;Selection Test&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Environmental constraints that determine which systems can be self perpetuating and which ones die.
Know the selection tests for a market and you can change the field; especially as markets change due to tech.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
</feed>
