<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>


<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title type="text">Will Cartar&#39;s Blog</title>
    <subtitle type="html">MemE is a powerful and highly customizable GoHugo theme for personal blogs.</subtitle>
    <updated>2022-08-05T09:38:42&#43;01:00</updated>
    <id>https://cartar.github.io./</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./" />
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom&#43;xml" href="https://cartar.github.io./atom.xml" />
    <author>
            <name>Will Cartar</name>
            <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
            
                <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
            </author>
    <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights>
    <generator uri="https://gohugo.io/" version="0.92.0">Hugo</generator>
        <entry>
            <title type="text">The Ride of a Lifetime</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202208rideofalifetime/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202208rideofalifetime/</id>
            <updated>2022-08-05T09:37:41&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2022-08-03T01:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">A captivating recount of how Disney transformed over the past 20+ years. Bob reviews many acquisitions, and some near-misses (Disney almost bought Twitter before Disney +). A good read for anyone curious how big companies grow larger. Lots of lessons learned.
Highlights:  &amp;ldquo;Avoid getting into the business of manufacturing trombone oil.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A captivating recount of how Disney transformed over the past 20+ years. Bob reviews many acquisitions, and some near-misses (Disney almost bought Twitter before Disney +). A good read for anyone curious how big companies grow larger. Lots of lessons learned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;highlights&#34;&gt;Highlights:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Avoid getting into the business of manufacturing trombone oil. You may become the greatest trombone-oil manufacturer in the world, but in the end, the world only consumes a few quarts of trombone oil a year!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s a hard thing to do, especially in the moment, but those instances in which you find yourself hoping that something will work without being able to convincingly explain to yourself how it will work - that&amp;rsquo;s when a little bell should go off, and you should walk yourself through some clarifying questions. What&amp;rsquo;s the problem I need to solve? Does this solution make sense? If I&amp;rsquo;m feeling some doubt, why? Am I doing this for sound reasons or am I motivated by something personal?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;A company&amp;rsquo;s culture is shaped by a lot of things, but this is one of the most important - you have to convey your priorities clearly and repeatedly. In my experience, it&amp;rsquo;s what separates great managers from the rest.&amp;rdquo;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;You can do a lot for the morale of the people around you (and therefore the people around them) just by taking the guesswork out of their day-to-day life&amp;hellip; This is where we want to be. This is how we&amp;rsquo;re going to get there.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;My job was to set our company on a new path, and the first step was to defuse this unnecessary struggle. The easiest and most productive way to do that was to recognize that what Roy needed, ultimately, was to feel respected. That was precious to him, and it cost me and the company so little.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;This is you making a decision about them - not them as a person but the way they have performed in their job - and they need and deserve to know that it&amp;rsquo;s coming from you. You can&amp;rsquo;t make small talk once you bring someone in for that conversation. I normally say something along the lines of: &amp;lsquo;I&amp;rsquo;ve asked you to come in here for a difficult reason.&amp;rsquo; And then I try to be as direct about the issue as possible, explaining clearly and concisely what wasn&amp;rsquo;t working and why I didn&amp;rsquo;t think it was going to change. I emphasize that it was a tough decision to make, and that I understand that it&amp;rsquo;s much harder on them.&amp;rdquo;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;If you respect the person, then you owe them a clear explanation for the decision you&amp;rsquo;re making. There&amp;rsquo;s no way for the conversation not to be painful, but at least it can be honest.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;the hardest but also the most necessary lesson to keep in mind, that wherever you are along the path, you&amp;rsquo;re the same person you&amp;rsquo;ve always been.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Pessimism leads to paranoia, which leads to defensiveness, which leads to risk aversion.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;If something doesn&amp;rsquo;t feel right to you, it won&amp;rsquo;t be right for you.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/" term="Good Books" label="Good Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">Six Not-So-Easy Pieces</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202207sixnoteasypieces/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202207sixnoteasypieces/</id>
            <updated>2022-07-28T11:00:38&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2022-07-27T01:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">This book introduces the reader to relativity, symmetry and space-time through Feynman&amp;rsquo;s eyes. He discusses features of our universe with engaging analogies, like how to distinguish right from left (which is a tricky business). Or why we have time dilation from gravity. However, I&amp;rsquo;d argue that there are better books introducing audiences to these topics nowadays, like black holes and time warps by Kip S.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This book introduces the reader to relativity, symmetry and space-time through Feynman&amp;rsquo;s eyes. He discusses features of our universe with engaging analogies, like how to distinguish right from left (which is a tricky business). Or why we have time dilation from gravity. However, I&amp;rsquo;d argue that there are better books introducing audiences to these topics nowadays, like black holes and time warps by Kip S. Thorne.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;symmetry-and-conservation-laws&#34;&gt;Symmetry and conservation laws&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;For each of the rules of symmetry there is a corresponding conservation law&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;, in quantum mechanics. For example, that laws are symmetrical for&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;translation in space = momentum is conserved&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;translation in time = energy is conserved&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;invariance under rotation = angular momentum is conserved&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;phase shift of the wave function = electrical charge is conserved&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And some are bizarre, like reflection symmetry which leads to the conservation of parity (no classical analog). However, this conservation is not conserved in matter alone. There are ways in which reflection symmetry is broken, like beta (or weak) decay. It is only with the introduction of anti-matter that the reflection symmetry is restored - and so, we say that parity is conserved under reflection and matter/antimatter symmetry. That is, &amp;ldquo;matter to the right is symmetrical with anti-matter to the left&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;bookmarked-ideas&#34;&gt;Bookmarked ideas&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If we have a particle of rest mass zero, it cannot stop. It always goes the speed c, as in the case of light. Photons have energy, without mass, by perpetually going the speed of light. [This is similar to how any object with rest mass non-zero cannot go the speed of light, without having an infinite amount of energy. Light has finite energy, with zero mass, yet always travels at the speed of light.]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One way to think of gravitational time dilation is to picture an accelerating rocket ship with a clock at the front, and back. The clock at the front will appear to run faster than the clock at the tail due to the doppler shift of light travelling between the two clocks. And since an accelerating spaceship is the same thing as earth&amp;rsquo;s gravity (equivalence principle), we can say that blocks separated by some height H will run at different speeds! The further one runs faster than the one closer to the gravitational source. Hence, gravitational time dilation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Light gains energy as it falls towards earth, and loses some as it leaves. This is true due to the conservation of energy!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/okay-books/" term="Okay Books" label="Okay Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">The Lifecycle of Software Objects</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202207softwarelifecycle/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202207softwarelifecycle/</id>
            <updated>2022-07-25T07:30:36&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2022-07-24T01:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">A short story about what our digital future might hold. We follow an ex-zoo keeper turned digital pet trainer after the zoo she worked at closed down. The world her digi-pet grew up in becomes threatened, and we see the great lengths she&amp;rsquo;ll go, along with a small community of like-minded fanatics, to give these digital humanoids a better future.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A short story about what our digital future might hold. We follow an ex-zoo keeper turned digital pet trainer after the zoo she worked at closed down. The world her digi-pet grew up in becomes threatened, and we see the great lengths she&amp;rsquo;ll go, along with a small community of like-minded fanatics, to give these digital humanoids a better future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/poor-books/" term="Poor Books" label="Poor Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">The Sovereign Individual</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202207sovereignindividual/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202207sovereignindividual/</id>
            <updated>2022-07-17T11:52:58&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2022-07-17T01:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">I only skimmed this book, read about 1/3 of the content, but felt I got the gist. The authors outline what they think a future without government power will look like, as power shifts to individuals in the information age.
Individuals will be able to insulate themselves from governments in ways previously impossible.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I only skimmed this book, read about 1/3 of the content, but felt I got the gist. The authors outline what they think a future without government power will look like, as power shifts to individuals in the information age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Individuals will be able to insulate themselves from governments in ways previously impossible. Work, communications, assets, and banking systems will be fully digital, allowing life to move wherever the individual desires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this newfound autonomy, people will be free to choose their nationality, as it is the author&amp;rsquo;s belief that nations will offer nationality as a service to attract sovereign individuals. Essentially, the book describes a world where governments have fallen out of power, due to tax evasion and social uprisings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;new information technology - the fact that it transcends the tyranny of place. The new technology creates for the first time an infinite, nonterrestrial realm for economic activity. It opens an option to explore the new frontiers of the cybereconomy, to &amp;lsquo;think globally and act globally&amp;rsquo;.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, 1/5 - I would not recommend this book.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/worst-books/" term="Worst Books" label="Worst Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">The Bond King</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202207bondking/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202207bondking/</id>
            <updated>2022-07-07T17:05:12&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2022-07-07T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">An interesting book for financial buffs. It reviews the origin story of active bond trading and goes through some of the details Pimco used to &amp;ldquo;generate alpha&amp;rdquo;.
Some of the nifty tricks include:
 buying future contracts to meet risk requirements and then investing $ in short term bonds before the contract requires, betting on future volatility of the markets (upper and lower bounds), trading securities with itself (in differing accounts) to minimize fees, pricing bonds more aggressively than the market to front-load performance within a fund, and most generally, taking bets that future interest rates would be different from what &amp;ldquo;the market&amp;rdquo; was expecting.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;An interesting book for financial buffs. It reviews the origin story of active bond trading and goes through some of the details Pimco used to &amp;ldquo;generate alpha&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the nifty tricks include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;buying future contracts to meet risk requirements and then investing $ in short term bonds before the contract requires,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;betting on future volatility of the markets (upper and lower bounds),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;trading securities with itself (in differing accounts) to minimize fees,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pricing bonds more aggressively than the market to front-load performance within a fund,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and most generally, taking bets that future interest rates would be different from what &amp;ldquo;the market&amp;rdquo; was expecting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall it was an interesting read, but some parts were a little slow, and of course, you have to have an interest in bonds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/okay-books/" term="Okay Books" label="Okay Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">Homo Deus</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202206homodeus/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202206homodeus/</id>
            <updated>2022-07-22T11:58:30&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2022-06-28T01:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">Tid-bits of history sprinkled throughout a synopsis of where humanity is heading.
Parts of the story were interesting, as history often is, but the general arc of the book took too long, and many of the ideas have been subject to too many recent podcasts that I tended to lose interest.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Tid-bits of history sprinkled throughout a synopsis of where humanity is heading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parts of the story were interesting, as history often is, but the general arc of the book took too long, and many of the ideas have been subject to too many recent podcasts that I tended to lose interest. On the flip side, for anyone who&amp;rsquo;s not come across these ideas before (i.e., do we have free will, what do humans value, the &amp;ldquo;story&amp;rdquo; that is currency, the internet of things, etc.), I&amp;rsquo;d suggest giving this book a read. For others, I&amp;rsquo;d recommend passing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-of-my-highlighted-points-include&#34;&gt;Some of my highlighted points include:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Some 2,300 years ago, Epicurus warned his disciples that immoderate pursuit of pleasure is likely to make them miserable rather than happy.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The paradox of historical knowledge is that if the information does not change behaviour, it is useless; but if it does change behaviour, it is quickly irrelevant.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lawns were invented to display wealth as they are meaningless wastes of land that require many resources to remain pretty (thanks France!).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Anyone who has ever dealt with the tax authorities, the educational system or any complex bureaucracy knows that the truth hardly matters. What&amp;rsquo;s written on your form is far more important.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Religion is a deal, whereas spirituality is a journey.&amp;rdquo; And a dangerous one at that for religious, political, and business leaders trying to keep their human resources in order.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ending a painful experience with minor pain, or even pleasure distorts our remembered history of the event. Children&amp;rsquo;s dentists know this well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Today, having power means knowing what to ignore.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our future is increasingly one of &amp;ldquo;techo-humanism&amp;rdquo; whereby technology allows us to mediate our human desires, emotions and feelings. Humanism holds &amp;ldquo;free will&amp;rdquo; as the most important thing in the world, which complicates this newfound power. To rescue our dilemma of how to wield such power, we are moving away from a worldview that sanctifies desires/experiences, towards a new religion of &amp;ldquo;Dataism&amp;rdquo; - the worship of the creation, distribution, and utilization of data, to make the world a better place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through the lense of Dataism, democracy beat communism by being a distributed processing system, instead of centralized. As the 21&amp;rsquo;st century unfolds, the best systems for governing humans will be the one that best uses the immense amount of data our society can produce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/okay-books/" term="Okay Books" label="Okay Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">The Great Depression</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202206greatdepression/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202206greatdepression/</id>
            <updated>2022-06-27T21:26:39&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2022-06-27T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">Going through a recession will never be quite the same again after reading this diary. Strange to see how many similarities exist in stock markets in such a different setting in time.
Humans love to speculate, and are quick to become greedy when the party is pumping.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Going through a recession will never be quite the same again after reading this diary. Strange to see how many similarities exist in stock markets in such a different setting in time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humans love to speculate, and are quick to become greedy when the party is pumping. Those who like to party a little too hardy, leveraging their gains as collateral to buy more stock on margin, are almost always wiped out sooner or later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This diary has many such stories, and describes the news of the day as if it was yesterday. An interesting way to hear about life in the 1930&amp;rsquo;s and the start of WW2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/okay-books/" term="Okay Books" label="Okay Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">The Quick Fix</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202206quickfix/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202206quickfix/</id>
            <updated>2022-06-29T16:06:08&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2022-06-18T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">A well researched review of the necessary skepticism established Psychology fads need. Chapters focusing on the implicit bias test, grit, the power of self-esteem, power posing, prime world (everything we do is the result of previous priming sensory input), fears over &amp;ldquo;superpredators&amp;rdquo;, and the ability for war veteran&amp;rsquo;s to overcome PTSD with mental training.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A well researched review of the necessary skepticism established Psychology fads need. Chapters focusing on the implicit bias test, grit, the power of self-esteem, power posing, prime world (everything we do is the result of previous priming sensory input), fears over &amp;ldquo;superpredators&amp;rdquo;, and the ability for war veteran&amp;rsquo;s to overcome PTSD with mental training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all cases, simple solutions (i.e., quick fixes), would enter a cycle of over-claiming, oversimplifying, and on the back of growing momentum, minimal skepticism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only after large (sometimes massive) amounts of time and money had been spent was there enough review literature to cast doubts on the runaway fads. These fads caused more harm than good as money and time were redirected away from meaningful changes, such as better policy focused on tackling the root problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What was needed was rigorous science, pilot programs, and of course, a health dose of skepticism; which was all too easy to forget when the storytelling of these ideas fit so well into existing mental models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The future is bright however, as the field of Psychology has begun to reconcile with its replication crises and implement more statistical rigor. Finally, nudging does look to have promising effects when implemented modestly; but be careful to not over subscribe nudges as a quick fix. Tackling root problems are never as simple as they seem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/" term="Good Books" label="Good Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">The Glass Castle</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202205glasscastle/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202205glasscastle/</id>
            <updated>2022-05-28T22:48:53&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2022-05-28T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">A memoir of an extraordinary childhood; one where quotes like &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;d gotten pretty good at shooting the revolver by the time I was 4&amp;rdquo; is but the tip of the iceberg. Parents who disliked &amp;ldquo;the system&amp;rdquo;, and thought their misfortunes were adventures to be had.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A memoir of an extraordinary childhood; one where quotes like &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;d gotten pretty good at shooting the revolver by the time I was 4&amp;rdquo; is but the tip of the iceberg. Parents who disliked &amp;ldquo;the system&amp;rdquo;, and thought their misfortunes were adventures to be had. Hard times were simply hard lessons, but not worth fussing over. A true look behind the curtain at some of America&amp;rsquo;s forgotten people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/" term="Good Books" label="Good Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">Papillon</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202205papillon/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202205papillon/</id>
            <updated>2022-05-21T00:43:22&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2022-05-20T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">A wild ride through the early-mid 20th century Euro-America prison systems. Our autobiographical story is piloted by a Frenchman, who&amp;rsquo;s candour is contagious, often to his benefit, but at crucial moments, to his demise. Super fun to read; it&amp;rsquo;s a fantastical life story to be sure.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A wild ride through the early-mid 20th century Euro-America prison systems. Our autobiographical story is piloted by a Frenchman, who&amp;rsquo;s candour is contagious, often to his benefit, but at crucial moments, to his demise. Super fun to read; it&amp;rsquo;s a fantastical life story to be sure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/" term="Good Books" label="Good Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">Six Easy Pieces</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202205sixezpieces/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202205sixezpieces/</id>
            <updated>2022-07-22T11:26:02&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2022-05-02T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">Parts were good, but overall, a lot has changed in ~60 years to make this book more of a historical piece than a superb physics text.
Bookmarked ideas  As molecules evaporate, they are leaving with more energy than the average motion of the liquid they depart.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Parts were good, but overall, a lot has changed in ~60 years to make this book more of a historical piece than a superb physics text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;bookmarked-ideas&#34;&gt;Bookmarked ideas&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As molecules evaporate, they are leaving with more energy than the average motion of the liquid they depart. Conversely, when vapour from the air joins a liquid, there is a sudden great attraction as the molecule approaches the surface, resulting in energy added. Therefore, evaporation is the loss of heat, and consensation is the the generation of some back. When these are net equal, there is no heat exchange. However, this is a nifty thing to know when cooling hot liquids. i.e., blow on hot soup.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Carbon attracts oxygen (C-O) much more than O-O or C-C. So much so, that when they come together, they snap together with such force that excess energy is distributed to their surroundings. This of course is burning, and the sensation of heat. In certain circumstances, the excess energy is given off more than molecular motion of hot gas. The energy is so great, that it &lt;em&gt;generates light&lt;/em&gt;. This is how one gets flames!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;What keeps electrons from simply falling in[to the nucleus]? This principle: If they were in the nucleus, we would know their position precisely, and the uncertainty principle would then require that they have a very large (but uncertain) momentum (and therefore energy). With this energy, they&amp;rsquo;d break away from the nucleus. They make a compromise: they leave themselves a little room for this uncertainty and then jiggle with a certain amount of minimum motion in accordance with this rule.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;cavendishs-experiment-aka-the-weighing-of-the-earth&#34;&gt;Cavendish&amp;rsquo;s experiment (aka, the weighing of the earth)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;If there is a force between any pair of objects, we ought to be able to measure the force between our own objects&amp;hellip; It was first measured by Cavendish&amp;hellip; demonstrating the direct force between two large, fixed balls of lead and two smaller balls of lead on the ends of an arm supported by a very fine fiber, called a torsion fiber. By measuring how much the fiber gets twisted, once can measure the strength of the force, verify that it is inversely proportional to the square of the distance, and determine how strong it is. Thus, one may accurately determine the coefficient G in our gravitational force equation. By knowing G from this experiement, and by knowing how strongly the earth attracts, we indirectly learned the mass of the earth!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was experiments like this that, and the simplicity of the mathematics that garnered peoples interest in science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/okay-books/" term="Okay Books" label="Okay Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">Dopamine Nation</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202204dopaminenation/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202204dopaminenation/</id>
            <updated>2022-07-21T21:06:45&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2022-04-28T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">An insightful perspective on our society today, the author weaves stories of addiction throughout to illustrate how we&amp;rsquo;re easily prone to it, and how we might pull ourselves out.
The most insightful lesson (for me) was that pain is in fact a pleasurable time-sink, due to the pleasure-pain balance our bodies strive for.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;An insightful perspective on our society today, the author weaves stories of addiction throughout to illustrate how we&amp;rsquo;re easily prone to it, and how we might pull ourselves out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most insightful lesson (for me) was that pain is in fact a pleasurable time-sink, due to the pleasure-pain balance our bodies strive for. Post pain, we are often flooded with euphoric hormones to compensate. Beware of becoming addicted to pain, but, when used correctly, it is a low risk powerful stimulant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples can include: cold water sessions (I&amp;rsquo;d argue hot ones too), physical activity, caloric restriction (careful for adverse health effects), and learning something new. Ideally, we could do one thing everyday that was &amp;ldquo;painful&amp;rdquo; to help keep our pleasure-pain scale in balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Just as pain is the price we play for pleasure, so too is pleasure our reward for pain&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll add that in our high-speed dopamine-saturated society, slow activities like yoga, meditation, and aimless mind wandering can feel painful if you&amp;rsquo;re addicted to delivering results (which itself is an addiction to pain mechanism). Over time, leaning into these activities will deliver healthier pleasure too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything in moderation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-quotes&#34;&gt;Other quotes:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;In humans, high levels of physical activity in junior high, high school, and early adulthood predict lower levels of drug use. Exercise has also been shown to help those already addicted to stop or cut back.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Pain to treat pain. Anxiety to treat anxiety. This approach is counterintuitive, and exactly opposite to what we&amp;rsquo;ve been taught over the last 150 years about how to manage disease, distress, and discomfort.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The relentless pursuit of pleasure (and avoidance of pain) leads to pain.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Recovery begins with abstinence.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Abstinence resets the brain&amp;rsquo;s reward pathway and with it our capacity to take joy in simpler pleasures.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Self-binding creates literal and metacognitive space between desire and consumption, a modern necessity in our dopamine-overloaded world.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Medications can restore homeostasis, but consider what we lose by medicating away our pain.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pressing on the pain side resets our balance to the side of pleasure.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Beware of getting addicted to pain.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Radical honesty promotes awareness, enhances intimacy, and fosters a plenty mindset.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Prosocial shame&amp;rdquo; (i.e., feeling shame for transgressive behaviours where appropriate) affirms that we belong to the human tribe.&lt;/em&gt; [Not to be confused with destructive shame, which is swept under the rug, and often a negative feedback loop unto itself.]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Instead of running away from the world, we can find escape by immersing ourselves in it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/best-books/" term="Best Books" label="Best Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">Stolen Focus</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202204stolenfocus/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202204stolenfocus/</id>
            <updated>2022-07-22T13:45:06&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2022-04-20T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">A must read for those itching to learn why they have a love hate relationship with technology. All ideas are presented alongside their empirical findings, including where the scientific community has a consensus, and where it does not.
Many of these ideas are present in other self help books, like: sleep more, eat well, work less, and make time for slowness (yoga, meditation, nature walks without audio) and play.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A must read for those itching to learn why they have a love hate relationship with technology. All ideas are presented alongside their empirical findings, including where the scientific community has a consensus, and where it does not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of these ideas are present in other self help books, like: sleep more, eat well, work less, and make time for slowness (yoga, meditation, nature walks without audio) and play. But the studies and storytelling in this book make it worthwhile nonetheless for those who are already familiar with this list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Life begins at the edge of your comfort zone&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;on-relating-to-others&#34;&gt;On relating to others:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s worth thinking deeply about how other people live and how their minds work. They have complex inner lives, just like you.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found this idea particularly interesting. How there is research that the more fiction novels you read, the better you are (on average) at reading other people&amp;rsquo;s emotions (but not for nonfiction). This improvement in our ability to empathize was also found in children who consumed more long-format TV series, or movies. But not shorter shows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This helps explain why our societies are becoming ever more divided. Our media is continuing to become compressed, from TV series, to YouTube, down to Tik Tok. It&amp;rsquo;s no wonder people have less empathy for each other than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;technology-has-overrun-us&#34;&gt;Technology has overrun us:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It used to be that technology was created to be an extension of us. That is what a paintbrush is, or a musical instrument. In a way, so too are light bulbs (light to be together, or engage with ___), automobiles (moving us faster from A to B), or the internet (connecting us to those far away).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But our internet giants have discovered their recommendation systems can keep us scrolling forever. Keeping us engaged with content that we don&amp;rsquo;t realize is influencing us. Making us less empathetic (see section above). Causing us to move faster. Multitask more. All in the name of engagement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keeping people in the digital realms is good for business. But it&amp;rsquo;s making us less human. I&amp;rsquo;d argue, more so than any previous innovation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;basic-takeaways&#34;&gt;Basic takeaways:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slow down, do one thing at a time, sleep more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove noise from your environment. (don&amp;rsquo;t live within 50 meters of a major road!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mind wander more. Especially in a forest.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find your flow states.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduce 4 day work weeks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let kids run around, explore, and think for themselves.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;some-bookmarked-ideas&#34;&gt;Some Bookmarked ideas&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yoga, meditation, walking in the forest, etc. are incredible practices to train your attention and focus. &amp;ldquo;Slowness nurtures attention, and speed shatters it&amp;rdquo;.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;I realized that my desire to absorb a tsunami of information without losing my ability to focus was like my desire to eat at McDonald&amp;rsquo;s every day and stay trim - an impossible dream.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;There&amp;rsquo;s broad scientific evidence that if you are sitting in a noisy room, your ability to pay attention deteriorates, and your work gets worse&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;We often seek relief from distraction by crashing (say in front of a TV). But if you only break away from distraction into rest - if you don&amp;rsquo;t replace it with a positive goal, you are striving toward - you will always be pulled back to distraction sooner or later. &lt;strong&gt;The more powerful path out of distraction is to find your flow&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;When people are kept awake, one of the first things to go is their ability to focus.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mind wandering is a different form of attention - and a necessary one.&amp;rdquo;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;In situations of low stress and safety, mind-wandering will be a gift, a pleasure, a creative force. In situations of high stress or danger, mind-wandering will be a torment.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;In Canada, a study found that people who lived within 50 meters of a major road were 15 percent more likely to develop dementia than people who did not.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/" term="Good Books" label="Good Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">The Bomber Mafia</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202204bombermafia/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202204bombermafia/</id>
            <updated>2022-05-09T04:31:16&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2022-04-17T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">A masterclass in storytelling. I found it hard to put this book down from start to finish. As the title says, this book follows the evolution of America&amp;rsquo;s bomber mafia, a group of pilots who helped create the Air Force. We learn about their military decisions, shortcomings, success, and the ending of WW2.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A masterclass in storytelling. I found it hard to put this book down from start to finish. As the title says, this book follows the evolution of America&amp;rsquo;s bomber mafia, a group of pilots who helped create the Air Force. We learn about their military decisions, shortcomings, success, and the ending of WW2. An interesting story told by one of the greatest storytellers of our time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/best-books/" term="Best Books" label="Best Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">There There</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202204therethere/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202204therethere/</id>
            <updated>2022-05-09T04:26:57&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2022-04-14T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">Some beautifully written passages that were thought provoking in the way good poetry often is; however the book overall wasn&amp;rsquo;t as captivating of a story as I&amp;rsquo;d hoped.
Unique storytelling in how the chapters were constructed, but I found it hard to build up empathy for any one character, and found myself loosing steam in the middle.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Some beautifully written passages that were thought provoking in the way good poetry often is; however the book overall wasn&amp;rsquo;t as captivating of a story as I&amp;rsquo;d hoped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unique storytelling in how the chapters were constructed, but I found it hard to build up empathy for any one character, and found myself loosing steam in the middle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conclusion however was worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/okay-books/" term="Okay Books" label="Okay Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">The Power of Now</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202203powerofnow/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202203powerofnow/</id>
            <updated>2022-05-09T04:25:35&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2022-03-14T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">A book about spirituality accessed by focusing your attention on the present. Written in the late 90&amp;rsquo;s, this book seems ahead of its time regarding the power of mindfulness. However, the author extends the benefits of mindfulness into the mystical realm of God, which might resonate with some folks, but harder for an atheist (like me) to digest.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A book about spirituality accessed by focusing your attention on the present. Written in the late 90&amp;rsquo;s, this book seems ahead of its time regarding the power of mindfulness. However, the author extends the benefits of mindfulness into the mystical realm of God, which might resonate with some folks, but harder for an atheist (like me) to digest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/okay-books/" term="Okay Books" label="Okay Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">Less Is More</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202202lessismore/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202202lessismore/</id>
            <updated>2022-05-09T04:24:53&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2022-02-24T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">&amp;ldquo;How degrowth will save the world&amp;rdquo;. This book describes how we might move away from a constantly growing economy, to one that is decelerating, without harming the people who live in it, and in fact, improving their lives along the way.
To get us there, the &amp;ldquo;upper class 1%&amp;rdquo; will suffer; they won&amp;rsquo;t be able to consume at the current multiplier they enjoy.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;How degrowth will save the world&amp;rdquo;. This book describes how we might move away from a constantly growing economy, to one that is decelerating, without harming the people who live in it, and in fact, improving their lives along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get us there, the &amp;ldquo;upper class 1%&amp;rdquo; will suffer; they won&amp;rsquo;t be able to consume at the current multiplier they enjoy. But they too will benefit from a healthier way of life, and a society that is more inclusive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main benefactor will be our planet, and our ancestors, who&amp;rsquo;ll inherit a world that narrowly escaped an ecological disaster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A possible path forward would be the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;end planned obsolences (stop creating purposefully fragile objects),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cut advertising (stop nudging people to buy things they don&amp;rsquo;t need),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;shift from ownership to usership,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;end food waster, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;scale down ecologically destructive industries (and have the remaining industries scale down working hours to make room for the newly unemployed).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My gripe with this book is that the author calls on capitalism as the culprit. IMO, the culprit is poorly insulated governments who aren&amp;rsquo;t able to enact resilient policies that&amp;rsquo;d make this degrowth possible. We need better political infrastructure, not an end to capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/" term="Good Books" label="Good Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">Educated</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202202educated/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202202educated/</id>
            <updated>2022-05-09T04:24:27&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2022-02-04T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">A gripping story of being raised without traditional education, and the impact that had on Tara as she discovers a world beyond her childhood.
I found this book hard to put down. I highly recommend it to anyone looking for a non-fiction story that&amp;rsquo;ll transport you to another world.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A gripping story of being raised without traditional education, and the impact that had on Tara as she discovers a world beyond her childhood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found this book hard to put down. I highly recommend it to anyone looking for a non-fiction story that&amp;rsquo;ll transport you to another world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/best-books/" term="Best Books" label="Best Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">Noise: A flaw in Human Judgment</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202110noise/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202110noise/</id>
            <updated>2022-05-01T23:58:05&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2021-10-07T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">This book opened my eyes to the differences between bias and noise, and how they are equally proportional to disrupting our desired outcome. That is to say, imagine missing a target by some random &amp;ldquo;noisy&amp;rdquo; amount, which widens the bell curve of outcomes.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This book opened my eyes to the differences between bias and noise, and how they are equally proportional to disrupting our desired outcome. That is to say, imagine missing a target by some random &amp;ldquo;noisy&amp;rdquo; amount, which widens the bell curve of outcomes. The distance, on average, away from the target result would be just as bad as an equal error magnitude in bias. The only difference being that the bias is easier to see, because it is clustering away from the target. Thus, bias is often the focus in reducing error for our desired outcomes, when really, it should be considered equally with noise, if our goal is error reduction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simple techniques for reducing error through noise include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a noise audit,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;collecting multiple opinions (even yourself multiple times), without priming the answer of individuals, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;regularly measuring noise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;three-principles-of-decision-hygiene&#34;&gt;Three Principles of Decision Hygiene&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Resist premature intuitions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Think like a statistician.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Accuracy, not individual expression.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See a quick summary of these ideas &lt;a href=&#34;https://productcoalition.com/three-principles-for-making-better-decisions-cbcb3bbea956&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, or review the book for greater detail!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/best-books/" term="Best Books" label="Best Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">Braiding Sweetgrass</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202107braidingsweetgrass/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202107braidingsweetgrass/</id>
            <updated>2022-05-01T23:42:44&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2021-07-22T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">Note: I only read ~50% of this book. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t captivated by the content my first time through, which might be why I only rated this a 3/5. I should like to try again one day, as I know many people who say this is one of their favourite books.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Note: I only read ~50% of this book. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t captivated by the content my first time through, which might be why I only rated this a 3/5. I should like to try again one day, as I know many people who say this is one of their favourite books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stories of indigenous wisdom, woven with scientific thinking, told in a North American setting. Many beautiful lessons to be had here, like how our language shapes our relationship with the environment. For example, the personification of nature in indigenous tongues, and the naturefication of human actions is indicative of their relationship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other lessons include regenerative farming techniques, deep respect for the land and ecosystem you depend on, spending time in nature, and the mystery of pecan trees who drop all their nuts at the same time as if in contact with one another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/okay-books/" term="Okay Books" label="Okay Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">Physics of the Impossible</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202106physicsimpossible/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202106physicsimpossible/</id>
            <updated>2022-04-30T00:36:30&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2021-05-19T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">A physics book unlike any other I&amp;rsquo;ve read. Reality is distorted by the mind-bending possibilities of physics that are beyond our reach. Sometimes, the physics has been proven, but we&amp;rsquo;re missing technological advances necessary to bring it to life, other times, it&amp;rsquo;s physics that might truly be impossible.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A physics book unlike any other I&amp;rsquo;ve read. Reality is distorted by the mind-bending possibilities of physics that are beyond our reach. Sometimes, the physics has been proven, but we&amp;rsquo;re missing technological advances necessary to bring it to life, other times, it&amp;rsquo;s physics that might truly be impossible. In either case, the idea&amp;rsquo;s themselves are delightful to consume. Some minds are truly special.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;bookmarked-ideas&#34;&gt;Bookmarked ideas&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A tidal wave of commercial applications could be set off if we create room-temperature superconductors. Magnetic fields a million times stronger than that of the earth could become commonplace.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Levitation for zero friction movement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since water is a diamagnet, it too can levitate in the presence of a powerful magnetic field. Scientists have levitated small animals, like frogs, for example.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Negative energy is real! The Casimir effect - the pressure felt by two parallel (neutral) plates in a vacuum by &amp;ldquo;virtual particles&amp;rdquo;. When these plates are brought close together, you can extract energy out of the system&amp;rsquo;s mutual attraction. Predicted in 1933, and proven in 1948, the attractive force was precisely measured in 1996 to be miniscule, 1/30,000 the weight of an ant.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are exotic solutions to relativity whereby stable wormholes can be created that transport you to other universes, or transversable wormholes where you can pass back and forth freely. The problem with these exotic solutions is that they require a fabulous amount of positive and negative matter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-founder-of-antimatter-tldr&#34;&gt;The founder of antimatter (TL;DR)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A longer version of this can be found in the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul Dirac noticed that Schrdinger&amp;rsquo;s equations failed to work with the theory of relativity. In 1928, he proposed a radical reformulation (now called Dirac&amp;rsquo;s equation) that satisfied both, using a mathematical object called spinors. Additionally, these new equations showed that E = mc^2 no longer holds. Rather, it is E = +/- mc^2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The implications of this mathematics is considered one of the greatest triumphs in theoretical physics. Not only did this new formulation predict anti-matter, which was then discovered a few years &lt;em&gt;later&lt;/em&gt;, it also provided a theoretical justification for the fundamental phenomenon of spin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/best-books/" term="Best Books" label="Best Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">Delivering Happiness</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202105deliveringhappiness/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202105deliveringhappiness/</id>
            <updated>2022-04-29T23:22:06&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2021-05-03T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">A dot-com winner, then loser, then back to the top story. Lots of building-a-business advice from a very unique person. A lot of his focus is on the customer, and internal culture. Sorta changed my perception of what a &amp;ldquo;head of culture&amp;rdquo; can even do at a company.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A dot-com winner, then loser, then back to the top story. Lots of building-a-business advice from a very unique person. A lot of his focus is on the customer, and internal culture. Sorta changed my perception of what a &amp;ldquo;head of culture&amp;rdquo; can even do at a company. Namely, they can facilitate an environment to help people connect, but that could be very different for each person, and at the end of the day, culture is what is &lt;em&gt;felt&lt;/em&gt; by each person. The collective average being that which is its core, but truly, it&amp;rsquo;s just a feeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;bookmarked-ideas&#34;&gt;Bookmarked ideas&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Share what you&amp;rsquo;ve learned with others.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Look for opportunities beyond just the game you sat down to play. You never know who you&amp;rsquo;re going to meet, including new friends for life or new business contacts.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Have fun. The game is a lot more enjoyable when you&amp;rsquo;re trying to do more than just make money.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;[Creating a] culture book is not about the book&amp;hellip; it&amp;rsquo;s about the culture.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;What&amp;rsquo;s the best way to build a brand for the long term? In a word: culture. At Zappos, our belief is that if you get the culture right, most of the other stuff - customer service, long-term brand, etc. will happen naturally&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/" term="Good Books" label="Good Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">Shoe Dog</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202103shoedog/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202103shoedog/</id>
            <updated>2022-04-29T23:22:26&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2021-03-16T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">A novel that&amp;rsquo;ll transport you back to a decade quite unlike today. Not only was there no Nike, there wasn&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;athleisure&amp;rdquo; or jogging for fun. The story on it&amp;rsquo;s own is hard to put down, but the way it&amp;rsquo;s told makes this a truly joyful read.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A novel that&amp;rsquo;ll transport you back to a decade quite unlike today. Not only was there no Nike, there wasn&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;athleisure&amp;rdquo; or jogging for fun. The story on it&amp;rsquo;s own is hard to put down, but the way it&amp;rsquo;s told makes this a truly joyful read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;bookmarked-ideas&#34;&gt;Bookmarked ideas&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Don&amp;rsquo;t tell people how to do things, tell them what to do and let them surprise you with their results.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;[To help young entrepreneurs,] I&amp;rsquo;d tell them to hit pause, think long and hard about how they want to spend their time, and with whom they want to spend it for the next forty years. I&amp;rsquo;d tell men and women in their mid twenties not to settle for a job or a profession or even a career. Seek a calling. Even if you don&amp;rsquo;t know what that means, seek it. If you&amp;rsquo;re following your calling, the fatigue will be easier to bear, the disappointment will be fuel, the highs will be like nothing you&amp;rsquo;ve ever felt.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/best-books/" term="Best Books" label="Best Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">Atomic Habits</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202101atomichabits/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202101atomichabits/</id>
            <updated>2022-04-29T22:49:53&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2021-01-04T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">Very engaging book. In addition to learning about the power of habits, you&amp;rsquo;ll also learn to recognize what parts of your life are good/bad habits and how to build/break them. It&amp;rsquo;s a solid framework for everyone to understand, regardless of your goals. Best of all, this book keeps you engaged from chapter 1 with well told anecdotes and analogies.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Very engaging book. In addition to learning about the power of habits, you&amp;rsquo;ll also learn to recognize what parts of your life are good/bad habits and how to build/break them. It&amp;rsquo;s a solid framework for everyone to understand, regardless of your goals. Best of all, this book keeps you engaged from chapter 1 with well told anecdotes and analogies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-takeaways&#34;&gt;My takeaways:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small changes often appear to make no difference, until you&amp;rsquo;ve crossed some critical threshold. A hallmark feature of compounding gains. You need to be patient.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To improve your results, focus on your system, not the goals themselves.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To improve your system, focus on your identity. You become your habits. Therefore, changing your habits requires you to change your identity. Are you someone who wants to do X, or are you someone who is doing X?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any habit can be broken down into a 4-step feedback loop: que, craving, response, and reward. To effectively change behaviour, simply target one of the 4 parts of the feedback loop: i) make it obvious; ii) make it attractive; iii) make it easy; iv) make it satisfying.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Point &amp;amp; call the action to make it clear what is happening &amp;amp; its consequences. I.e., I am opening a new tab and typing &amp;ldquo;r&amp;rdquo; out of habit, this will take me to reddit if I press enter where I&amp;rsquo;ll have some fun but likely spend too much time and regret having come in the first place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use &lt;strong&gt;habit stacking&lt;/strong&gt; to chain new habits to existing ones. i.e., After I close my laptop for the day, I&amp;rsquo;ll immediately do 20 minutes of language homework.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a complete list of habit strategies, checkout the &lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/jamesclear/Atomic+Habits/Habits+Cheat+Sheet.pdf&#34;&gt;Atomic Habits cheat sheet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;habits-work-best-applied-to-your-strengths&#34;&gt;Habits work best applied to your strengths:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your strengths are a cross between your genetics &amp;amp; your interests. What doesn&amp;rsquo;t feel like work to you? What are you naturally predisposed to being great at?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, I think I&amp;rsquo;m great at communicating a goal to a team, organizing the team&amp;rsquo;s energy and focus to tackle the problem quickly. Allowing for new thoughts to form, connecting dots, and listening to others while creating a space that allows others to speak up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a behaviour strength, which I&amp;rsquo;ve slowly come to learn about the more teamwork I&amp;rsquo;ve done. A personality test could have helped me uncover it too, but in general, it&amp;rsquo;s always good to be doing some &amp;ldquo;exploring&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, when you&amp;rsquo;ve found a regime that fits you well, you can &amp;ldquo;exploit&amp;rdquo; it, for accelerated gains compared to your peers. This process is known as &amp;ldquo;explore vs. exploit&amp;rdquo;. You should always have a bit of both in your life; likely more explore while your young, and exploit once you&amp;rsquo;ve found your groove.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/best-books/" term="Best Books" label="Best Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">How I Invest My Money</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202012investmoney/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202012investmoney/</id>
            <updated>2022-04-29T23:22:43&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2020-12-27T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">A collection of financial industry darlings speak openly about how they invest their money. Often aligning with the products they&amp;rsquo;ve worked on, but not always. It&amp;rsquo;d be nice to have more books openly discuss this topic to showcase the complexities of investing.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A collection of financial industry darlings speak openly about how they invest their money. Often aligning with the products they&amp;rsquo;ve worked on, but not always. It&amp;rsquo;d be nice to have more books openly discuss this topic to showcase the complexities of investing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;bookmarked-ideas&#34;&gt;Bookmarked ideas&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;EquityZen is an interesting platform that allows for pre-IPO shares to be traded.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;your money is a wonderful servant and a terrible master&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/okay-books/" term="Okay Books" label="Okay Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">The Almanack of Naval Ravikant</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202012almanack/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202012almanack/</id>
            <updated>2022-04-29T22:50:46&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2020-12-22T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">A collection of Naval Ravikant&amp;rsquo;s tweetstorms, discussions, and ideas woven into a digestible ebook. The ideas focus on wealth on happiness.
Some of my favourite ideas:
Tweetstorm about wealth creation:  &amp;ldquo;Seek wealth, not money or status. Wealth is having assets that earn while you sleep.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A collection of Naval Ravikant&amp;rsquo;s tweetstorms, discussions, and ideas woven into a digestible &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.navalmanack.com/&#34;&gt;ebook&lt;/a&gt;. The ideas focus on wealth on happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of my favourite ideas:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tweetstorm-about-wealth-creation&#34;&gt;Tweetstorm about wealth creation:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Seek wealth, not money or status. Wealth is having assets that earn while you sleep. Money is how we transfer time and wealth. Status is your place in the social hierarchy&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understand ethical wealth creation is possible. If you secretly despise wealth, it will elude you&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ignore ppl playing status games. They gain status by attacking ppl playing wealth creation games&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;re not going to get rich renting out your time. You must own equity&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will get rich by giving society what it wants but does not yet know how to get. At scale&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pick an industry where you can play long-term games with long-term ppl&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The internet has massively broadened the possible space of careers. Most ppl haven&amp;rsquo;t figured this out yet&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Play iterated games. All returns in life, whether in wealth, relationships, or knowledge, from compound interest&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pick your business partners with high intelligence, energy, and, above all, integrity&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t partner with cynics and pessimists. Their beliefs are self-fulfilling&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn to sell. Learn to build. If you can do both, you will be unstoppable&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arm yourself with specific knowledge, accountability, and leverage&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specific knowledge is knowledge you cannot be trained for, found by pursuing your genuine curiosity and passion rather than whatever is hot right now&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building specific knowledge will feel like play to you, but look like work to others&amp;hellip; and is taught through apprenticeships, not school&amp;hellip; often highly technical or creative, it cannot be outsourced or automated&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Embrace accountability, and take business risks under your own name. Society will reward you with responsibility, equity, and leverage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunes require leverage. Business leverage comes from capital, people, and products with no marginal cost of replication (code &amp;amp; media). Code and media are permissionless leverage. They&amp;rsquo;re the leverage behind the newly rich. You can create software and media that works for you while you sleep&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Avoid business magazines and business classes. Study microeconomics, game theory, psychology, persuasion, ethics, math and computers&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading is faster than listening. Doing is faster than watching&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should be too busy to &amp;ldquo;do coffee&amp;rdquo; while still keeping an uncluttered calendar&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Set and enforce an aspirational personal hourly rate. If fixing a problem will save less than your hourly rate, ignore it. If outsourcing a task will cost less than your hourly rate, outsource it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Become the best in the world at what you do. Keep redefining what you do until this is true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you&amp;rsquo;re finally wealthy, you&amp;rsquo;ll realize it wasn&amp;rsquo;t what you were seeking in the first place. But that is for another day.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;find-a-position-of-leverage&#34;&gt;Find a position of leverage:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;the CEO job is really a financial job.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Capital scales very, very well. If you get good at managing capital, you can manage more and more capital much more easily than you can manage more and more people.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;the most democratic form [of leverage]&amp;hellip; is products with no marginal cost of replication. This includes books, media, movies, and code. Code is probably the most powerful form of permissionless leverage.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-get-lucky&#34;&gt;How to get lucky:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hope luck finds you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hustle until you stumble into it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prepare the mind and be sensitive to chances others miss.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Become the best at what you do. Refine what you do until this is true. Opportunity will seek you out. Luck becomes your destiny.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An extreme example of this last form of luck, as described in the book, is the following: &amp;ldquo;suppose you&amp;rsquo;re the best person in the world at deep-sea diving. You&amp;rsquo;re known to take dives no one else will dare attempt. By sheer luck, someone finds a sunken treasure they cannot get. Their luck has just become your luck, as they&amp;rsquo;re going to come to you.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;mental-models&#34;&gt;Mental models&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Simple heuristic: if you&amp;rsquo;re evenly split on a difficult decision, take the path more painful in the short term.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;wrapping-up&#34;&gt;Wrapping up&amp;hellip;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Learn to love to read&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Happiness is being satisfied with what you have&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And an incredibly long list of book recommendations that I&amp;rsquo;m working through slowly&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/" term="Good Books" label="Good Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">The Hard thing about Hard Things</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202012hardthings/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202012hardthings/</id>
            <updated>2022-04-29T22:50:51&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2020-11-12T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">A brutally honest take on the challenges faced when trying to build a company. A fantastic story of the compromises a CEO might face, and why being an entrepreneur is so hard.
4/5.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A brutally honest take on the challenges faced when trying to build a company. A fantastic story of the compromises a CEO might face, and why being an entrepreneur is so hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/" term="Good Books" label="Good Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">The Alchemist</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202010thealchemist/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202010thealchemist/</id>
            <updated>2022-04-29T22:50:42&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2020-10-26T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">A bit dated, this book remains a captivating story of the human condition. Seeking an outcome for fulfillment:
 &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s the possibility of having a dream come true that makes life interesting, he thought, as he looked again at the position of the sun, and hurried his pace.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A bit dated, this book remains a captivating story of the human condition. Seeking an outcome for fulfillment:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s the possibility of having a dream come true that makes life interesting, he thought, as he looked again at the position of the sun, and hurried his pace.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the story takes the reader through relatable ups-and-downs, occasional magic, and a satisfying ending.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/" term="Good Books" label="Good Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">Stamped From The Beginning</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202009stampedfromthebeginning/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202009stampedfromthebeginning/</id>
            <updated>2022-04-29T22:50:37&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2020-09-30T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">I agree with the book&amp;rsquo;s subtitle, this is definitely a mammoth overview of racist ideas in America. Starting with the racists ideas of colonial Europe that seeded the founding father, or white-religous-upperclassmen, as is more appropriate, up to Barack Obama, and some of the racist ideas he pondered aloud.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I agree with the book&amp;rsquo;s subtitle, this is definitely a mammoth overview of racist ideas in America. Starting with the racists ideas of colonial Europe that seeded the founding father, or white-religous-upperclassmen, as is more appropriate, up to Barack Obama, and some of the racist ideas he pondered aloud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to educate yourself on how poorly Black Americans have been treated by their peers and the policies in their society, look no further. It is a little long, but comes together quite nicely in the end. And it&amp;rsquo;s on Spotify as an audio book!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-key-takeaway&#34;&gt;My key takeaway&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, to talk of a person as being different from the rest of society because of something about their race/sex/gender/age/etc., rather than their environment, is wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I agree with the premise, and it is interesting to catch yourself being X-ist whenever you think thoughts upon a group. &lt;strong&gt;No individual should be stamped from the beginning&lt;/strong&gt;. And, as discussed by Malcom Gladwell in &lt;a href=&#34;https://cartar.github.io./books/talking2strangers/#my-favourite-takeaways&#34;&gt;Talking to Strangers&lt;/a&gt;, you SHOULD consider an individual&amp;rsquo;s environment. Think about how their environment has shaped them before concluding what is a reasonable thought, or conducting your behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-discussion&#34;&gt;A discussion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d like to start at the end. Ibram X. Kendi concludes with the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;There will come a time when principled anti-racists are in power, and then anti-racist policies become the law of the land, and then anti-racists ideas become the common sense of the people, and the anti-racists common sense of the people hold their anti-racists leaders and policies accountable.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wholeheartedly agree. And like to think many people in power have thought themselves anti-racists, but, to this book&amp;rsquo;s credit, not been. Ibram shows exactly why not:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Self-interest leads to racist policies, leads to racist ideas, which leads to ignorance and hate.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is it that people elected into positions of power, literally charged to be other-interested, fail so miserably? Ibram claims it is because power is inherently self-interested. Power cannot make decisions that are against its self-interest. Otherwise, the power is lost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is true. However, his solutions: i) to educate those without power to band together and grow in strength, and ii) that non-white-religous-upperclassmen who are self-interested should fight for anti-racisms because it is the precursor to humanity for all, are remist. Both of these solutions are principled to the same ideas that lead the founding fathers. Namely, together, we are strong enough to take power from the powerful and only then will there be peace for all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t get me wrong, I agree that &amp;ldquo;when we fight for humanity, we are fighting for ourselves.&amp;rdquo; And that we need principled anti-racists in power. And that we need to educate those without power the most of all. But the largest problem I see is not that education doesn&amp;rsquo;t work; it&amp;rsquo;s that our political system has totally fucked up incentives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us posit the job of our politicians to be caring for the entire population under their control, and the earth as a whole. That&amp;rsquo;s a tall order for any single person, so our politicians will need to work together to get the job done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, there are many people involved, and to make progress will require alignment. Alignment of ideas requires, from time to time, the odd mind to be changed. This IS education. However, the problem arises whenever a needed solution is radically different from the accepted culture of the time. It is these moments that the powerful must decide between 2 choices:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Push through a solution that degrades their influence with a majority of people, thus leading to their removal from power&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compromise a solution that neither fixes the problem, nor lose too much favor with the public such that they keep power (for now)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the balancing act we ask of politicians, who rose to power off the piggy banks of individuals whose influence is yet another factor for the person in charge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we need most of all is a new incentive system for our politicians. We need to remove donations from politicians&#39; bank roles. We need to incentivize quality decisions that positively affect those who are losing the most, as measured by third parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need reform of those who do the reforming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe education does work, we just need the right incentives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/" term="Good Books" label="Good Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">The Silk Roads</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202006silkroads/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202006silkroads/</id>
            <updated>2022-04-29T22:49:36&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2020-06-14T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">This book is an epic undertaking, showcasing world history up to the early 2010&amp;rsquo;s, through the lense of the silk road. History has many authors, and this book does well to capture their ideas in a cohesive framework. The thesis presented here outlines how resource transportation routes shaped our world history.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This book is an epic undertaking, showcasing world history up to the early 2010&amp;rsquo;s, through the lense of the silk road. History has many authors, and this book does well to capture their ideas in a cohesive framework. The thesis presented here outlines how resource transportation routes shaped our world history. Equally important to the goods flowing through commerce were new ideas, including religions, and a massive game of political chess. Short term policies crafted to maintain power at the expense of those without it, often led to self destruction through overreach (and over spending). Worse still was the long term instability created by dying powers&#39; abrupt departure from battleground regions. The most shocking lesson I took away is how cyclical our world history is. The fight for power, and abhorrent disregard for others by those trying to maintain it, is the saddest trait we share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book starts off slow, but is worth persevering through. It started about 2000 years ago, with the empire of Persia, and the creation of the silk roads. From there, the rise and fall of new and old players, in a dance of power politics and war is spectacular. I hope one day we&amp;rsquo;ll learn from our history, and end the senseless killing of those who are simply trying their best to get by.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-key-takeaways&#34;&gt;My key takeaways&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How a world with hundreds of religions is reduced to a few&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why the middle east is so unstable, well into the 21st century&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The luck involved to create a golden era
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How quickly that era falls when the KingPin dies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All empires at the top of the totem pole eventually fall
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The cause of their downfall is often overspending on military:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Roman empire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Portugal/Spain in the 15th &amp;amp; 16th century&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;England in the 17th-20th century&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The human cost required to sustain an empire is terrible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And most importantly, &lt;strong&gt;how frequently history repeats itself&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/best-books/" term="Best Books" label="Best Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">Alexs Adventures in Numberland</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202004alexadventurenumberland/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202004alexadventurenumberland/</id>
            <updated>2022-04-29T22:49:33&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2020-04-25T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">This book was truly a wonderful read! If you want to learn about math&amp;rsquo;s history, you will love this book 
You do not need to have a strong background in math to get the full punch from this story.
My favourite takeaways Regression to the mean Regression to the mean is the concept that, over time, event likelihood converges on the average result.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This book was truly a wonderful read! If you want to learn about math&amp;rsquo;s history, you will love this book &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You do not need to have a strong background in math to get the full punch from this story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-favourite-takeaways&#34;&gt;My favourite takeaways&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;regression-to-the-mean&#34;&gt;Regression to the mean&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regression to the mean is the concept that, over time, event likelihood converges on the average result. Said another way, whenever an outlier occurs, there&amp;rsquo;s a good chance that the next event will be closer to the main outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This idea has interesting implications within the workplace. Manager&amp;rsquo;s are stung when praising outstanding work that is followed by normal work; whereas chastising bad work is usually followed by better performance. However, neither the praise nor the reprimand likely had as large of an effect as regression to the mean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;normal-distribution&#34;&gt;Normal Distribution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The normal distribution is the result of randomness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whenever you see a normal distribution not caused by randomness, be suspicious.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you carefully measure something, if you do not see a normal distribution where randomness should occur (i.e., measurement error), you have likely destroyed the randomness that should be present.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/best-books/" term="Best Books" label="Best Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">Talking to Strangers</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202003talking2strangers/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202003talking2strangers/</id>
            <updated>2022-04-29T22:49:25&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2020-03-20T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">Using a mix of data and in-depth investigations around high profile human interactions, where human behaviour is interpreted terribly, we learn some very important lessons. As usual, Malcolm Gladwell delivers these stories in a wonderful read.
My favourite takeaways  Defaulting to the truth is OK.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Using a mix of data and in-depth investigations around high profile human interactions, where human behaviour is interpreted terribly, we learn some very important lessons. As usual, Malcolm Gladwell delivers these stories in a wonderful read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-favourite-takeaways&#34;&gt;My favourite takeaways&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Defaulting to the truth is OK. It is what created our society and it would be stupid to override this companionship generating trait.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The coupling of environment and action is so strong that it should always be taken into account when interacting with strangers.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t judge a stranger, judge their environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are bad lie detectors. We expect a liar to act one way, and a truth teller another. Our snap decision lie detection is never to be trusted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/best-books/" term="Best Books" label="Best Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">The Personal MBA</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cartar.github.io./books/202002mypersonalmba/" />
            <id>https://cartar.github.io./books/202002mypersonalmba/</id>
            <updated>2022-04-29T22:50:28&#43;01:00</updated>
            <published>2020-02-20T11:40:14-04:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Will Cartar</name>
                    <uri>https://cartar.github.io./</uri>
                    <email>william.cartar@gmail.com</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">I enjoyed this book, but am hesitant to recommend it to others. The writing is only OK, and so much of the content felt somewhat common sense. However, I did find multiple nuggets worth keeping!
My favourite takeaways Prototyping When developing a business, iteration and feedback are key.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed this book, but am hesitant to recommend it to others. The writing is only OK, and so much of the content felt somewhat common sense. However, I did find multiple nuggets worth keeping!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-favourite-takeaways&#34;&gt;My favourite takeaways&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;prototyping&#34;&gt;Prototyping&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When developing a business, iteration and feedback are key. Offering a pre-order with full access to the witten Prototype (description of what is being offered) is ideal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If no one wants to pre-order a free prototype your offer is not valuable enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;reorganization&#34;&gt;Reorganization&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Random actions change things. Attempt to reorganize ideas is our body&amp;rsquo;s way of searching for solutions. When reference levels are violated, and we do not know what action to take next, try reorganization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simulations in your brain only works well with a goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;environment&#34;&gt;Environment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Easiest way to change things is by changing your environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;reference-levels&#34;&gt;Reference Levels&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humans do not have easily manipulated behavior. We are too complex for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather we have reference levels that, when out of whack, force us to make change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;reinterpretation&#34;&gt;Reinterpretation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you want to change your beliefs (or mental stimuli) simply follow:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recall that belief in as much detail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Think of alternative interpretations for that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Realize your belief is an interpretation, not fact.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discard your belief.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose an alternative interpretation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;motivation&#34;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either moving towards or away from things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We evolved to prioritize moving away, which makes sense from our ancestors point-of-view, but doesn&amp;rsquo;t serve us as well today. Understand this emotional tug-of-war when making decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we prioritize moving away, we focus on what is being lost. This can make us fearful of change, because we aren&amp;rsquo;t understanding the complete picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;selection-test&#34;&gt;Selection Test&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Environmental constraints that determine which systems can be self perpetuating and which ones die.
Know the selection tests for a market and you can change the field; especially as markets change due to tech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/" term="Good Books" label="Good Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/" term="Books" label="Books" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
</feed>
