<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>






<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>Will Cartar&#39;s Blog</title>
        <link>https://cartar.github.io./</link>
        <description>MemE is a powerful and highly customizable GoHugo theme for personal blogs.</description>
        <generator>Hugo 0.134.0 https://gohugo.io/</generator>
        
            <language>en</language>
        
        
            <managingEditor>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</managingEditor>
        
        
            <webMaster>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</webMaster>
        
        
            <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
        
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2024 12:13:46 -0400</lastBuildDate>
        
            <atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss&#43;xml" href="https://cartar.github.io./rss.xml" />
        
        
            <item>
                <title>Where the Falcon Flies</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202409wherethefalconflies/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202409wherethefalconflies/</guid>
                <pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2024 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;Adam Shoalts is a wild man. In this book, he travels 3,400 km over 3 months to see where peregrine falcons nest. He does so on foot, and canoe. Paddling down the great lakes from his house on Lake Erie, past Toronto, up the Saint Lawrence through the many locks, past Montreal and Quebec City, all the way past Tadoussac to Saguenay, where he swaps his canoe for a backpack. He then hikes all the way to Labrador City (which Google maps says takes ~200 hours), where he buys a canoe, to paddles to the arctic to spot a falcon nest. After this, he paddles out to Kangiqsualujjuaq, which is just west of the Torngat Mountains. What sparked this epic journey? Perhaps a fundraiser, or a lifelong goal? It was neither; rather, in 2019 he spotted a peregrine falcon flying past his home, and was inspired to follow this migratory bird to its nesting place in the arctic. He&amp;rsquo;d have set out in 2020 if it weren&amp;rsquo;t for the pandemic. As soon as life settled down, he went in 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adam&amp;rsquo;s knowledge of the land is second to none. His ability to supplement his food with foraged goods is always impressive, alongside a general knowledge of the history of whatever he comes across. Some of my favourite anecdotes include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I saw an unmistakably ancient-looking windmill, which curiosity compelled me to land at. It turned out it was the Moulin à vent de Grondines: built in 1674, it&amp;rsquo;s the oldest windmill still standing in all of Canada&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;by 1763 the British ruled all of &amp;lsquo;Old Canada&amp;rsquo; aside form a couple islands, Saint-Pierre and Miquelon, off the coast of Newfoundland, which to this day remain part of France&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;These rugged peaks are part of the Charlevoix region, which has some of eastern Canada&amp;rsquo;s highest summits. Near their centre lies a massive asteroid crater, which flattened a huge area when it struck three hundred and fifty million years ago. These mountains also happen to be one of Canada&amp;rsquo;s most earthquake prone regions.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&amp;lsquo;arctic&amp;rsquo; derives from the Greek word for &amp;lsquo;bear&amp;rsquo;, a reference to the Great Bear constellation visible in northern skies, so originally arctic was just a vague term for anywhere north&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, it was an enjoyable read for anyone who goes to the backcountry, and has done hikes / canoe trips themselves. The scale and ambition of this trip are worth a read. However, the writing itself could have been improved, making it a bit of a slog to get through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/okay-books/">Okay Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Outlive</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202407outlived/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202407outlived/</guid>
                <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2024 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;Like successful aging, this book is a fascinating read that compiles the latest understandings about our bodies into a compendium of knowledge with many recommendations. Much of this book is summarizing studies about which molecules - proteins, hormones, types of cholesterol, and cellular processes are benefited by eating well, not too much (or too little), exercise, and sleep. However, unlike successful aging, the recommendations can be too specialized at times, and require too many resources (time and money) to execute properly. For example, the discussion about exercise requires a personal trainer, and many hours a week to carry out. Or, to hit the recommended protein levels, one needs to be having a good amount of meat twice per day, every day, on top of a protein shake, and high protein snack. This just doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem wise for the average person, or doable for the average household income. Having said all of this, the overall book was interesting nonetheless, and stacking this book with successful aging was enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll start at the end, with my favourite quote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&amp;lsquo;I think people get old when they stop thinking about the future,&amp;rsquo; Ric told me. &amp;lsquo;If you want to find someone&amp;rsquo;s true age, listen to them. If they talk about the past and they talk about all the things that happened that they did, they&amp;rsquo;ve gotten old. If they think about their dreams, their aspiration, what they&amp;rsquo;re still looking forward to - they&amp;rsquo;re young.&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hoping into other points from the book:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I liked the part about rucking, as a great way to improve the benefit of simply going for a walk in your neighbourhood or in the forest -&amp;gt; a good goal is to be able to carry a quarter to a third of your body weight, once you develop enough strength and stamina.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stability training is all about the &amp;ldquo;safe and powerful transmission of force through muscles and bones, and not joints or spinal hinge points&amp;rdquo;. A great way to determine if you&amp;rsquo;re doing a particular exercise well is to film yourself doing it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;odds are overwhelming that you will die as a result of one of the chronic diseases of aging that I call the Four Horsemen: heart disease, cancer neurodegenerative disease, or type 2 diabetes and related metabolic dysfunction.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;when we are slightly deprived of nutrients, or when we are exercising, FOXO3 (a gene) tends to be more activated, which is what we want (it is correlated with longevity)&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Why do we care about mTOR? Because this mechanism turns out to be one of the most important mediators of longevity at the cellular level. Not only that, but it is highly &amp;lsquo;conserved&amp;rsquo; meaning it is found in virtually all forms of life, ranging from yeast to flies, to worms and right up to us humans&amp;hellip; this exotic molecule, found only on an isolated scrap of land in the middle of the ocean, acts almost like a switch that inhibits a very specific cellular mechanism that exists in nearly everything that lives. It was a perfect fit, and this fact still blows my mind every time I think about it. The job of mTOR is basically to balance an organism&amp;rsquo;s need to grow and reproduce against the availability of nutrients. When food is plentiful, mTOR is activated and the cell (or organism) goes into growth mode&amp;hellip;when nutrients are scarce, mTOR is suppressed and cells go into a kind of &amp;lsquo;recycling&amp;rsquo; mode, breaking down cellular components and generally cleaning house.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Reducing the amount of nutrients available to a cell seems to trigger a group of innate pathways that enhance the cell&amp;rsquo;s stress resistance and metabolic efficiency - all of them related, in some to mTOR.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;While AMPK (an AMP-activated protein kinase) is activated when it low levels of nutrients are detected it is also activated when we exercise.&amp;rdquo; -&amp;gt; Its activation leads to a cascade of helpful cellular responses. -&amp;gt; like, &amp;ldquo;instead of creating new proteins and undergoing cell division, the cell goes into a more fuel-efficient and stress-resistance mode, activating an important cellular recycling process called autophagy, which is basically self-eating&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Impaired autophagy is thought to be an important driver of numerous aging-related phenotypes and ailments, such as neurodegeneration and osteoarthritis.&amp;rdquo; I thus find it fascinating that this very important cellular mechanism can be triggered by certain interventions (exercising and caloric restriction) - and the drug rapamycin. Rapamycin seems to reduce systemic inflammation, perhaps by tamping down the activity of so-called senescent cells, which are &amp;lsquo;older&amp;rsquo; cells that have stopped dividing but have not died&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The various treatment guidelines specify target ranges for LDL-C, typically 100 mg / dL for patients at normal risk, or 70 mg / dL for high-risk individuals. In my view, this is still far too high&amp;hellip; [which is] 10 - 20 mg / dL.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Some scientists believe there may be something about menopause, and the abrupt decline in hormonal signaling, that sharply increases the risk of neurodegeneration in older women. In particular, it appears that a rapid drop in estradiol in women with an e4 allele is a driver of risk; that, in turn, suggests a possible role for perimenopausal hormone replacement therapy in these women. Menopause is not the only issue here. Other reproductive history factors, such as the number of children the women has had, age of first menstruation, and exposure to oral contraceptives, may also have a significant impact on Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s risk and later life cognition. And new research suggests that women are more prone to accumulate tau, the neurotoxic protein.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Brain cells metabolize glucose in a different way from the rest of the body; they do not depend on insulin, instead absorbing circulating glucose directly&amp;hellip; enabling the brain to take priority when blood glucose levels are low. If we lack new sources of glucose, the brain&amp;rsquo;s preferred fuel, the liver converts our fat into ketone bodies, as an alternative energy source that can sustain us for a very long time, depending on the extent of our fat stores (Unlike muscle or liver, the brain itself does not store energy). When our fat runs out, we begin to consume our own muscle tissue, then our other organs, and even bone, all in order to keep the brain running at all costs. The brain is the last thing to shut off.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s easy to overlook, but alcohol should be considered as its own category of macronutrients because it is so widely consumed, it has such potent effects on our metabolism, and it is so calorically dense at 7 kcal / g (closer to the 9 kcal / g of fat than the 4 kcal / g of both protein and carbohydrate)&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FOR GLUCOSE MONITORING&lt;/strong&gt; - &amp;ldquo;I like to keep average glucose at or below 100 mg / dL, with a STD of less than 15 mg / dL. These are aggressive goals: 100 mg / dL corresponds to an HbA1c of 5.1%, which is quite low.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FOR PROTEIN&lt;/strong&gt; - &amp;ldquo;the first thing you should know about protein is that the standard recommendations for daily consumption are a joke. The US recommended dietary allowance (RDA) for protein is 0.8 g/kg of body weight. This may reflect how much protein we need to stay alive, but a far cry from what we need to thrive. There is ample evidence showing that we require more than this - and that consuming less leads to worse outcomes. More than one study has found that elderly people consuming that RDA of protein end up losing muscle mass, even in as short a period as two weeks&amp;hellip;. I typically set 1.6 g/kg/day as the minimum, and 2.2 as a good place to start for active people&amp;rdquo;. -&amp;gt; split up over 4 heavy-protein intakes: 2 protein rich meals, and 2 protein rich snacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Trauma generally falls into five categories: abuse, neglect, abandonment, enmeshment (the blurring of boundaries between adults and children) and witnessing tragic events. Most things that wound children fit into these five categories&amp;hellip; dysfunction is represented by the four branches of the trauma tree: addition (not only vices such as drugs, alcohol and gambling, but also socially acceptable things such as work, exercise and perfectionism); codependency, or excessive psychological reliance on another person; habituated survival strategies, such as a propensity to anger and rage; attachment disorders, difficulty forming and maintaining connections or meaningful relationships with others.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;children don&amp;rsquo;t respond to a parent&amp;rsquo;s anger in a logical way. If they see me screaming at a driver who just cut me off, they internalize that rage as though it were directed to them.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;changing the behaviour can change the mood. You don&amp;rsquo;t need to wait for your mood to improve to make a behavioural change. This is why cognitive therapies alone sometimes come up short; simply thinking about problems might not help if our thinking itself is disordered.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/">Good Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Ultra-Processed People</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202403ultraprocessedpeople/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202403ultraprocessedpeople/</guid>
                <pubDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2024 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;Oh boy, this book wasn&amp;rsquo;t so much anything new, as it was a compelling reminder to eat whole foods, or at the very least, purchase food who&amp;rsquo;s full list of ingredients you&amp;rsquo;d have at home. There is a slow, but steady, understanding of these so-called Ultra-Processed Foods (UPFs), and their negative health implications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had an inkling about it beforehand, but I had thought the problem stemmed from a low fiber, high in fats, sugar, and salt diet that often goes hand-in-hand with UPFs. However, that isn&amp;rsquo;t it. When controlling for these variables, recent studies have still found negative health outcomes of ~25% increase risks for a whole host of diseases and cancers - including alzheimers! Clearly, there is something unnatural about these ingredients that interact negatively with our bodies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The catch is, these UPFs are cheap, and pervasive. They&amp;rsquo;ve done well to deflect blame to poor eating habits, and align themselves with present day nutritional guidelines published by various governments. So although the packaging of these prepared snacks or meals might look healthy on the outside (think of cereal labels claiming high fiber, low salt / fat, high vitamins, etc.), they&amp;rsquo;re actually made with the help of UPFs. So eating a diet free of UPFs is quite challenging, and expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything in moderation is probably true, but best to try and avoid these foods. Here are a collection of my favourite quotes and moments from this book:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;You might recognize the names of some of these: guar gum, locust bean gum, alginate, carrageenan, and the near ubiquitous xanthan gum. The last of these is, revoltingly, a bacterial exudate: slime that bacteria produce to allow them to cling to surfaces. Think of xanthan gum when you next scrape the accumulated gunk from the filter on your dishwasher.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The classification system is now called the NOVA system, and it divides food into four groups. The first is &amp;lsquo;unprocessed or minimally processed foods&amp;rsquo; - foods found in nature like meat, fruit and vegetables, but also things like flour and pasta. Group 2 is &amp;lsquo;processed culinary ingredients&amp;rsquo; including oils, lard, butter, sugar, salt, vinegar, honey, starches - traditional foods that might well be prepared using industrial technologies. They&amp;rsquo;re not things we can survive on, because they tend to be nutrient-poor and energy-dense. But mix them with stuff from the first group and you&amp;rsquo;ve got the basis of some delicious food. Group 3 is &amp;lsquo;processed food&amp;rsquo;, ready-made mixtures of groups 1 and 2, processed mainly for preservation: tins of beans, salted nuts, smoked meat, canned fish, chunks of fruit in syrup and proper freshly made bread. And then we come to group 4, &amp;lsquo;ultra-processed foods&amp;rsquo; (UPF). It&amp;rsquo;s long, perhaps the longest definition I&amp;rsquo;d ever read of a scientific category: &amp;lsquo;Formulations of ingredients, mostly of exclusive industrial use, made by a series of industrial processes, many requiring sophisticated equipment and technology.&amp;rsquo; That&amp;rsquo;s just the first bit. It continues: &amp;lsquo;Processes used to make UPF include the fractionation of whole foods into substances, chemical modifications of these substances&amp;hellip;&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Processes and ingredients used to manufacture ultra-processed foods are designed to create highly profitable (low-cost ingredients, long shelf life, emphatic branding) convenient (ready-to-consume) hyperpalatable products liable to displace freshly prepared dishes and meals made from all other NOVA food groups.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;It is the ultra-processing, not the nutritional content, that&amp;rsquo;s the problem&amp;hellip; there is evidence that increased UPF intake is strongly associated with an increased risk of: all-cause mortality (i.e., death), cardiovascular disease, cancers, type 2 diabetes, high blood pressure, fatty liver disease, inflammatory bowel disease, depression, worse blood fat profile, frailty (measured by grip strength), irritable bowel syndrome, dyspepsia (indigestion), and dementia&amp;rdquo; [references in the book]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;In 2022, a study published in the journal Neurology looked at data from over 72,000 people. Increasing intake of UPF by 10% was associated with a 25% increase in the risk of dementia and a 14% increase in the risk of Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;the majority of visits to paediatricians during the 1920&amp;rsquo;s were about fussy eating. The profession responded sensibly&amp;hellip;by advising parents to let children go hungry and to treat them &amp;lsquo;firmly&amp;rsquo;. Alan Brown&amp;rsquo;s 1926 book, &lt;em&gt;The Normal Child, Its Care and Feeding&lt;/em&gt;, provides a good example: &amp;lsquo;Force is necessary for children who spit out their food or those who vomit at will. Give such a child a small amount of the food, if he vomits give him more; continue until he keeps the food down.&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo; -&amp;gt; this led one doctor to test children&amp;rsquo;s abilities to self govern their food intake, as young as 1 years old. The moment the children were done breastfeeding, they were fed all their meals by nurses who put 12 bowls of ingredients in front of the kids. Whatever the child pointed to, or tried to eat, was given to them. Amazingly, and somewhat expectedly, they&amp;rsquo;d identify the foods they were nutrient deficient in, to the point where one kid consumed straight fish-oil until they had their vitamine D back in check.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Nearly a century later, in 1959, an English physiologist called G. R. Hervey began a series of experiments using the parabiotic pair technique to understand weight control. The study is tough reading. Ninety-three pairs of rats were sewn together, only thirty-two of which survived long enough to be used in the experiment. These rats then had a small electric probe inserted into their skulls, which was used to specifically damage a part of the brain called the hypothalamus, which maintains homeostasis in the body, controlling temperature, water intake, how much you sweat and so on. Hervey found that the rats with a damaged hypothalamus lost control of their eating and often developed obesity. So, he started damaging the hypothalamus of just one rat in each parabiotic pair, and if anything , the results got even more horrifying. The rats with the damaged hypothalamus ate so much so quickly that they sometimes died by choking on their food: they were no longer able to detect the &amp;lsquo;stop eating&amp;rsquo; signals coming from their bodies. Meanwhile the other rat - entirely normal apart from being attached to the rat with the hypothalamus lesion - started wasting away. It was getting a signal through the shared circulatory system telling it to stop eating.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;If, like me, you&amp;rsquo;re surprised by the idea that doing more won&amp;rsquo;t allow you to eat more calories, it may be because the opposite idea, that you can burn off excess calories, has been promoted by companies like Coke all the way from the scientific papers through to policy initiatives like Exercise is Medicine. It took me some time to accept that, despite having a medical degree, part of the way that I have understood my body and its energy requirements has come from the Coca-Cola Company.&amp;rdquo; -&amp;gt; Interesting take on a few studies showing that energy use is roughly constant regardless how physically active we are. When we do more, we simply use less energy for other things later on, i.e., rest more thereafter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Apple juice, which is typically around 15% sugar, behaves much like any soft drink. But so does the apple purée, even though it contains all the constituents of the apple, including the fibre, and was made moments before consumption. Fiber is important, but the matrix, the structure of the apple, is key.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Schatzger&amp;rsquo;s proposal is that just like Doc Holliday&amp;rsquo;s cows, we may be eating more food to compensate for becoming increasingly deficient in micronutrients. Ultra-processing reduces micronutrients to the point that modern diets lead to malnutrition even as they cause obesity.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;These four tastes - sweet, salt, sour, and umami - are probably handled by basically four receptors. But bitterness is a different story. Bitter signals &amp;lsquo;potentially toxic&amp;rsquo;, and a huge number of different chemical structures taste bitterness. We need twenty-five different genes to detect bitterness, which gives us a great ability to detect toxins. But we can learn to love bitterness too. Bitter coffee will make a child gag and retch, but you can learn to associate the bitter taste with the exhilaration of the caffeine such that it becomes essential for making adult life bearable.&amp;rdquo; -&amp;gt; Some other interesting things here were that although we don&amp;rsquo;t smell as well dogs, for example, our taste receptors are more complex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;When Cola was invented, the aim was to make a drink to perk people up, and the original formula contained extract of coca leaves and caffeine. Cocaine and caffeine are both extremely bitter, so the company added lots of sugar to mask this. But that initial bitterness was actually an advantage. It was the extreme bitterness that allowed the addition of more sugar to the drink than would otherwise have been possible&amp;hellip; But why does Coca-Cola want us to drink all this sugar? Remember those rat studies who learned to like flavours paired with calories? Well the same is true in humans&amp;hellip; This may explain a bizarre pricing phenomenon first noticed in Central America but common in low-income countries around the world. Sweet fizzy beverages are nearly as cheap or cheaper than bottled water. Obviously, it&amp;rsquo;s more expensive to make cola, but once people buy one, they will buy more. Water is cheaper to produce, but it&amp;rsquo;s hard to get people to drink lots of it.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;So, by using additives that affect taste and combining sensory experiences, UPF sneaks more rewards (such as sugar) past our tongues than we would otherwise tolerate. It makes us crave UPF more than we could ever crave home cooking. And, by creating mismatches between the sensations in the mouth and the nutrition in the gut, the companies have (if only accidentally) arrived at a method for driving increased consumption.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/">Good Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Age of the City</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202402ageofthecity/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202402ageofthecity/</guid>
                <pubDate>Mon, 19 Feb 2024 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;Even as someone who isn&amp;rsquo;t a city planner, I found many of the chapters somewhat obvious. The challenge of climate change in cities, or increased risk of novel viruses for example. However, I did enjoy the book; not dissimilar to a good economist article, the ideas were well written, and the story easy to follow. Just not enough &amp;ldquo;Aha&amp;rdquo; moments I suppose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/okay-books/">Okay Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Spark</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202401spark/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202401spark/</guid>
                <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jan 2024 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;As someone who knew very little Chinese history, this was a fascinating book. We follow various underground historians, or dissidents as the Chinese government would call them, set across the ages. Some, hundreds of years ago, but mainly, it is the story of people keeping the past 100 years of history alive, despite the best efforts of the Chinese government to forget. The mass starvation during the great famine of the late 50&amp;rsquo;s under Mao&amp;rsquo;s mismanagement, mass burials of the cultural revolution, and the many executions or lifelong detention of &amp;ldquo;dissidents&amp;rdquo; for simply speaking with an open mind. As the party has changed hands from Mao, to Deng Xiaoping, and now Xi Jinping, the country has seen massive change. Much of it for the better, but the need to control history has resulted in lost truths which are harrowingly kept alive by a select few.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/">Good Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Piranesi</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202312piranesi/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202312piranesi/</guid>
                <pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2023 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;This book had a lot of hype, both online and from my friend who recommended it. I&amp;rsquo;ll say, it took a bit to get into but then I was hooked. The non-spoiler description from Good Reads reads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Piranesi’s house is no ordinary building: its rooms are infinite, its corridors endless, its walls are lined with thousands upon thousands of statues, each one different from all the others. Within the labyrinth of halls an ocean is imprisoned; waves thunder up staircases, rooms are flooded in an instant. But Piranesi is not afraid; he understands the tides as he understands the pattern of the labyrinth itself. He lives to explore the house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is one other person in the house—a man called The Other, who visits Piranesi twice a week and asks for help with research into A Great and Secret Knowledge. But as Piranesi explores, evidence emerges of another person, and a terrible truth begins to unravel, revealing a world beyond the one Piranesi has always known.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My initial impression was that the labyrinth was a metaphor for one&amp;rsquo;s career. Starting off in awe of all that it can provide, and excitement for exploration. There is a fair amount of calibration required to thrive (measuring the tides) and at least for me, a scientific approach necessary to do my work. Then there is the office politics (his relationship with The Other), and a desire to see the rest of the world once it becomes clear that what you&amp;rsquo;re doing is not the entire picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/">Good Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Successful Aging</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202311successfulaging/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202311successfulaging/</guid>
                <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2023 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;Before I had even finished it, I&amp;rsquo;d bought 2 copies of this book: one for my parents, and the other for my partner&amp;rsquo;s. I admit, some chapters review much of what I already knew; exercise is very good for our brains and body (and you don&amp;rsquo;t need to be a gym rat - just get your heart rate up!); healthy eating isn&amp;rsquo;t prescribable, but it&amp;rsquo;ll include eating a range of unprocessed food (processed food is bad), eating in moderation, less sweets, and finding a diet that works best for you (without going to the extremes). But the many reviews of the latest neuroscience and how they apply to us as we age was fascinating. For example, a reason we &amp;ldquo;always have room for dessert&amp;rdquo; is the novel flavours (sweet after salty) pique your interest even though enough was several mouthfuls ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made far too many bookmarks throughout, so I&amp;rsquo;ll jump right in. Here are a collection of my favourite quotes and moments from this book:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The eldest child in a multi child household tends to take on some of the parenting and instruction of the younger ones; the youngest child may be relatively coddled or ignored, depending on the parents; the middle child may find herself thrust into the role of peacemaker.&amp;rdquo; -&amp;gt; I do have the urge to arbitrate peace&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personality traits were very difficult to study because culture and language play a role in shaping them. To get around this, researchers realized &amp;lsquo;The more important an individual difference is in human transactions, the more languages will have a term for it.&amp;rsquo; &amp;ldquo;And so, intrepid researchers&amp;hellip; studied the languages of diverse cultures from around the globe. Consider one type of individual difference, mental illness. It seems rather important to know whether a person you&amp;rsquo;re interacting with is &lt;em&gt;sane&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;rational&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;emotionally stable&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;hears voices in their head&lt;/em&gt;. It turns out that people as diverse as the Inuit in Alaska; Yoruba tribes of Nigeria; and the Pintupi aborigines of Australia, have words in their languages for these important personality descriptors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;To become more conscientious, one must change underlying cognitive processes such as self-regulation, and self-monitoring. If you wish you [were better at this, checkout] David Allen&amp;rsquo;s book &lt;em&gt;Getting Things Done&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interesting anecdote of someone with &lt;em&gt;hypermnesia&lt;/em&gt; (the opposite of amnesia, essentially having super memory) was that they couldn&amp;rsquo;t recognize friends and colleagues because &amp;ldquo;everyone has so many faces.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot; This is how memory works in the brain - as soon as you retrieve a memory, it becomes editable, just like a text document; it enters a vulnerable state and can get rewritten without your intent, consent, or knowledge. Often, a memory is rewritten by new information that gets coloured in during one recollection, and then that new information gets grafted onto and stored with the old, all seamlessly, without your conscious awareness. This process can happen over and over again until the original memory in your brain has been replaced with subsequent interpretations , impressions, and recollections.&amp;rdquo; -&amp;gt; Shortly after reading this, I was recounting an excursion that had been so-so, but was in a terrible headspace when asked about it, and I found my retelling of the tale was done with a negative spin! Clearly, my negative mood was colouring the memory, which was a light bulb moment for me. Perhaps that is why when I ask my grandmother how her day is going she just says &amp;ldquo;don&amp;rsquo;t ask me that dear, getting old is for the birds!&amp;rdquo; When you don&amp;rsquo;t have something nice to say, best not to say (or think) anything at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve come to believe that Multiple-trace theory (MTT) is the correct way of looking at memory&amp;hellip; It provides a compelling explanation for why we forget recent events when we age but still remember older ones: The older ones created more memory traces, either through repetition or through multiple recollections of them.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strengthen your brain games haven&amp;rsquo;t been shown to work across functions outside of the &lt;em&gt;games&lt;/em&gt; you&amp;rsquo;re playing. But there are apps for building memory, &amp;ldquo;and those are an integral part of the program of healthy brain practices, such as Neurotrack.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The young infant lives in a state of psychedelic splendour in which a green light might have a taste, or their mother&amp;rsquo;s voice might elicit a warm and smooth sensation on the skin. Some babies never completely achieve sensory differentiation and then have a condition called synesthesia. There is some evidence that adults who develop certain forms of dementia can revert to this state, and it has been suggested that this may account, in part, for why some older adults develop a new interest in art quite suddenly.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Successfully making contact with a moving target, such as a spinning mobile over the crib, or catching a ball, is so important that it has a special name, &lt;em&gt;interceptive timing&lt;/em&gt;. This skill is a precursor to mathematical ability: It usually has to develop before a child can represent abstract concepts such as numbers.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The term &lt;em&gt;critical period&lt;/em&gt; is used to describe a time window within which a particular skill or ability needs to be cultivated with the right environmental input, or it can never be acquired (these windows are statistically distributed). You may remember some of these famous examples if you ever took a psychology class. Kittens who were deprived of normal visual input never develop normal eyesight. Kittens that wore an eye patch never develop binocular vision or depth perception, and kittens raised in the dark never learn to see, even though their eyes are fine (Many scientists today regret that the kitten experiments were considered ethical at the time, in the 1950&amp;rsquo;s)&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Older adults who want to maintain their sense of balance and orientation must not just observe the environment but also move around&amp;hellip; Neuroplasticity is what keeps us young, and it is only a walk in the park away.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Exercise, meditation, listening to music, immersing yourself in nature, and sometimes just talking to friends and having social support can help to reduce stress significantly.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot; Withdrawal from the world after a negative experience is evolutionarily adaptive - it gives us time to heal and to reflect productively on what went wrong so that we can avoid or correct patterns of our own behaviour that can lead to trouble.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Spend time with people who encourage you to grow, to explore new things, and who take joy in your successes. Try to find social situations that respect older adults and a role that allows you to contribute your accumulated knowledge and wisdom to a community organization whose goals you admire. And when you can, go outside. Go outside.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;People who are in enriched environments - with lots of things to see, listen to, and do - experience less pain than those in simpler environments, and this sort of distraction diminishes pain signals in the insula and primary sensory cortex. Effective distractions while in pain includes exercise, hobbies, interesting conversation, practicing yoga, meditation, socializing, listening to soothing music, or immersing yourself in nature.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Melatonin levels in the blood are highest in young people (55-75 pg/ml) and start to decline after the age of forty, with the fastest decrease found from sixty years of age onward, reaching very low levels in the elderly (18-40 pg/ml). New research suggests that melatonin may have protective effects against many cancers, which may be part of the reason that as people age - and melatonin levels go down - they are more susceptible to cancers.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Among nondrug treatments [for improved aging], cognitive stimulation therapy (CST) has the highest record of efficacy.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Other treatments: studies that are only preliminary, and wouldn&amp;rsquo;t yet be called &lt;em&gt;medicine&lt;/em&gt; because evidence is still being gathered:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vitamin B_12, found in meat, poultry, eggs, milk and fish, is necessary for the production of myelin in the brain and is involved in the metabolism of every cell in the body&amp;hellip; We believe that [homocysteine] increases oxidative stress and increases damage to DNA and that its neurotoxicity leads to cell death. B_12 (along with B_6 and folate) is responsible for recycling homocysteine, thereby keeping its levels in check; insufficient amounts of B_12 are therefore believed responsible for a toxic buildup of homocysteine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Neuroshroom - which includes Hericium erinaceus polysaccharides (HEP), cordyceps militaris, and ganoderma lucidum, that increase acetylcholine for memory / neuroprotective / neuroregenerative qualities, boost energy levels, and boost memory function / reduce stress / have anti-inflammatory properties respectively.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bacopa - water hyssop, might improve higher-order cognitive processes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meditation - helps with our ability to maintain attention, reducing activity within the default mode network and increases connectivity between regions of the brain that are implicated in cognitive control.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cartar.github.io./images/SuccessfulAging2.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;h4&gt;Well Being Score&lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Daniel Pink has to say this about the middle-aged dip: &amp;lsquo;One possibility is the disappointment of unrealized expectations. In our naive twenties and thirties, our hopes are high, our scenarios rosy. Then reality trickled in like a slow leak in the room. Only one person gets to be CEO - and it&amp;rsquo;s not going to be you. Some marriages crumble - and yours, sadly, is one of them&amp;hellip; Yet we don&amp;rsquo;t remain in the emotional basement for long, because over time we adjust our aspirations and later realize that life is pretty good. In short, we dip in the middle because we&amp;rsquo;re lousy forecasters. In youth, our expectations are too high.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Three questions: who&amp;rsquo;ll change my light bulbs? [i.e., who&amp;rsquo;ll do the mundane shit when you&amp;rsquo;re unable to]; What if I want an ice cream cone [i.e., are you setup to live the life you want as your systems begin to fail - do you have to drive to that ice cream, or can you walk]? and Who will I have lunch with?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Decreasing the risk of dying from one disease has increased our risk of dying from other, arguably more horrible ones. [i.e., alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s instead of a heart attack]&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;The single most important factor in determining successful aging is the personality trait of Conscientiousness.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Three additional factors that determine how well we age are more important than the rest. The first is childhood experiences, in particular of parental attachment and of head injury. The second is exercise in varied, natural environments. And the third is social interaction.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Nearly every part of our brains is activated by interacting with others, live, face-to-face, in real time.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;One major block to social engagement is anger&amp;hellip;. As former US senator Alan Simpson says, &amp;lsquo;Hatred corrodes the container in which it is carried&amp;rsquo;.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Remember that the world is changing, and those changes are at odds with your accumulated experience. Force yourself to update, to keep current with changes in the world.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Remember also that pain is physical and informed by our senses, yet it is also influenced by emotional and cultural factors. A negative emotional state can lead to increased pain, and an otherwise painful sensation can be interpreted as positive, such as soreness after exercise.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Practice gratitude for what you have.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cartar.github.io./images/SuccessfulAging1.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;h4&gt;Risk / Protective Factors&lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;appendix-rejuvenating-your-brain&#34;&gt;Appendix: Rejuvenating your brain:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t retire. Don&amp;rsquo;t stop being engaged with meaningful work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look forward. Don&amp;rsquo;t look back.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exercise. Get your heart rate going. Preferably in nature.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Embrace a moderate lifestyle with healthy practices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep your social circle exciting and new.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spend time with people younger than you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;See your doctor regularly, but not obsessively.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t think of yourself as old.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Appreciate your cognitive strengths - pattern recognition, crystallized intelligence, wisdom, accumulated knowledge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Promote cognitive health through experiential learning: travelling, spending time with grandchildren, and immersing yourself in new activities and situations. DO NEW THINGS!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/best-books/">Best Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Brief Answers to the Big Questions</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202310briefanswerstobigquestions/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202310briefanswerstobigquestions/</guid>
                <pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;A fun reminder of the wonders of our universe, guided by one of the most astonishing minds of the last century. My favourite parts were the forward, introduction, and prelude &amp;ldquo;why we must ask the big questions&amp;rdquo;, but that is because the reminder of the book reviewed ideas that I&amp;rsquo;m familiar with. It is remarkable that Stephen could write this book in his last year of life, given his limited ability to express himself (just some facial muscles by that point). That, mixed with his discussions about black holes, the beginning of the universe, and various other areas where our knowledge is incomplete were what made this book worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/okay-books/">Okay Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Team of Rivals</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202309teamofrivals/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202309teamofrivals/</guid>
                <pubDate>Sat, 23 Sep 2023 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;As someone with little knowledge of the American Civil War, or President Lincoln, this book was equally fascinating and well written. Lincoln&amp;rsquo;s name hasn&amp;rsquo;t gone down in history because of his superior military knowhow, or skilful &amp;ldquo;statesmanship&amp;rdquo;, but because of his superior &amp;ldquo;peculiar moral power and greatness of character&amp;rdquo;. It is truly a shame that politicians are not like Lincoln - who was so keenly aware of making the morally correct choice, at the opportune time, that he was able to craft a cabinet of rivals that balanced themselves on the whole. As is often touted today of top tier leadership, you want to foster trust, respect, and open disagreement that allows for the best ideas to flourish. Creating a leadership team of &amp;ldquo;yes-people&amp;rdquo; is never good in the long run. Lincoln was ahead of his time here, as that is exactly the atmosphere he was able to create and maintain through arguably the most trying times in all of America&amp;rsquo;s history. Comparing Lincoln (the first elected President of the Republican Party), to Donald Trump shows the alarming distance politicians have travelled into a world of short term exuberance. It is no wonder that democracy should suffer with America so divided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two of my favourite moments from this book are when Lincoln appears on the battlefield - at the distress of everyone else around him. At the start of the war, he journeys to the front line, and in the dark, takes a boat over to the enemy camp to scout out an adequate landing for his forces. This was completely unheard of, as Lincoln was no general - however, he had become fed up with the slow progress of his commander at this particular post, and took it upon himself to get the troops moving. At another battlefront, late in the war, he was within range of the enemy, to the point that the surgeon by his side was actually shot by opposing fire. Can you imagine anything so wild as the sitting president being on the front line of what was the chaos of a 19th century war?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto a couple of my favourite quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;in times of anxiety it is critical to &amp;lsquo;avoid being idle,&amp;rsquo; that &amp;lsquo;business and conversation of friends&amp;rsquo; were necessary to give the mind &amp;lsquo;rest from that intensity of thought, which will some times wear the sweetest idea threadbare and turn it to the bitterness of death&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;One of Lincoln&amp;rsquo;s favorite anecdotes spring from the early days just after the Revolution. Shortly after the peace was signed, the story began, the Revolutionary War hero Ethan Allen &amp;lsquo;had occasion to visit England&amp;rsquo;, where he was subjected to considerable teasing banter. The British would make &amp;lsquo;fun of the Americans and General Washington in particular and one day they got a picture of General Washington&amp;rsquo; and displayed it prominently in the outhouse so Mr. Allen could not miss it. When he made no mention of it, they finally asked him if he had seen the Washington picture. Mr. Allen said, &amp;lsquo;he thought that was a very appropriated [place] for an Englishman to Keep it. Why they asked, for said Mr. Allen there is Nothing that Will Make an Englishman Shit So quick as the Sight of Genl Washington&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&amp;lsquo;Having hope&amp;rsquo;, writes Daniel Goleman in his study of emotional intelligence, &amp;lsquo;means that one will not give in to overwhelming anxiety, a defeatist attitude, or depression in the face of difficult challenges or setbacks.&amp;rsquo; Hope is &amp;lsquo;more than the sunny view that everything will turn out all right&amp;rsquo;; it is &amp;lsquo;believing you have the will and the way to accomplish your goals.&amp;rsquo; More clearly than his colleagues, Lincoln understood that numerous setbacks were inevitable before the war could be brought to a close.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Washing was a typical American. Napoleon was a typical Frenchman, but Lincoln was a humanitarian as broad as the world. He was bigger than his country - bigger than all the Presidents together.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/">Good Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>The Infinite Game</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202308infinitegame/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202308infinitegame/</guid>
                <pubDate>Thu, 24 Aug 2023 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;This book is great for anyone leading a company, and good for those wanting to know if they&amp;rsquo;re a part of an organization that is in it for the long haul. The basic premise is that companies without a proper &lt;em&gt;Just Cause&lt;/em&gt;, and various other attributes, will at one point or another, succumb to their short sightedness, and fail. There are many examples to draw on, where companies prioritize profit over their purpose, and end up losing out to the inevitable innovation of competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leading by purpose is not easy, and it is almost never rewarded by Wall Street. Therefore, Simon argues that leaders must have courage to do the right thing, in the face of short term incentives. To find that courage, he suggests the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Find a Just Cause that inspires us; surround ourselves with others with whom we share common cause, people we trust and who trust us; identify a Rival worthy of comparison that will push us to constantly improve; and remind ourselves that we are more committed to the Cause than to any particular path or strategy we happen to be following right now.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This excerpt was taken from the final chapter, and is a good summary of all the preceding chapters, which do a better job of highlighting why each of these ideas is important, and examples of what to-do, and what not-to-do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/okay-books/">Okay Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Mendeleyev’s dream</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202308mendeleyevsdream/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202308mendeleyevsdream/</guid>
                <pubDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2023 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;This book was the first time I came into contact with a history of chemistry, and it was absolutely fascinating. Histories of physics have been my default, due to their ongoing contributions to the origins of life, the universe and everything; but much of that history is the back and forth of military funded experiments, and intellectual genius. Chemistry, on the other hand, was funded by the wealthy in an attempt to create more wealth through transmutation (i.e., alchemy), as well as the mishaps of mad scientists tinkering with &amp;ldquo;the elements&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book covers over two thousand years of history, which includes the origin story of many words (some are included below), and the intellectual struggle of determining what exactly is an element? The following are ideas, and excerpts from the book to hopefully give you an idea of why it was such an engaging read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aristotle was responsible for creating a worldview that would last almost 2 thousand years. His scientific brilliance was built on the lens of object qualities, rather than object properties. In this way, he failed to see a world composed of atoms, which had been proposed by Democritus decades before Aristotle. Instead, he saw the world through four &amp;ldquo;basic elements&amp;rdquo;: Earth ws the center, next came water, above that was air, and above the air fire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;All motion in the world was the attempt of the elements to find their rightful place. Thus stones fell to the bottom of water, bubbles rose up out of it, fire rose upwards through the air and so forth. But the sun, the moon and the stars clearly did not move in such a way, so Aristotle proposed a fifth element. This rarefied element he called aether. Remnants of this element persist in our words ethereal (celestial, airy), and quintessence (literally &amp;lsquo;fifth essence&amp;rsquo;)&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;[The middle ages were] not so much an anti-scientific age as an a-scientific one. There was simply no need for science in an age without progress, an age which believed that timeless spiritual values were superior to the vagaries of reality&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once discovered, sulphuric acid transformed the development of many materials, so much so that until the mid-twentieth century, a country&amp;rsquo;s development was measured by the volume of sulphuric acid it&amp;rsquo;s industry used each year!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nicolas Flamel was a real person who set out on an alchemical pilgrimage through France and Spain in search of the philosopher&amp;rsquo;s stone - his published memoirs mention: &amp;ldquo;Finally, in the yeere of the restoring of mankind, 1382, I made a projection of the Red stone upon the like quantity of Mercury the five and twentieth day of April, about five a clock in the Evening; which I transmuted truly into almost as much pure Gold, better assuredly than common Gold, more soft, and more pliable.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Theophrastus Bombast von Hohenheim, better known as Paracelsus, was another well known character in the history of Alchemy - which I suppose was a nod from Full Metal Alchemist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Arabic name for the substance with which Jezebel painted her eyes was kohl. By a series of misapprehensions this word came to be used to describe distilled liquids, and eventually the distilled liquid al-kohl (the kohl) - which became alcohol&amp;rdquo; Many other words with the &amp;ldquo;al&amp;rdquo; prefix come from Arabic - like Algebra, Algorithm, Alkali, and even Alchemy etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Hydrogen&amp;rdquo; comes from the Greek hydro &amp;ldquo;water&amp;rdquo; and -gen, &amp;ldquo;generator, getter, maker&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/best-books/">Best Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>The Future of AI</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202307futureofai/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202307futureofai/</guid>
                <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jul 2023 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;This book has maybe two interesting parts to it. The description of how a new antibiotic was discovered by AI, and the modelling of protein folding by AI. Other than that, the book doesn&amp;rsquo;t go into much detail about AI, and instead focuses on ideas like the cyber threat of AI, and how it is that that cyber threat is different from say nuclear threat. I suppose those would be interesting topics to folks more politically inclined than me. I just wanted to explore cutting edge AI and its novel impacts, which I didn&amp;rsquo;t get from this book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/worst-books/">Worst Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Death’s End</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202305deathsend/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202305deathsend/</guid>
                <pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2023 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;The cover of this book says: &amp;ldquo;wildly imaginative&amp;rdquo;, which is a perfect synopsys. I&amp;rsquo;ve not had my mind blow so many times over by a series, and I doubt I ever will again. It isn&amp;rsquo;t just the exotic physics of higher dimensions utilized by hyper advanced civilizations. It is the political interactions of those civilizations with one another, and a story arc that is truly captivating. I felt the full range of emotions in this book - from excitedly anticipating reunions, to battles outcomes, mind games, and love stories. This book had it all. I cannot recommend this book, or this series enough. The only downside is that the books are a little long, and take ~50-100 pages to really get into. But once you&amp;rsquo;re there, the length of the story becomes a blessing, as you&amp;rsquo;ll not want the ride to end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/best-books/">Best Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Surely You’re Joking Mr. Feynman</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202304surelyyourejoking/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202304surelyyourejoking/</guid>
                <pubDate>Sat, 15 Apr 2023 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;This collection of stories from Richard Feynman&amp;rsquo;s life is a fascinating time capsule into life in the mid 1900&amp;rsquo;s. From his work on the Manhattan Project, to his inquisitive mind and child-like love of life, he truly is a magnificent character whose voice and adventures shine bright in this book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/">Good Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>The Dark Forest</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202303thedarkforest/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202303thedarkforest/</guid>
                <pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;With the story well underway, this second book is a masterpiece. Without giving too much away, we are transported to a future where Luo Ji is awake and well. Technology has progressed far enough to give humanity a sense of security, and that leads to some interesting plot development. We finally learn why Luo Ji had so many assassination attempts against him, and yet again, the story unfolds with unanticipated twists that make it hard to put down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After finishing this book, I understand all the hype. It took me a bit to get into it, but it truly is an incredibly creative story that inspires the reader to see the beauty in our world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/best-books/">Best Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>The Five Most Important Questions</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202302questions/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202302questions/</guid>
                <pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2023 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;A dated book that feels a little ahead of it&amp;rsquo;s time. Certainly still relevant today, it is full of anecdotes about why the 5 questions outlined below are so crucial to success for any organization (private, public, non-profit, etc.). But really, if you agree that the five questions are valuable, you don&amp;rsquo;t need to read the book so much as do the exercise. However, the book is a quick 2 hour read (or less), so you don&amp;rsquo;t lose much giving it a spin!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;peter-druckers-five-questions-are&#34;&gt;Peter Drucker&amp;rsquo;s five questions are:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is our Mission?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who is our Customer?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What does the Customer Value?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are our Results?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is our Plan?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/okay-books/">Okay Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>The Three-Body Problem</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202301threebodyproblem/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202301threebodyproblem/</guid>
                <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2023 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;I found the narrative a little hard to follow at first, but by the end, I was hooked. This sci-fi adventure is inventive in the creation of the antagonist, and keeps you wanting to learn more about their story. Having not read any literature from China before, I found there to a weight behind the backstory that was new to me. The author spoke of cultural revolution in China in a way that was unexpected, and captivating. I&amp;rsquo;m excited to read the next 2 parts of the adventure!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/">Good Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Flush</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202212flush/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202212flush/</guid>
                <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2022 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;An interesting review of how useful our poop is, the current science of capturing that information, and what is going on on the inside to cause our stool to look the way it does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main takeaways are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re constipated - you&amp;rsquo;re absorbing too much water, drink more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you have diarrhea - you&amp;rsquo;re losing a lot of water, drink more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If your poop experience is poor, try&amp;hellip;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;eating more fiber, but ramp up slowly as you might not have the right mix of microbes at the start.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;boosting the diversity of your microbiome by eating plain yogurt (daily), and fermented foods like kimchi or kombucha.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you travel, expect to have a bad time - best to prepare your microbiome beforehand with the above tips.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-other-notes-i-took&#34;&gt;Some other notes I took:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;useful&#34;&gt;Useful&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overuse of laxatives in general can decrease absorption of nutrients and other medications, cause electrolyte imbalances, create dependency and actually worsen constipation by interfering with the colon’s natural contractions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yellow and greasy suggest not digesting fat well; and that evaluation for celiac disease or another cause of malabsorption is warranted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Green stool could be food passing too quickly and not giving your bile a chance to break down into brown colour;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Black could be bleeding in upper tract or black licorice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Red could be beets or bleeding in lower tract - often hemorrhoids but sometimes more seriously colon cancer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;White or clay-coloured / devoid of colour from bile suggests a blockage in a duct that carries bile from liver to gallbladder -&amp;gt; in infants is life threatening if not corrected&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Constipation can tear the main intestinal lining and cause anal fissures. Intense pressure on the colon can cause diverticulitis (inflamed or infected pouches of gut tissue), hemorrhoids (akin to varicose veins; also can be from prolonged sitting on the pot), to more serious conditions like defecation syncope (fainting on the toilet), or even a stroke.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Posture modification on the toilet can reduce strain and encourage a more complete evacuation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When ramping up on fiber, if you didn’t already eat a lot of fiber, you’ll need to ramp up slowly, to avoid stomach cramps (as it’s unlikely you have the right fiber-munching bacteria to begin with). Slow and steady can cultivate the microbiome you seek, and adding fermented foods / yogurt can do wonders too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The bacteria sometimes take time to ramp up the right metabolic pathways or fiber-processing genes. In artificial guts, you see bacteria don’t degrade the fiber as much on the first day compared to the next.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Microbiome disruptions like: food poisoning, international travel, and dietary changes are all associated with shifts in gut flora.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sometimes, these changes can introduce totally new species that sometimes wipe out weaker competition. However, it is usually the case that the system as a whole preserves their functionality - like digesting carbohydrates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is where food sensitivity tests, and microbiome lab tests (stool testing) fall short. It’s an expensive snapshot of your current system that will need to be done again in the near future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eating a diet rich in fermented foods like: yogurt, kimchi, and kombucha tea for many weeks shows signs of improved gut microbiome diversity and reduced signs of inflammation compared to counterparts on a high-fiber diet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“The bacteria food alone isn’t enough; we need the bacteria that can eat it.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Caution: nothing is guaranteed. What works for others won’t necessarily work for you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;less-useful-but-noteworthy&#34;&gt;Less useful, but noteworthy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Constipation - colon absorbs too much water. 15 major classes of drugs can cause constipation, according to one tally, even tylenol can stop things up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many drugs cause diarrhea by increasing intestinal muscle movements that push everything onwards. Allergies, infections, contaminated or overly spicy food can trigger an immune response to flush out the system. Can be from IBS, lactose intolerance, diseases, drugs or damage can inflame or tear the intestinal lining, interfering with water absorption that makes matters worse.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some researchers claim timing transit is more important than Bristol stool scale.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Median is 29 hours. Range is 4 hours - 10 days&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Longer transit time associated with greater gut diversity -&amp;gt; not sure how well studied this is&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And greater diversity isn’t always a good thing -&amp;gt; if that diversity includes an unfavourable mix.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;C-section + instant formula over vagina birth + breastfeeding alter microbiome in ways that increase the risk of asthma and allergies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Babies exposed to a broader diversity of microbes are more protected and have lower risk of bad lifelong health outcomes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Think of your microbiome as your mini ecosystem for which you are the caretaker. * If you eat poorly, don’t prioritise sleep, exercise, and a balanced lifestyle, your microbiome is likely to get out of balance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;not-useful-but-cool&#34;&gt;Not useful, but cool&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;German made: Flachspuler - or flat-flush toilet, helps people examine their stool before being flushed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People in the US eat about 30-35% of the fiber that they should - which makes the average deposit in western toilets a fraction of what they should be&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lots of applications for measuring specific biomarkers like proteins, carbohydrates, fats, and smaller metabolites that your microbes create. These have been used to predict childhood obesity and even intelligence. However, this research is beyond the scope of Gut Hub - and the research is very new. It’s unclear in which direction the relationship is causal; does measurable intelligence modify your gut biome, or the other way around?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/okay-books/">Okay Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>naked statistics</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202211nakedstatistics/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202211nakedstatistics/</guid>
                <pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2022 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;A masterpiece in fun-reading education; this book is accessible to everyone who&amp;rsquo;s goal is to learn statistics. And for those with a strong handle on the subject, it is a good reminder of the pitfalls of being too brash with the toolkit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My key takeaways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;always-check-both-mean-and-median&#34;&gt;Always check both mean and median&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using one without knowing the other can be dangerous, as both are good at hiding data. Mean can easily hide the distribution, while median hides outliers. Better yet, use both AND include a distribution graph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;common-biases&#34;&gt;Common biases:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Selection bias: poorly sampled data skewing results&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Publication bias: omitting negative results via preference for positive news&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recall bias: our memories suck - or at least they are different than lived experience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Survivorship bias: what hedge funds do&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;healthy user bias: does pills make you healthier or do healthy ppl take pills?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;central-limit-theorem-clt&#34;&gt;Central limit theorem (CLT)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mean of sampled populations will create its own normal distribution, regardless if the population being sampled is normally distributed. The mean of this normal distribution will overlap with the true mean of the population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Standard Error (SE) of the sampled means will be proportional to the standard deviation of the underlying population, and the sample number (N).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Review chapter 9 for an elegant example using CLT to infer brain size difference between kids with / without autism. Reviews p-values, SE between 2 means, and one vs two tail hypothesis testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;polling&#34;&gt;Polling&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Polling is an interesting application of statistics in that we can sample a small subset of the entire population, and if done correctly, have a pretty good understanding of the outcome. That is, one must be careful not to accidently introduce a selection bias, and the way in which questions are asked can make a big difference as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An aside: SE of polling uses a different formula, which has a maximum variance when the results are 50 / 50.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;regression-analysis&#34;&gt;Regression analysis&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;regression coefficient&lt;/strong&gt; is simply the slope of the line; the residual is the &amp;ldquo;error&amp;rdquo; or deviation away from the straight line slope for every dependent variable; independent variables are often called &amp;ldquo;explanatory&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;control&amp;rdquo; variables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The R^2 measures the total amount of variation explained by the regression equation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multiple regression analysis is simply a multi-dimensional slope that allows a comparison between explanatory variables to determine how much each variable contributes to the dependent variable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;common-regression-mistakes&#34;&gt;Common regression mistakes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using regression for a non-linear relationship&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Correlation does not equal causation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reverse causality (B actually causes A, rather than A -&amp;gt; B)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Omitted variable bias (i.e., missing age when it is in fact the strongest predictor)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Highly correlated explanatory variables (multicollinearity)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extrapolating beyond the data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data mining (too many variables)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;gotchas&#34;&gt;Gotchas:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assuming events are independent when they&amp;rsquo;re not: i.e., plane engine failures. You&amp;rsquo;d expect each engine to have an independant probability of failure, but when one fails, it is more likely the second one fails too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/best-books/">Best Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Thinking in Bets</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202210thinkinginbets/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202210thinkinginbets/</guid>
                <pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2022 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;The first half of this book is very interesting, and includes many fun anecdotes from the life of a professional poker player. The second half is classic psychology material that is found in many other similar books: diversity helps consensus, allowing for dissent within teams helps them move towards the truth, our remembered experience is different from our experience, and learning when you&amp;rsquo;re on &amp;ldquo;tilt&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The novel takeaway from this book is that everyone becomes less biased when they&amp;rsquo;re placing bets. Putting money where our mouth is really does improve our sense of truth seeking. Makes you wonder why this trick isn&amp;rsquo;t used more frequently in the world of business? From the sounds of it, the change is just beginning (with betting markets inside businesses).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;favourite-quotes&#34;&gt;Favourite quotes:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Chess is not a game. Chess is a well-defined form of computation. You may not be able to work out the answers, but in theory there must be a solution, a right procedure in any position. Now, real games, he said, are not like that at all. Real life is not like that. Real life consists of bluffing, of little tactics of deception, of asking yourself what the other person is thinking.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Kahan&amp;rsquo;s findings&amp;hellip; discovered that the more numerate people made more mistakes interpreting the data on emotionally charged topics than the less numerate subjects.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Experts engaging in traditional peer review, providing their opinion on whether an experimental result would replicate, were right 58% of the time. A betting market in which the traders were the exact same experts and those experts had money on the line predicted correctly 71% of the time.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/okay-books/">Okay Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Slicing Pie</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202209slicingpie/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202209slicingpie/</guid>
                <pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;A very quick read. Lots of &amp;ldquo;supporting&amp;rdquo; stories up front. The pain points of issuing equity too early in a project, or too late. So what is the solution? dynamic equity. Everyone tracks their work, either per hour, or per day, depending on what is more appropriate. Everyone is given a hypothetical hourly rate. The pie is then split up based on the amount of hypothetical cash they are owed relative to the entire amount of cash owed to all participants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a fantastic way to grow a project from zero to company, without having to worry too much about over/under-compensating participants who are being compensated in equity. Of course, the story is different if there is a blend of cash &amp;amp; equity conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book has some nice heuristics to keep in mind. Like what is a fair hypothetical hourly rate. How much equity should an angel investor&amp;rsquo;s cash be given? And what to do if someone leaves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/okay-books/">Okay Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>The Psychology of Money</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202209psychologyofmoney/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202209psychologyofmoney/</guid>
                <pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2022 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;A collection of stories demonstrating that people aren&amp;rsquo;t crazy, but they do sometimes fail to make reasonable decisions with their money. Being rational with money can sometimes be the unreasonable thing to do after you&amp;rsquo;ve factored in human psychology. This book is a fantastic starting point for anyone wanting to improve their relationship with money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;favourite-quotes&#34;&gt;Favourite quotes:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;There is no reason to risk what you have and need for what you don&amp;rsquo;t have and don&amp;rsquo;t need.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Happiness, as it&amp;rsquo;s said, is just results minus expectations.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;More than I want big returns, I want to be financially unbreakable. And if I&amp;rsquo;m unbreakable, I actually think I&amp;rsquo;ll get the biggest returns, because I&amp;rsquo;ll be able to stick around long enough for compounding to work wonders.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Planning is important, but the most important part of every plan is to plan on the plan not going according to plan.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The majority of what&amp;rsquo;s happening at any given moment in the global economy can be tied back to a handful of past events that were nearly impossible to predict.&amp;rdquo; For example&amp;hellip; &amp;ldquo;9/11 prompted the fed reserve to cut interest rates, which helped drive the housing bubble, which led to the financial crisis, which led to a poor jobs market, which led tens of millions to seek a college education, leading to $1.6 trillion in student loans with a 10.8% default rate.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Sunk costs - anchoring decisions to past efforts that can&amp;rsquo;t be refunded - are a devil in a world where people change over time. They make our future selves prisoners to our past, different, selves. It&amp;rsquo;s the equivalent of a stranger making major life decisions for you.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;everything else worthwhile, successful investing demands a price. But its currency is not dollars and  cents. It&amp;rsquo;s volatility, fear, doubt, uncertainty, and regret - all of which are easy to overlook until you&amp;rsquo;re dealing with them in real time.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Like most products, the bigger the returns, the higher the price. Netflix stock returned more than 35,000% from 2002 to 2018, but traded below its previous all-time high 94% of days.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Why do so many people who are willing to pay the price of cars, houses, food, and vacations try so hard to avoid pay the price of good investment returns? The answer is simple: The price of investing success is not immediately obvious. It&amp;rsquo;s not a price tag you can see, so when the bill comes due it doesn&amp;rsquo;t feel like a fee for getting something good. It feels like a fine for doing something wrong. And while people are generally fine with paying fees, fines are supposed to be avoided.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;It sounds trivial, but thinking of market volatility as a fee rather than a fine is an important part of developing the kind of mindset that lets you stick around long enough for investing gains to work in your favor.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;What do you expect people to do when momentum creates a big short-term return potential? Sit and watch patiently? Never. That&amp;rsquo;s not how the world works. Profits will always be chased. And short-term traders operate in an area where the rules governing long-term investing - particularly around valuation - are ignored, because they&amp;rsquo;re irrelevant to the game being played.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Bubbles do their damage when long-term investors playing one game start taking their cues from those short-term traders playing another.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;You should like risk because it pays off over time. But you should be paranoid of ruinous risk because it prevents you from taking future risks that will pay off over time. Define the game you&amp;rsquo;re playing, and make sure your actions are not being influenced by people playing a different game.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;If you can meet all your goals without having to take the added risk that comes from trying to outperform the market, then what&amp;rsquo;s the point of even trying? I can afford to not be the greatest investor in the world, but I can&amp;rsquo;t afford to be a bad one. When I think of it that way, the choice to buy the index and hold on is a no-brainer for us.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/">Good Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Quantum: Einstein, Bohr, and the Great Debate about the Nature of Reality</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202209quantumgreatdebate/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202209quantumgreatdebate/</guid>
                <pubDate>Sat, 03 Sep 2022 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;For anyone who loves physics, this is a must read. The magnitude of breakthroughs in theoretical physics between the late 1800&amp;rsquo;s and early 1900&amp;rsquo;s is staggering. Kumar takes you through those breakthroughs one at a time, carefully including personal anecdotes of the great scientists as their leaps of understanding changed the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a collection of my favourite moments:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-birth-of-quantum-1900&#34;&gt;The birth of quantum (1900):&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Applying Boltzmann&amp;rsquo;s techniques, Planck discovered that he could derive his formula for the distribution of blackbody radiation only if the oscillators absorbed and emitted packets of energy that were proportional to their frequency of oscillation.&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;The problem for Planck was that Boltzmann&amp;rsquo;s procedure for slicing energy required that at the end the slices be made ever thinner until mathematically their thickness was zero and they vanished, with the whole being restored. To reunite a slice-up quantity in such a fashion was a mathematical technique at the very heart of calculus. Unfortunately forPlanck, if he did the same his formula vanished too. He was stuck with quanta, but was unconcerned. He had his formula; the rest could be sorted out later.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ref:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://hsm.stackexchange.com/questions/11725/how-to-get-to-planck-s-radiation-law-as-planck-did-it-warts-and-all&#34;&gt;https://hsm.stackexchange.com/questions/11725/how-to-get-to-planck-s-radiation-law-as-planck-did-it-warts-and-all&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://strangepaths.com/files/planck1901.pdf&#34;&gt;http://strangepaths.com/files/planck1901.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://hermes.ffn.ub.es/luisnavarro/nuevo_maletin/Planck%20(1900),%20Distribution%20Law.pdf&#34;&gt;http://hermes.ffn.ub.es/luisnavarro/nuevo_maletin/Planck%20(1900),%20Distribution%20Law.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-birth-of-photons-1905&#34;&gt;The birth of photons (1905):&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The photoelectric effect was a measure of the energy of electrons emitted when light was shown at them.  &amp;ldquo;It was expected that increasing the intensity of a light beam, by making it brighter, would yield the same number of electrons, but with each having more energy. However, the opposite was found: a greater number of electrons were emitted with no change in their individual energy.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Whereas Planck had only quantised the emission and absorption of electromagnetic radiation so that his imaginary oscillators would produce the correct spectral distribution of blackbody radiation, Einstein had quantised light itself. The energy of a quantum of yellow light was just Planck&amp;rsquo;s constant multiplied by the frequency of yellow light.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;evidence-for-atoms-1905&#34;&gt;Evidence for atoms (1905):&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Einstein realised that Brownian motion was due to water molecules regularly deviating from their &amp;rsquo;normal&amp;rsquo; behaviour as some of them got bunched up and struck the pollen together, sending it in a particular direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using this insight, Einstein succeeded in calculating the average horizontal distance a particle would travel as it zigzagged along in a given time. He predicted that in water at 17 degrees C, suspended particles with a diameter of one-thousandth of a millimetre would move on average just six-thousandths of a millimetre in one minute. Einstein had come up with a formula that offered the possibility of working out the size of atoms.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3 years later, in 1908, his predictions were confirmed, for which he received the Nobel Prize in 1926.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;more-timelines&#34;&gt;More timelines:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1911: Rutherford announces the discovery of the atomic nucleus at a meeting in Manchester, England.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1913: Bohr hears about Balmer&amp;rsquo;s formula for the spectral lines of hydrogen for the first time (Feb). He presents his new theory of the quantum atom at the British Association for the Advancement of Science (Sept).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1914: The Franck-Hertz experiment confirms Bohr&amp;rsquo;s concept of quantum jumps and atomic energy levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1916: Sommerfeld proposes a theory for the fine structure of hydrogen, and introduces a second quantum number to replace Bohr&amp;rsquo;s circular orbits with ellipticals. Einstein discovers the phenomena of spontaneous and induced emission of a photon from an atom. Sommefeld adds the magnetic quantum number to Bohr&amp;rsquo;s original atomic model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1919: Experimental evidence for general relativity is found (light deflected by gravitational fields). Einstein becomes a global celebrity overnight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1923: Scattering of X-ray photons by atomic electrons is found (the &amp;lsquo;Compton effect&amp;rsquo;), bringing irrefutable evidence in support of photons. De Broglie links waves with electrons extending wave-particle duality to incorporate matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1925: Pauli discoveres the exclusion principle. Heisenberg develops the beginning of matrix mechanics, the first theory of quantum. Goudsmit and Uhlenbeck propose the concept of quantum spin. Pauli applies matrix mechanics to the hydrogen atom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1926: Heisenberg, Born, and Jordan publish their paper on matrix mechanics. Schrodinger&amp;rsquo;s first paper on wave mechanics is published. Shrodinger and others prove that wave mechanics and matrix mechanics are mathematically equivalent. They are two forms of the same theory - &lt;strong&gt;quantum mechanics&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1927: Evidence for wave-particle duality applied to matter is found via diffracting electrons. Heisenberg discovered the uncertainty principle. Bohr presents his principle of complementarity and the central elements of what would become known as the Copenhagen interpretation of QM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;quantum-mechanics&#34;&gt;Quantum Mechanics:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Bohr-Sommerfeld quantum atom could account for the frequency of hydrogen&amp;rsquo;s spectral lines, but not how bright or dim they were. Heisenberg&amp;rsquo;s idea was to separate what was observable and what was not. The orbit of an electron around the nucleus of a hydrogen atom was not observable. So Heisenberg decided to abandon the idea of electrons orbiting the nucleus of an atom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Neils Bohr would soon argue that until an observation or measurement is made, a microphysical object like an electron does not exist anywhere. Between one measurement and the next it has no existence outside the abstract possibilities of the wave function. It is only when an observation or measurement is made that the &amp;lsquo;wave function collapses&amp;rsquo; as one of the &amp;lsquo;possible&amp;rsquo; states of the electron becomes the &amp;lsquo;actual&amp;rsquo; state of the probability of all the other possibilities become zero.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Bell was able to calculate the limits on the degree of spin correlation between pairs of entangled electrons in a Bohm-modified EPR experiment. He found that in the ethereal realm of quantum there is a greater level of correlation if QM reigns supreme than in any world that depends on hidden variables and locality. Bell&amp;rsquo;s theorem said that no local hidden variables theory could reproduce the same set of correlations as QM. Any local hidden variable theory would lead to spin correlations that generated numbers called the correlation coefficient between -2 and +2. However, for certain orientations of the spin detectors, QM predicted correlation coefficients that lay outside the range known as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scholarpedia.org/article/Bell%27s_theorem#:~:text=Bell&#39;s%20theorem%20asserts%20that%20if,at%20the%20speed%20of%20light&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;Bell&amp;rsquo;s inequality&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt; that ran from -2 to +2. (1964).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The testing of Bell&amp;rsquo;s inequality directly or indirectly helped spawn new areas of research including quantum cryptography, quantum information theory, and quantum computing. Among the most remarkable of these new fields is quantum teleportation.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-electron-microscope-1931&#34;&gt;The electron microscope (1931):&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;No particle smaller than approximately half the wavelength of white light can absorb or reflect light waves so as to make the particle visible through an ordinary microscope. However, with wavelengths more than 100,000 times smaller than that of light, electron waves could. The construction of the first commercial electron microscope began in England in 1935.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/">Good Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Outliers</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202208outliers/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202208outliers/</guid>
                <pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;For those unfamiliar with how impactful luck is in our lives, this book is an eye opener. Malcolm sheds light on how societal outliers achieved (or failed to achieve) greatness, and the role of luck in their journey. He recounts the luck of entrepreneurs in America born in the 1850’s (?), Jewish lawyers born in the 1920’s, and software engineers born in the 1950’s. The role of language &amp;amp; culture in airplane crashes, and many more interesting stories that’ll make you appreciate just how random life really is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/">Good Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>The Ride of a Lifetime</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202208rideofalifetime/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202208rideofalifetime/</guid>
                <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2022 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;A captivating recount of how Disney transformed over the past 20+ years. Bob reviews many acquisitions, and some near-misses (Disney almost bought Twitter before Disney +). A good read for anyone curious how big companies grow larger. Lots of lessons learned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;highlights&#34;&gt;Highlights:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Avoid getting into the business of manufacturing trombone oil. You may become the greatest trombone-oil manufacturer in the world, but in the end, the world only consumes a few quarts of trombone oil a year!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s a hard thing to do, especially in the moment, but those instances in which you find yourself hoping that something will work without being able to convincingly explain to yourself how it will work - that&amp;rsquo;s when a little bell should go off, and you should walk yourself through some clarifying questions. What&amp;rsquo;s the problem I need to solve? Does this solution make sense? If I&amp;rsquo;m feeling some doubt, why? Am I doing this for sound reasons or am I motivated by something personal?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;A company&amp;rsquo;s culture is shaped by a lot of things, but this is one of the most important - you have to convey your priorities clearly and repeatedly. In my experience, it&amp;rsquo;s what separates great managers from the rest.&amp;rdquo;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;You can do a lot for the morale of the people around you (and therefore the people around them) just by taking the guesswork out of their day-to-day life&amp;hellip; This is where we want to be. This is how we&amp;rsquo;re going to get there.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;My job was to set our company on a new path, and the first step was to defuse this unnecessary struggle. The easiest and most productive way to do that was to recognize that what Roy needed, ultimately, was to feel respected. That was precious to him, and it cost me and the company so little.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;This is you making a decision about them - not them as a person but the way they have performed in their job - and they need and deserve to know that it&amp;rsquo;s coming from you. You can&amp;rsquo;t make small talk once you bring someone in for that conversation. I normally say something along the lines of: &amp;lsquo;I&amp;rsquo;ve asked you to come in here for a difficult reason.&amp;rsquo; And then I try to be as direct about the issue as possible, explaining clearly and concisely what wasn&amp;rsquo;t working and why I didn&amp;rsquo;t think it was going to change. I emphasize that it was a tough decision to make, and that I understand that it&amp;rsquo;s much harder on them.&amp;rdquo;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;If you respect the person, then you owe them a clear explanation for the decision you&amp;rsquo;re making. There&amp;rsquo;s no way for the conversation not to be painful, but at least it can be honest.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;the hardest but also the most necessary lesson to keep in mind, that wherever you are along the path, you&amp;rsquo;re the same person you&amp;rsquo;ve always been.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Pessimism leads to paranoia, which leads to defensiveness, which leads to risk aversion.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;If something doesn&amp;rsquo;t feel right to you, it won&amp;rsquo;t be right for you.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/">Good Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Six Not-So-Easy Pieces</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202207sixnoteasypieces/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202207sixnoteasypieces/</guid>
                <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2022 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;This book introduces the reader to relativity, symmetry and space-time through Feynman&amp;rsquo;s eyes. He discusses features of our universe with engaging analogies, like how to distinguish right from left (which is a tricky business). Or why we have time dilation from gravity. However, I&amp;rsquo;d argue that there are better books introducing audiences to these topics nowadays, like black holes and time warps by Kip S. Thorne.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;symmetry-and-conservation-laws&#34;&gt;Symmetry and conservation laws&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;For each of the rules of symmetry there is a corresponding conservation law&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;, in quantum mechanics. For example, that laws are symmetrical for&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;translation in space = momentum is conserved&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;translation in time = energy is conserved&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;invariance under rotation = angular momentum is conserved&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;phase shift of the wave function = electrical charge is conserved&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And some are bizarre, like reflection symmetry which leads to the conservation of parity (no classical analog). However, this conservation is not conserved in matter alone. There are ways in which reflection symmetry is broken, like beta (or weak) decay. It is only with the introduction of anti-matter that the reflection symmetry is restored - and so, we say that parity is conserved under reflection and matter/antimatter symmetry. That is, &amp;ldquo;matter to the right is symmetrical with anti-matter to the left&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;bookmarked-ideas&#34;&gt;Bookmarked ideas&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If we have a particle of rest mass zero, it cannot stop. It always goes the speed c, as in the case of light. Photons have energy, without mass, by perpetually going the speed of light. [This is similar to how any object with rest mass non-zero cannot go the speed of light, without having an infinite amount of energy. Light has finite energy, with zero mass, yet always travels at the speed of light.]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One way to think of gravitational time dilation is to picture an accelerating rocket ship with a clock at the front, and back. The clock at the front will appear to run faster than the clock at the tail due to the doppler shift of light travelling between the two clocks. And since an accelerating spaceship is the same thing as earth&amp;rsquo;s gravity (equivalence principle), we can say that blocks separated by some height H will run at different speeds! The further one runs faster than the one closer to the gravitational source. Hence, gravitational time dilation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Light gains energy as it falls towards earth, and loses some as it leaves. This is true due to the conservation of energy!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/okay-books/">Okay Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>The Lifecycle of Software Objects</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202207softwarelifecycle/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202207softwarelifecycle/</guid>
                <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jul 2022 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;A short story about what our digital future might hold. We follow an ex-zoo keeper turned digital pet trainer after the zoo she worked at closed down. The world her digi-pet grew up in becomes threatened, and we see the great lengths she&amp;rsquo;ll go, along with a small community of like-minded fanatics, to give these digital humanoids a better future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/poor-books/">Poor Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>The Sovereign Individual</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202207sovereignindividual/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202207sovereignindividual/</guid>
                <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2022 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;I only skimmed this book, read about 1/3 of the content, but felt I got the gist. The authors outline what they think a future without government power will look like, as power shifts to individuals in the information age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Individuals will be able to insulate themselves from governments in ways previously impossible. Work, communications, assets, and banking systems will be fully digital, allowing life to move wherever the individual desires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this newfound autonomy, people will be free to choose their nationality, as it is the author&amp;rsquo;s belief that nations will offer nationality as a service to attract sovereign individuals. Essentially, the book describes a world where governments have fallen out of power, due to tax evasion and social uprisings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;new information technology - the fact that it transcends the tyranny of place. The new technology creates for the first time an infinite, nonterrestrial realm for economic activity. It opens an option to explore the new frontiers of the cybereconomy, to &amp;rsquo;think globally and act globally&amp;rsquo;.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, 1/5 - I would not recommend this book.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/worst-books/">Worst Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>The Bond King</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202207bondking/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202207bondking/</guid>
                <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;An interesting book for financial buffs. It reviews the origin story of active bond trading and goes through some of the details Pimco used to &amp;ldquo;generate alpha&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the nifty tricks include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;buying future contracts to meet risk requirements and then investing $ in short term bonds before the contract requires,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;betting on future volatility of the markets (upper and lower bounds),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;trading securities with itself (in differing accounts) to minimize fees,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pricing bonds more aggressively than the market to front-load performance within a fund,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and most generally, taking bets that future interest rates would be different from what &amp;ldquo;the market&amp;rdquo; was expecting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall it was an interesting read, but some parts were a little slow, and of course, you have to have an interest in bonds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/okay-books/">Okay Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Homo Deus</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202206homodeus/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202206homodeus/</guid>
                <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2022 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;Tid-bits of history sprinkled throughout a synopsis of where humanity is heading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parts of the story were interesting, as history often is, but the general arc of the book took too long, and many of the ideas have been subject to too many recent podcasts that I tended to lose interest. On the flip side, for anyone who&amp;rsquo;s not come across these ideas before (i.e., do we have free will, what do humans value, the &amp;ldquo;story&amp;rdquo; that is currency, the internet of things, etc.), I&amp;rsquo;d suggest giving this book a read. For others, I&amp;rsquo;d recommend passing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-of-my-highlighted-points-include&#34;&gt;Some of my highlighted points include:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Some 2,300 years ago, Epicurus warned his disciples that immoderate pursuit of pleasure is likely to make them miserable rather than happy.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The paradox of historical knowledge is that if the information does not change behaviour, it is useless; but if it does change behaviour, it is quickly irrelevant.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lawns were invented to display wealth as they are meaningless wastes of land that require many resources to remain pretty (thanks France!).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Anyone who has ever dealt with the tax authorities, the educational system or any complex bureaucracy knows that the truth hardly matters. What&amp;rsquo;s written on your form is far more important.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Religion is a deal, whereas spirituality is a journey.&amp;rdquo; And a dangerous one at that for religious, political, and business leaders trying to keep their human resources in order.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ending a painful experience with minor pain, or even pleasure distorts our remembered history of the event. Children&amp;rsquo;s dentists know this well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Today, having power means knowing what to ignore.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our future is increasingly one of &amp;ldquo;techo-humanism&amp;rdquo; whereby technology allows us to mediate our human desires, emotions and feelings. Humanism holds &amp;ldquo;free will&amp;rdquo; as the most important thing in the world, which complicates this newfound power. To rescue our dilemma of how to wield such power, we are moving away from a worldview that sanctifies desires/experiences, towards a new religion of &amp;ldquo;Dataism&amp;rdquo; - the worship of the creation, distribution, and utilization of data, to make the world a better place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through the lense of Dataism, democracy beat communism by being a distributed processing system, instead of centralized. As the 21&amp;rsquo;st century unfolds, the best systems for governing humans will be the one that best uses the immense amount of data our society can produce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/okay-books/">Okay Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>The Great Depression</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202206greatdepression/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202206greatdepression/</guid>
                <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;Going through a recession will never be quite the same again after reading this diary. Strange to see how many similarities exist in stock markets in such a different setting in time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humans love to speculate, and are quick to become greedy when the party is pumping. Those who like to party a little too hardy, leveraging their gains as collateral to buy more stock on margin, are almost always wiped out sooner or later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This diary has many such stories, and describes the news of the day as if it was yesterday. An interesting way to hear about life in the 1930&amp;rsquo;s and the start of WW2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/okay-books/">Okay Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>The Quick Fix</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202206quickfix/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202206quickfix/</guid>
                <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;A well researched review of the necessary skepticism established Psychology fads need. Chapters focusing on the implicit bias test, grit, the power of self-esteem, power posing, prime world (everything we do is the result of previous priming sensory input), fears over &amp;ldquo;superpredators&amp;rdquo;, and the ability for war veteran&amp;rsquo;s to overcome PTSD with mental training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all cases, simple solutions (i.e., quick fixes), would enter a cycle of over-claiming, oversimplifying, and on the back of growing momentum, minimal skepticism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only after large (sometimes massive) amounts of time and money had been spent was there enough review literature to cast doubts on the runaway fads. These fads caused more harm than good as money and time were redirected away from meaningful changes, such as better policy focused on tackling the root problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What was needed was rigorous science, pilot programs, and of course, a health dose of skepticism; which was all too easy to forget when the storytelling of these ideas fit so well into existing mental models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The future is bright however, as the field of Psychology has begun to reconcile with its replication crises and implement more statistical rigor. Finally, nudging does look to have promising effects when implemented modestly; but be careful to not over subscribe nudges as a quick fix. Tackling root problems are never as simple as they seem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/">Good Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>The Glass Castle</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202205glasscastle/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202205glasscastle/</guid>
                <pubDate>Sat, 28 May 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;A memoir of an extraordinary childhood; one where quotes like &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;d gotten pretty good at shooting the revolver by the time I was 4&amp;rdquo; is but the tip of the iceberg. Parents who disliked &amp;ldquo;the system&amp;rdquo;, and thought their misfortunes were adventures to be had. Hard times were simply hard lessons, but not worth fussing over. A true look behind the curtain at some of America&amp;rsquo;s forgotten people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/">Good Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Papillon</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202205papillon/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202205papillon/</guid>
                <pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;A wild ride through the early-mid 20th century Euro-America prison systems. Our autobiographical story is piloted by a Frenchman, who&amp;rsquo;s candour is contagious, often to his benefit, but at crucial moments, to his demise. Super fun to read; it&amp;rsquo;s a fantastical life story to be sure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/">Good Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Six Easy Pieces</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202205sixezpieces/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202205sixezpieces/</guid>
                <pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;Parts were good, but overall, a lot has changed in ~60 years to make this book more of a historical piece than a superb physics text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;bookmarked-ideas&#34;&gt;Bookmarked ideas&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As molecules evaporate, they are leaving with more energy than the average motion of the liquid they depart. Conversely, when vapour from the air joins a liquid, there is a sudden great attraction as the molecule approaches the surface, resulting in energy added. Therefore, evaporation is the loss of heat, and consensation is the the generation of some back. When these are net equal, there is no heat exchange. However, this is a nifty thing to know when cooling hot liquids. i.e., blow on hot soup.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Carbon attracts oxygen (C-O) much more than O-O or C-C. So much so, that when they come together, they snap together with such force that excess energy is distributed to their surroundings. This of course is burning, and the sensation of heat. In certain circumstances, the excess energy is given off more than molecular motion of hot gas. The energy is so great, that it &lt;em&gt;generates light&lt;/em&gt;. This is how one gets flames!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;What keeps electrons from simply falling in[to the nucleus]? This principle: If they were in the nucleus, we would know their position precisely, and the uncertainty principle would then require that they have a very large (but uncertain) momentum (and therefore energy). With this energy, they&amp;rsquo;d break away from the nucleus. They make a compromise: they leave themselves a little room for this uncertainty and then jiggle with a certain amount of minimum motion in accordance with this rule.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;cavendishs-experiment-aka-the-weighing-of-the-earth&#34;&gt;Cavendish&amp;rsquo;s experiment (aka, the weighing of the earth)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;If there is a force between any pair of objects, we ought to be able to measure the force between our own objects&amp;hellip; It was first measured by Cavendish&amp;hellip; demonstrating the direct force between two large, fixed balls of lead and two smaller balls of lead on the ends of an arm supported by a very fine fiber, called a torsion fiber. By measuring how much the fiber gets twisted, once can measure the strength of the force, verify that it is inversely proportional to the square of the distance, and determine how strong it is. Thus, one may accurately determine the coefficient G in our gravitational force equation. By knowing G from this experiement, and by knowing how strongly the earth attracts, we indirectly learned the mass of the earth!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was experiments like this that, and the simplicity of the mathematics that garnered peoples interest in science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/okay-books/">Okay Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Dopamine Nation</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202204dopaminenation/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202204dopaminenation/</guid>
                <pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;An insightful perspective on our society today, the author weaves stories of addiction throughout to illustrate how we&amp;rsquo;re easily prone to it, and how we might pull ourselves out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most insightful lesson (for me) was that pain is in fact a pleasurable time-sink, due to the pleasure-pain balance our bodies strive for. Post pain, we are often flooded with euphoric hormones to compensate. Beware of becoming addicted to pain, but, when used correctly, it is a low risk powerful stimulant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples can include: cold water sessions (I&amp;rsquo;d argue hot ones too), physical activity, caloric restriction (careful for adverse health effects), and learning something new. Ideally, we could do one thing everyday that was &amp;ldquo;painful&amp;rdquo; to help keep our pleasure-pain scale in balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Just as pain is the price we play for pleasure, so too is pleasure our reward for pain&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll add that in our high-speed dopamine-saturated society, slow activities like yoga, meditation, and aimless mind wandering can feel painful if you&amp;rsquo;re addicted to delivering results (which itself is an addiction to pain mechanism). Over time, leaning into these activities will deliver healthier pleasure too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything in moderation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-quotes&#34;&gt;Other quotes:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;In humans, high levels of physical activity in junior high, high school, and early adulthood predict lower levels of drug use. Exercise has also been shown to help those already addicted to stop or cut back.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Pain to treat pain. Anxiety to treat anxiety. This approach is counterintuitive, and exactly opposite to what we&amp;rsquo;ve been taught over the last 150 years about how to manage disease, distress, and discomfort.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The relentless pursuit of pleasure (and avoidance of pain) leads to pain.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Recovery begins with abstinence.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Abstinence resets the brain&amp;rsquo;s reward pathway and with it our capacity to take joy in simpler pleasures.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Self-binding creates literal and metacognitive space between desire and consumption, a modern necessity in our dopamine-overloaded world.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Medications can restore homeostasis, but consider what we lose by medicating away our pain.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pressing on the pain side resets our balance to the side of pleasure.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Beware of getting addicted to pain.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Radical honesty promotes awareness, enhances intimacy, and fosters a plenty mindset.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Prosocial shame&amp;rdquo; (i.e., feeling shame for transgressive behaviours where appropriate) affirms that we belong to the human tribe.&lt;/em&gt; [Not to be confused with destructive shame, which is swept under the rug, and often a negative feedback loop unto itself.]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Instead of running away from the world, we can find escape by immersing ourselves in it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/best-books/">Best Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Stolen Focus</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202204stolenfocus/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202204stolenfocus/</guid>
                <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;A must read for those itching to learn why they have a love hate relationship with technology. All ideas are presented alongside their empirical findings, including where the scientific community has a consensus, and where it does not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of these ideas are present in other self help books, like: sleep more, eat well, work less, and make time for slowness (yoga, meditation, nature walks without audio) and play. But the studies and storytelling in this book make it worthwhile nonetheless for those who are already familiar with this list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Life begins at the edge of your comfort zone&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;on-relating-to-others&#34;&gt;On relating to others:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s worth thinking deeply about how other people live and how their minds work. They have complex inner lives, just like you.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found this idea particularly interesting. How there is research that the more fiction novels you read, the better you are (on average) at reading other people&amp;rsquo;s emotions (but not for nonfiction). This improvement in our ability to empathize was also found in children who consumed more long-format TV series, or movies. But not shorter shows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This helps explain why our societies are becoming ever more divided. Our media is continuing to become compressed, from TV series, to YouTube, down to Tik Tok. It&amp;rsquo;s no wonder people have less empathy for each other than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;technology-has-overrun-us&#34;&gt;Technology has overrun us:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It used to be that technology was created to be an extension of us. That is what a paintbrush is, or a musical instrument. In a way, so too are light bulbs (light to be together, or engage with ___), automobiles (moving us faster from A to B), or the internet (connecting us to those far away).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But our internet giants have discovered their recommendation systems can keep us scrolling forever. Keeping us engaged with content that we don&amp;rsquo;t realize is influencing us. Making us less empathetic (see section above). Causing us to move faster. Multitask more. All in the name of engagement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keeping people in the digital realms is good for business. But it&amp;rsquo;s making us less human. I&amp;rsquo;d argue, more so than any previous innovation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;basic-takeaways&#34;&gt;Basic takeaways:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slow down, do one thing at a time, sleep more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove noise from your environment. (don&amp;rsquo;t live within 50 meters of a major road!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mind wander more. Especially in a forest.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find your flow states.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduce 4 day work weeks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let kids run around, explore, and think for themselves.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;some-bookmarked-ideas&#34;&gt;Some Bookmarked ideas&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yoga, meditation, walking in the forest, etc. are incredible practices to train your attention and focus. &amp;ldquo;Slowness nurtures attention, and speed shatters it&amp;rdquo;.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;I realized that my desire to absorb a tsunami of information without losing my ability to focus was like my desire to eat at McDonald&amp;rsquo;s every day and stay trim - an impossible dream.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;There&amp;rsquo;s broad scientific evidence that if you are sitting in a noisy room, your ability to pay attention deteriorates, and your work gets worse&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;We often seek relief from distraction by crashing (say in front of a TV). But if you only break away from distraction into rest - if you don&amp;rsquo;t replace it with a positive goal, you are striving toward - you will always be pulled back to distraction sooner or later. &lt;strong&gt;The more powerful path out of distraction is to find your flow&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;When people are kept awake, one of the first things to go is their ability to focus.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mind wandering is a different form of attention - and a necessary one.&amp;rdquo;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;In situations of low stress and safety, mind-wandering will be a gift, a pleasure, a creative force. In situations of high stress or danger, mind-wandering will be a torment.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;In Canada, a study found that people who lived within 50 meters of a major road were 15 percent more likely to develop dementia than people who did not.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/">Good Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>The Bomber Mafia</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202204bombermafia/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202204bombermafia/</guid>
                <pubDate>Sun, 17 Apr 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;A masterclass in storytelling. I found it hard to put this book down from start to finish. As the title says, this book follows the evolution of America&amp;rsquo;s bomber mafia, a group of pilots who helped create the Air Force. We learn about their military decisions, shortcomings, success, and the ending of WW2. An interesting story told by one of the greatest storytellers of our time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/best-books/">Best Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>There There</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202204therethere/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202204therethere/</guid>
                <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;Some beautifully written passages that were thought provoking in the way good poetry often is; however the book overall wasn&amp;rsquo;t as captivating of a story as I&amp;rsquo;d hoped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unique storytelling in how the chapters were constructed, but I found it hard to build up empathy for any one character, and found myself loosing steam in the middle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conclusion however was worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/okay-books/">Okay Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>The Power of Now</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202203powerofnow/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202203powerofnow/</guid>
                <pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;A book about spirituality accessed by focusing your attention on the present. Written in the late 90&amp;rsquo;s, this book seems ahead of its time regarding the power of mindfulness. However, the author extends the benefits of mindfulness into the mystical realm of God, which might resonate with some folks, but harder for an atheist (like me) to digest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/okay-books/">Okay Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Less Is More</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202202lessismore/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202202lessismore/</guid>
                <pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;How degrowth will save the world&amp;rdquo;. This book describes how we might move away from a constantly growing economy, to one that is decelerating, without harming the people who live in it, and in fact, improving their lives along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get us there, the &amp;ldquo;upper class 1%&amp;rdquo; will suffer; they won&amp;rsquo;t be able to consume at the current multiplier they enjoy. But they too will benefit from a healthier way of life, and a society that is more inclusive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main benefactor will be our planet, and our ancestors, who&amp;rsquo;ll inherit a world that narrowly escaped an ecological disaster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A possible path forward would be the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;end planned obsolences (stop creating purposefully fragile objects),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cut advertising (stop nudging people to buy things they don&amp;rsquo;t need),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;shift from ownership to usership,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;end food waster, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;scale down ecologically destructive industries (and have the remaining industries scale down working hours to make room for the newly unemployed).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My gripe with this book is that the author calls on capitalism as the culprit. IMO, the culprit is poorly insulated governments who aren&amp;rsquo;t able to enact resilient policies that&amp;rsquo;d make this degrowth possible. We need better political infrastructure, not an end to capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/">Good Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Educated</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202202educated/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202202educated/</guid>
                <pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;A gripping story of being raised without traditional education, and the impact that had on Tara as she discovers a world beyond her childhood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found this book hard to put down. I highly recommend it to anyone looking for a non-fiction story that&amp;rsquo;ll transport you to another world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/best-books/">Best Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Noise: A flaw in Human Judgment</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202110noise/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202110noise/</guid>
                <pubDate>Thu, 07 Oct 2021 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;This book opened my eyes to the differences between bias and noise, and how they are equally proportional to disrupting our desired outcome. That is to say, imagine missing a target by some random &amp;ldquo;noisy&amp;rdquo; amount, which widens the bell curve of outcomes. The distance, on average, away from the target result would be just as bad as an equal error magnitude in bias. The only difference being that the bias is easier to see, because it is clustering away from the target. Thus, bias is often the focus in reducing error for our desired outcomes, when really, it should be considered equally with noise, if our goal is error reduction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simple techniques for reducing error through noise include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a noise audit,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;collecting multiple opinions (even yourself multiple times), without priming the answer of individuals, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;regularly measuring noise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;three-principles-of-decision-hygiene&#34;&gt;Three Principles of Decision Hygiene&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Resist premature intuitions.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Think like a statistician.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Accuracy, not individual expression.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See a quick summary of these ideas &lt;a href=&#34;https://productcoalition.com/three-principles-for-making-better-decisions-cbcb3bbea956&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, or review the book for greater detail!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/best-books/">Best Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Braiding Sweetgrass</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202107braidingsweetgrass/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202107braidingsweetgrass/</guid>
                <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jul 2021 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;Note: I only read ~50% of this book. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t captivated by the content my first time through, which might be why I only rated this a 3/5. I should like to try again one day, as I know many people who say this is one of their favourite books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stories of indigenous wisdom, woven with scientific thinking, told in a North American setting. Many beautiful lessons to be had here, like how our language shapes our relationship with the environment. For example, the personification of nature in indigenous tongues, and the naturefication of human actions is indicative of their relationship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other lessons include regenerative farming techniques, deep respect for the land and ecosystem you depend on, spending time in nature, and the mystery of pecan trees who drop all their nuts at the same time as if in contact with one another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/okay-books/">Okay Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Physics of the Impossible</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202106physicsimpossible/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202106physicsimpossible/</guid>
                <pubDate>Wed, 19 May 2021 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;A physics book unlike any other I&amp;rsquo;ve read. Reality is distorted by the mind-bending possibilities of physics that are beyond our reach. Sometimes, the physics has been proven, but we&amp;rsquo;re missing technological advances necessary to bring it to life, other times, it&amp;rsquo;s physics that might truly be impossible. In either case, the idea&amp;rsquo;s themselves are delightful to consume. Some minds are truly special.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;bookmarked-ideas&#34;&gt;Bookmarked ideas&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A tidal wave of commercial applications could be set off if we create room-temperature superconductors. Magnetic fields a million times stronger than that of the earth could become commonplace.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Levitation for zero friction movement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since water is a diamagnet, it too can levitate in the presence of a powerful magnetic field. Scientists have levitated small animals, like frogs, for example.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Negative energy is real! The Casimir effect - the pressure felt by two parallel (neutral) plates in a vacuum by &amp;ldquo;virtual particles&amp;rdquo;. When these plates are brought close together, you can extract energy out of the system&amp;rsquo;s mutual attraction. Predicted in 1933, and proven in 1948, the attractive force was precisely measured in 1996 to be miniscule, 1/30,000 the weight of an ant.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are exotic solutions to relativity whereby stable wormholes can be created that transport you to other universes, or transversable wormholes where you can pass back and forth freely. The problem with these exotic solutions is that they require a fabulous amount of positive and negative matter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-founder-of-antimatter-tldr&#34;&gt;The founder of antimatter (TL;DR)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A longer version of this can be found in the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul Dirac noticed that Schrödinger&amp;rsquo;s equations failed to work with the theory of relativity. In 1928, he proposed a radical reformulation (now called Dirac&amp;rsquo;s equation) that satisfied both, using a mathematical object called spinors. Additionally, these new equations showed that E = mc^2 no longer holds. Rather, it is E = +/- mc^2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The implications of this mathematics is considered one of the greatest triumphs in theoretical physics. Not only did this new formulation predict anti-matter, which was then discovered a few years &lt;em&gt;later&lt;/em&gt;, it also provided a theoretical justification for the fundamental phenomenon of spin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/best-books/">Best Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Delivering Happiness</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202105deliveringhappiness/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202105deliveringhappiness/</guid>
                <pubDate>Mon, 03 May 2021 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;A dot-com winner, then loser, then back to the top story. Lots of building-a-business advice from a very unique person. A lot of his focus is on the customer, and internal culture. Sorta changed my perception of what a &amp;ldquo;head of culture&amp;rdquo; can even do at a company. Namely, they can facilitate an environment to help people connect, but that could be very different for each person, and at the end of the day, culture is what is &lt;em&gt;felt&lt;/em&gt; by each person. The collective average being that which is its core, but truly, it&amp;rsquo;s just a feeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;bookmarked-ideas&#34;&gt;Bookmarked ideas&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Share what you&amp;rsquo;ve learned with others.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Look for opportunities beyond just the game you sat down to play. You never know who you&amp;rsquo;re going to meet, including new friends for life or new business contacts.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Have fun. The game is a lot more enjoyable when you&amp;rsquo;re trying to do more than just make money.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;[Creating a] culture book is not about the book&amp;hellip; it&amp;rsquo;s about the culture.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;What&amp;rsquo;s the best way to build a brand for the long term? In a word: culture. At Zappos, our belief is that if you get the culture right, most of the other stuff - customer service, long-term brand, etc. will happen naturally&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/">Good Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Shoe Dog</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202103shoedog/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202103shoedog/</guid>
                <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2021 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;A novel that&amp;rsquo;ll transport you back to a decade quite unlike today. Not only was there no Nike, there wasn&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;athleisure&amp;rdquo; or jogging for fun. The story on it&amp;rsquo;s own is hard to put down, but the way it&amp;rsquo;s told makes this a truly joyful read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;bookmarked-ideas&#34;&gt;Bookmarked ideas&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Don&amp;rsquo;t tell people how to do things, tell them what to do and let them surprise you with their results.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;[To help young entrepreneurs,] I&amp;rsquo;d tell them to hit pause, think long and hard about how they want to spend their time, and with whom they want to spend it for the next forty years. I&amp;rsquo;d tell men and women in their mid twenties not to settle for a job or a profession or even a career. Seek a calling. Even if you don&amp;rsquo;t know what that means, seek it. If you&amp;rsquo;re following your calling, the fatigue will be easier to bear, the disappointment will be fuel, the highs will be like nothing you&amp;rsquo;ve ever felt.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/best-books/">Best Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Atomic Habits</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202101atomichabits/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202101atomichabits/</guid>
                <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;Very engaging book. In addition to learning about the power of habits, you&amp;rsquo;ll also learn to recognize what parts of your life are good/bad habits and how to build/break them. It&amp;rsquo;s a solid framework for everyone to understand, regardless of your goals. Best of all, this book keeps you engaged from chapter 1 with well told anecdotes and analogies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-takeaways&#34;&gt;My takeaways:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small changes often appear to make no difference, until you&amp;rsquo;ve crossed some critical threshold. A hallmark feature of compounding gains. You need to be patient.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To improve your results, focus on your system, not the goals themselves.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To improve your system, focus on your identity. You become your habits. Therefore, changing your habits requires you to change your identity. Are you someone who wants to do X, or are you someone who is doing X?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any habit can be broken down into a 4-step feedback loop: que, craving, response, and reward. To effectively change behaviour, simply target one of the 4 parts of the feedback loop: i) make it obvious; ii) make it attractive; iii) make it easy; iv) make it satisfying.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Point &amp;amp; call the action to make it clear what is happening &amp;amp; its consequences. I.e., I am opening a new tab and typing &amp;ldquo;r&amp;rdquo; out of habit, this will take me to reddit if I press enter where I&amp;rsquo;ll have some fun but likely spend too much time and regret having come in the first place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use &lt;strong&gt;habit stacking&lt;/strong&gt; to chain new habits to existing ones. i.e., After I close my laptop for the day, I&amp;rsquo;ll immediately do 20 minutes of language homework.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a complete list of habit strategies, checkout the &lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/jamesclear/Atomic+Habits/Habits+Cheat+Sheet.pdf&#34;&gt;Atomic Habits cheat sheet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;habits-work-best-applied-to-your-strengths&#34;&gt;Habits work best applied to your strengths:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your strengths are a cross between your genetics &amp;amp; your interests. What doesn&amp;rsquo;t feel like work to you? What are you naturally predisposed to being great at?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, I think I&amp;rsquo;m great at communicating a goal to a team, organizing the team&amp;rsquo;s energy and focus to tackle the problem quickly. Allowing for new thoughts to form, connecting dots, and listening to others while creating a space that allows others to speak up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a behaviour strength, which I&amp;rsquo;ve slowly come to learn about the more teamwork I&amp;rsquo;ve done. A personality test could have helped me uncover it too, but in general, it&amp;rsquo;s always good to be doing some &amp;ldquo;exploring&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, when you&amp;rsquo;ve found a regime that fits you well, you can &amp;ldquo;exploit&amp;rdquo; it, for accelerated gains compared to your peers. This process is known as &amp;ldquo;explore vs. exploit&amp;rdquo;. You should always have a bit of both in your life; likely more explore while your young, and exploit once you&amp;rsquo;ve found your groove.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/best-books/">Best Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>How I Invest My Money</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202012investmoney/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202012investmoney/</guid>
                <pubDate>Sun, 27 Dec 2020 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;A collection of financial industry darlings speak openly about how they invest their money. Often aligning with the products they&amp;rsquo;ve worked on, but not always. It&amp;rsquo;d be nice to have more books openly discuss this topic to showcase the complexities of investing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;bookmarked-ideas&#34;&gt;Bookmarked ideas&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;EquityZen is an interesting platform that allows for pre-IPO shares to be traded.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;your money is a wonderful servant and a terrible master&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/okay-books/">Okay Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>The Almanack of Naval Ravikant</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202012almanack/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202012almanack/</guid>
                <pubDate>Tue, 22 Dec 2020 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;A collection of Naval Ravikant&amp;rsquo;s tweetstorms, discussions, and ideas woven into a digestible &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.navalmanack.com/&#34;&gt;ebook&lt;/a&gt;. The ideas focus on wealth on happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of my favourite ideas:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tweetstorm-about-wealth-creation&#34;&gt;Tweetstorm about wealth creation:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Seek wealth, not money or status. Wealth is having assets that earn while you sleep. Money is how we transfer time and wealth. Status is your place in the social hierarchy&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understand ethical wealth creation is possible. If you secretly despise wealth, it will elude you&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ignore ppl playing status games. They gain status by attacking ppl playing wealth creation games&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;re not going to get rich renting out your time. You must own equity&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will get rich by giving society what it wants but does not yet know how to get. At scale&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pick an industry where you can play long-term games with long-term ppl&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The internet has massively broadened the possible space of careers. Most ppl haven&amp;rsquo;t figured this out yet&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Play iterated games. All returns in life, whether in wealth, relationships, or knowledge, from compound interest&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pick your business partners with high intelligence, energy, and, above all, integrity&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t partner with cynics and pessimists. Their beliefs are self-fulfilling&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn to sell. Learn to build. If you can do both, you will be unstoppable&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arm yourself with specific knowledge, accountability, and leverage&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specific knowledge is knowledge you cannot be trained for, found by pursuing your genuine curiosity and passion rather than whatever is hot right now&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building specific knowledge will feel like play to you, but look like work to others&amp;hellip; and is taught through apprenticeships, not school&amp;hellip; often highly technical or creative, it cannot be outsourced or automated&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Embrace accountability, and take business risks under your own name. Society will reward you with responsibility, equity, and leverage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunes require leverage. Business leverage comes from capital, people, and products with no marginal cost of replication (code &amp;amp; media). Code and media are permissionless leverage. They&amp;rsquo;re the leverage behind the newly rich. You can create software and media that works for you while you sleep&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Avoid business magazines and business classes. Study microeconomics, game theory, psychology, persuasion, ethics, math and computers&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading is faster than listening. Doing is faster than watching&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should be too busy to &amp;ldquo;do coffee&amp;rdquo; while still keeping an uncluttered calendar&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Set and enforce an aspirational personal hourly rate. If fixing a problem will save less than your hourly rate, ignore it. If outsourcing a task will cost less than your hourly rate, outsource it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Become the best in the world at what you do. Keep redefining what you do until this is true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you&amp;rsquo;re finally wealthy, you&amp;rsquo;ll realize it wasn&amp;rsquo;t what you were seeking in the first place. But that is for another day.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;find-a-position-of-leverage&#34;&gt;Find a position of leverage:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;the CEO job is really a financial job.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Capital scales very, very well. If you get good at managing capital, you can manage more and more capital much more easily than you can manage more and more people.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;the most democratic form [of leverage]&amp;hellip; is products with no marginal cost of replication. This includes books, media, movies, and code. Code is probably the most powerful form of permissionless leverage.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-get-lucky&#34;&gt;How to get lucky:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hope luck finds you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hustle until you stumble into it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prepare the mind and be sensitive to chances others miss.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Become the best at what you do. Refine what you do until this is true. Opportunity will seek you out. Luck becomes your destiny.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An extreme example of this last form of luck, as described in the book, is the following: &amp;ldquo;suppose you&amp;rsquo;re the best person in the world at deep-sea diving. You&amp;rsquo;re known to take dives no one else will dare attempt. By sheer luck, someone finds a sunken treasure they cannot get. Their luck has just become your luck, as they&amp;rsquo;re going to come to you.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;mental-models&#34;&gt;Mental models&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Simple heuristic: if you&amp;rsquo;re evenly split on a difficult decision, take the path more painful in the short term.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;wrapping-up&#34;&gt;Wrapping up&amp;hellip;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Learn to love to read&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Happiness is being satisfied with what you have&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And an incredibly long list of book recommendations that I&amp;rsquo;m working through slowly&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/">Good Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>The Hard thing about Hard Things</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202012hardthings/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202012hardthings/</guid>
                <pubDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2020 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;A brutally honest take on the challenges faced when trying to build a company. A fantastic story of the compromises a CEO might face, and why being an entrepreneur is so hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/">Good Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>The Alchemist</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202010thealchemist/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202010thealchemist/</guid>
                <pubDate>Mon, 26 Oct 2020 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;A bit dated, this book remains a captivating story of the human condition. Seeking an outcome for fulfillment:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s the possibility of having a dream come true that makes life interesting, he thought, as he looked again at the position of the sun, and hurried his pace.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the story takes the reader through relatable ups-and-downs, occasional magic, and a satisfying ending.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/">Good Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Stamped From The Beginning</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202009stampedfromthebeginning/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202009stampedfromthebeginning/</guid>
                <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;I agree with the book&amp;rsquo;s subtitle, this is definitely a mammoth overview of racist ideas in America. Starting with the racists ideas of colonial Europe that seeded the founding father, or white-religous-upperclassmen, as is more appropriate, up to Barack Obama, and some of the racist ideas he pondered aloud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to educate yourself on how poorly Black Americans have been treated by their peers and the policies in their society, look no further. It is a little long, but comes together quite nicely in the end. And it&amp;rsquo;s on Spotify as an audio book!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-key-takeaway&#34;&gt;My key takeaway&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, to talk of a person as being different from the rest of society because of something about their race/sex/gender/age/etc., rather than their environment, is wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I agree with the premise, and it is interesting to catch yourself being X-ist whenever you think thoughts upon a group. &lt;strong&gt;No individual should be stamped from the beginning&lt;/strong&gt;. And, as discussed by Malcom Gladwell in &lt;a href=&#34;https://cartar.github.io./books/talking2strangers/#my-favourite-takeaways&#34;&gt;Talking to Strangers&lt;/a&gt;, you SHOULD consider an individual&amp;rsquo;s environment. Think about how their environment has shaped them before concluding what is a reasonable thought, or conducting your behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-discussion&#34;&gt;A discussion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d like to start at the end. Ibram X. Kendi concludes with the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;There will come a time when principled anti-racists are in power, and then anti-racist policies become the law of the land, and then anti-racists ideas become the common sense of the people, and the anti-racists common sense of the people hold their anti-racists leaders and policies accountable.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wholeheartedly agree. And like to think many people in power have thought themselves anti-racists, but, to this book&amp;rsquo;s credit, not been. Ibram shows exactly why not:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Self-interest leads to racist policies, leads to racist ideas, which leads to ignorance and hate.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is it that people elected into positions of power, literally charged to be other-interested, fail so miserably? Ibram claims it is because power is inherently self-interested. Power cannot make decisions that are against its self-interest. Otherwise, the power is lost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is true. However, his solutions: i) to educate those without power to band together and grow in strength, and ii) that non-white-religous-upperclassmen who are self-interested should fight for anti-racisms because it is the precursor to humanity for all, are remist. Both of these solutions are principled to the same ideas that lead the founding fathers. Namely, together, we are strong enough to take power from the powerful and only then will there be peace for all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t get me wrong, I agree that &amp;ldquo;when we fight for humanity, we are fighting for ourselves.&amp;rdquo; And that we need principled anti-racists in power. And that we need to educate those without power the most of all. But the largest problem I see is not that education doesn&amp;rsquo;t work; it&amp;rsquo;s that our political system has totally fucked up incentives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us posit the job of our politicians to be caring for the entire population under their control, and the earth as a whole. That&amp;rsquo;s a tall order for any single person, so our politicians will need to work together to get the job done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, there are many people involved, and to make progress will require alignment. Alignment of ideas requires, from time to time, the odd mind to be changed. This IS education. However, the problem arises whenever a needed solution is radically different from the accepted culture of the time. It is these moments that the powerful must decide between 2 choices:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Push through a solution that degrades their influence with a majority of people, thus leading to their removal from power&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compromise a solution that neither fixes the problem, nor lose too much favor with the public such that they keep power (for now)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the balancing act we ask of politicians, who rose to power off the piggy banks of individuals whose influence is yet another factor for the person in charge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we need most of all is a new incentive system for our politicians. We need to remove donations from politicians&amp;rsquo; bank roles. We need to incentivize quality decisions that positively affect those who are losing the most, as measured by third parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need reform of those who do the reforming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe education does work, we just need the right incentives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/">Good Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>The Silk Roads</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202006silkroads/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202006silkroads/</guid>
                <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2020 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;This book is an epic undertaking, showcasing world history up to the early 2010&amp;rsquo;s, through the lense of the silk road. History has many authors, and this book does well to capture their ideas in a cohesive framework. The thesis presented here outlines how resource transportation routes shaped our world history. Equally important to the goods flowing through commerce were new ideas, including religions, and a massive game of political chess. Short term policies crafted to maintain power at the expense of those without it, often led to self destruction through overreach (and over spending). Worse still was the long term instability created by dying powers&amp;rsquo; abrupt departure from battleground regions. The most shocking lesson I took away is how cyclical our world history is. The fight for power, and abhorrent disregard for others by those trying to maintain it, is the saddest trait we share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book starts off slow, but is worth persevering through. It started about 2000 years ago, with the empire of Persia, and the creation of the silk roads. From there, the rise and fall of new and old players, in a dance of power politics and war is spectacular. I hope one day we&amp;rsquo;ll learn from our history, and end the senseless killing of those who are simply trying their best to get by.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-key-takeaways&#34;&gt;My key takeaways&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How a world with hundreds of religions is reduced to a few&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why the middle east is so unstable, well into the 21st century&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The luck involved to create a golden era
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How quickly that era falls when the KingPin dies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All empires at the top of the totem pole eventually fall
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The cause of their downfall is often overspending on military:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Roman empire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Portugal/Spain in the 15th &amp;amp; 16th century&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;England in the 17th-20th century&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The human cost required to sustain an empire is terrible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And most importantly, &lt;strong&gt;how frequently history repeats itself&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/best-books/">Best Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Alex’s Adventures in Numberland</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202004alexadventurenumberland/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202004alexadventurenumberland/</guid>
                <pubDate>Sat, 25 Apr 2020 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;This book was truly a wonderful read! If you want to learn about math&amp;rsquo;s history, you will love this book &amp;#x1f495;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You do not need to have a strong background in math to get the full punch from this story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-favourite-takeaways&#34;&gt;My favourite takeaways&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;regression-to-the-mean&#34;&gt;Regression to the mean&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regression to the mean is the concept that, over time, event likelihood converges on the average result. Said another way, whenever an outlier occurs, there&amp;rsquo;s a good chance that the next event will be closer to the main outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This idea has interesting implications within the workplace. Manager&amp;rsquo;s are stung when praising outstanding work that is followed by normal work; whereas chastising bad work is usually followed by better performance. However, neither the praise nor the reprimand likely had as large of an effect as regression to the mean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;normal-distribution&#34;&gt;Normal Distribution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The normal distribution is the result of randomness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whenever you see a normal distribution not caused by randomness, be suspicious.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you carefully measure something, if you do not see a normal distribution where randomness should occur (i.e., measurement error), you have likely destroyed the randomness that should be present.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/best-books/">Best Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Talking to Strangers</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202003talking2strangers/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202003talking2strangers/</guid>
                <pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;Using a mix of data and in-depth investigations around high profile human interactions, where human behaviour is interpreted terribly, we learn some very important lessons. As usual, Malcolm Gladwell delivers these stories in a wonderful read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-favourite-takeaways&#34;&gt;My favourite takeaways&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Defaulting to the truth is OK. It is what created our society and it would be stupid to override this companionship generating trait.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The coupling of environment and action is so strong that it should always be taken into account when interacting with strangers.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t judge a stranger, judge their environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are bad lie detectors. We expect a liar to act one way, and a truth teller another. Our snap decision lie detection is never to be trusted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/best-books/">Best Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>The Personal MBA</title>
                <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202002mypersonalmba/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://cartar.github.io./books/202002mypersonalmba/</guid>
                <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2020 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
                
                    <author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
                
                <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
                
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed this book, but am hesitant to recommend it to others. The writing is only OK, and so much of the content felt somewhat common sense. However, I did find multiple nuggets worth keeping!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-favourite-takeaways&#34;&gt;My favourite takeaways&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;prototyping&#34;&gt;Prototyping&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When developing a business, iteration and feedback are key. Offering a pre-order with full access to the witten Prototype (description of what is being offered) is ideal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If no one wants to pre-order a free prototype your offer is not valuable enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;reorganization&#34;&gt;Reorganization&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Random actions change things. Attempt to reorganize ideas is our body&amp;rsquo;s way of searching for solutions. When reference levels are violated, and we do not know what action to take next, try reorganization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simulations in your brain only works well with a goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;environment&#34;&gt;Environment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Easiest way to change things is by changing your environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;reference-levels&#34;&gt;Reference Levels&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humans do not have easily manipulated behavior. We are too complex for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather we have reference levels that, when out of whack, force us to make change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;reinterpretation&#34;&gt;Reinterpretation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you want to change your beliefs (or mental stimuli) simply follow:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recall that belief in as much detail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Think of alternative interpretations for that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Realize your belief is an interpretation, not fact.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discard your belief.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose an alternative interpretation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;motivation&#34;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either moving towards or away from things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We evolved to prioritize moving away, which makes sense from our ancestors point-of-view, but doesn&amp;rsquo;t serve us as well today. Understand this emotional tug-of-war when making decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we prioritize moving away, we focus on what is being lost. This can make us fearful of change, because we aren&amp;rsquo;t understanding the complete picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;selection-test&#34;&gt;Selection Test&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Environmental constraints that determine which systems can be self perpetuating and which ones die.
Know the selection tests for a market and you can change the field; especially as markets change due to tech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                
                
                
                
                
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./categories/good-books/">Good Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            
                                
                                
                                
                                    <category domain="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/">Books</category>
                                
                            
                        
                    
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
