<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Okay Books on Will Cartar&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://cartar.github.io./categories/okay-books/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Okay Books on Will Cartar&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <managingEditor>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</webMaster>
    <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2024 15:11:44 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://cartar.github.io./categories/okay-books/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Age of the City</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202402ageofthecity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Feb 2024 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202402ageofthecity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Even as someone who isn&amp;rsquo;t a city planner, I found many of the chapters somewhat obvious. The challenge of climate change in cities, or increased risk of novel viruses for example. However, I did enjoy the book; not dissimilar to a good economist article, the ideas were well written, and the story easy to follow. Just not enough &amp;ldquo;Aha&amp;rdquo; moments I suppose.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Brief Answers to the Big Questions</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202310briefanswerstobigquestions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202310briefanswerstobigquestions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A fun reminder of the wonders of our universe, guided by one of the most astonishing minds of the last century. My favourite parts were the forward, introduction, and prelude &amp;ldquo;why we must ask the big questions&amp;rdquo;, but that is because the reminder of the book reviewed ideas that I&amp;rsquo;m familiar with. It is remarkable that Stephen could write this book in his last year of life, given his limited ability to express himself (just some facial muscles by that point). That, mixed with his discussions about black holes, the beginning of the universe, and various other areas where our knowledge is incomplete were what made this book worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Infinite Game</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202308infinitegame/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Aug 2023 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202308infinitegame/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This book is great for anyone leading a company, and good for those wanting to know if they&amp;rsquo;re a part of an organization that is in it for the long haul. The basic premise is that companies without a proper &lt;em&gt;Just Cause&lt;/em&gt;, and various other attributes, will at one point or another, succumb to their short sightedness, and fail. There are many examples to draw on, where companies prioritize profit over their purpose, and end up losing out to the inevitable innovation of competition.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Five Most Important Questions</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202302questions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2023 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202302questions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A dated book that feels a little ahead of it&amp;rsquo;s time. Certainly still relevant today, it is full of anecdotes about why the 5 questions outlined below are so crucial to success for any organization (private, public, non-profit, etc.). But really, if you agree that the five questions are valuable, you don&amp;rsquo;t need to read the book so much as do the exercise. However, the book is a quick 2 hour read (or less), so you don&amp;rsquo;t lose much giving it a spin!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flush</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202212flush/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2022 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202212flush/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;An interesting review of how useful our poop is, the current science of capturing that information, and what is going on on the inside to cause our stool to look the way it does.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The main takeaways are:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re constipated - you&amp;rsquo;re absorbing too much water, drink more.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If you have diarrhea - you&amp;rsquo;re losing a lot of water, drink more.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If your poop experience is poor, try&amp;hellip;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;eating more fiber, but ramp up slowly as you might not have the right mix of microbes at the start.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;boosting the diversity of your microbiome by eating plain yogurt (daily), and fermented foods like kimchi or kombucha.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;When you travel, expect to have a bad time - best to prepare your microbiome beforehand with the above tips.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-other-notes-i-took&#34;&gt;Some other notes I took:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;useful&#34;&gt;Useful&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Overuse of laxatives in general can decrease absorption of nutrients and other medications, cause electrolyte imbalances, create dependency and actually worsen constipation by interfering with the colon’s natural contractions.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Yellow and greasy suggest not digesting fat well; and that evaluation for celiac disease or another cause of malabsorption is warranted.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Green stool could be food passing too quickly and not giving your bile a chance to break down into brown colour;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Black could be bleeding in upper tract or black licorice&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Red could be beets or bleeding in lower tract - often hemorrhoids but sometimes more seriously colon cancer&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;White or clay-coloured / devoid of colour from bile suggests a blockage in a duct that carries bile from liver to gallbladder -&amp;gt; in infants is life threatening if not corrected&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Constipation can tear the main intestinal lining and cause anal fissures. Intense pressure on the colon can cause diverticulitis (inflamed or infected pouches of gut tissue), hemorrhoids (akin to varicose veins; also can be from prolonged sitting on the pot), to more serious conditions like defecation syncope (fainting on the toilet), or even a stroke.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Posture modification on the toilet can reduce strain and encourage a more complete evacuation.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;When ramping up on fiber, if you didn’t already eat a lot of fiber, you’ll need to ramp up slowly, to avoid stomach cramps (as it’s unlikely you have the right fiber-munching bacteria to begin with). Slow and steady can cultivate the microbiome you seek, and adding fermented foods / yogurt can do wonders too.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The bacteria sometimes take time to ramp up the right metabolic pathways or fiber-processing genes. In artificial guts, you see bacteria don’t degrade the fiber as much on the first day compared to the next.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Microbiome disruptions like: food poisoning, international travel, and dietary changes are all associated with shifts in gut flora.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Sometimes, these changes can introduce totally new species that sometimes wipe out weaker competition. However, it is usually the case that the system as a whole preserves their functionality - like digesting carbohydrates.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;This is where food sensitivity tests, and microbiome lab tests (stool testing) fall short. It’s an expensive snapshot of your current system that will need to be done again in the near future.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Eating a diet rich in fermented foods like: yogurt, kimchi, and kombucha tea for many weeks shows signs of improved gut microbiome diversity and reduced signs of inflammation compared to counterparts on a high-fiber diet.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;“The bacteria food alone isn’t enough; we need the bacteria that can eat it.”&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Caution: nothing is guaranteed. What works for others won’t necessarily work for you&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;less-useful-but-noteworthy&#34;&gt;Less useful, but noteworthy&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Constipation - colon absorbs too much water. 15 major classes of drugs can cause constipation, according to one tally, even tylenol can stop things up&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Many drugs cause diarrhea by increasing intestinal muscle movements that push everything onwards. Allergies, infections, contaminated or overly spicy food can trigger an immune response to flush out the system. Can be from IBS, lactose intolerance, diseases, drugs or damage can inflame or tear the intestinal lining, interfering with water absorption that makes matters worse.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Some researchers claim timing transit is more important than Bristol stool scale.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Median is 29 hours. Range is 4 hours - 10 days&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Longer transit time associated with greater gut diversity -&amp;gt; not sure how well studied this is&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And greater diversity isn’t always a good thing -&amp;gt; if that diversity includes an unfavourable mix.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;C-section + instant formula over vagina birth + breastfeeding alter microbiome in ways that increase the risk of asthma and allergies.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Babies exposed to a broader diversity of microbes are more protected and have lower risk of bad lifelong health outcomes&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Think of your microbiome as your mini ecosystem for which you are the caretaker. * If you eat poorly, don’t prioritise sleep, exercise, and a balanced lifestyle, your microbiome is likely to get out of balance.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;not-useful-but-cool&#34;&gt;Not useful, but cool&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;German made: Flachspuler - or flat-flush toilet, helps people examine their stool before being flushed&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;People in the US eat about 30-35% of the fiber that they should - which makes the average deposit in western toilets a fraction of what they should be&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Lots of applications for measuring specific biomarkers like proteins, carbohydrates, fats, and smaller metabolites that your microbes create. These have been used to predict childhood obesity and even intelligence. However, this research is beyond the scope of Gut Hub - and the research is very new. It’s unclear in which direction the relationship is causal; does measurable intelligence modify your gut biome, or the other way around?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3/5.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thinking in Bets</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202210thinkinginbets/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2022 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202210thinkinginbets/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The first half of this book is very interesting, and includes many fun anecdotes from the life of a professional poker player. The second half is classic psychology material that is found in many other similar books: diversity helps consensus, allowing for dissent within teams helps them move towards the truth, our remembered experience is different from our experience, and learning when you&amp;rsquo;re on &amp;ldquo;tilt&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Slicing Pie</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202209slicingpie/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202209slicingpie/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A very quick read. Lots of &amp;ldquo;supporting&amp;rdquo; stories up front. The pain points of issuing equity too early in a project, or too late. So what is the solution? dynamic equity. Everyone tracks their work, either per hour, or per day, depending on what is more appropriate. Everyone is given a hypothetical hourly rate. The pie is then split up based on the amount of hypothetical cash they are owed relative to the entire amount of cash owed to all participants.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Six Not-So-Easy Pieces</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202207sixnoteasypieces/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2022 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202207sixnoteasypieces/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This book introduces the reader to relativity, symmetry and space-time through Feynman&amp;rsquo;s eyes. He discusses features of our universe with engaging analogies, like how to distinguish right from left (which is a tricky business). Or why we have time dilation from gravity. However, I&amp;rsquo;d argue that there are better books introducing audiences to these topics nowadays, like black holes and time warps by Kip S. Thorne.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Bond King</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202207bondking/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202207bondking/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;An interesting book for financial buffs. It reviews the origin story of active bond trading and goes through some of the details Pimco used to &amp;ldquo;generate alpha&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Some of the nifty tricks include:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;buying future contracts to meet risk requirements and then investing $ in short term bonds before the contract requires,&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;betting on future volatility of the markets (upper and lower bounds),&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;trading securities with itself (in differing accounts) to minimize fees,&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;pricing bonds more aggressively than the market to front-load performance within a fund,&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;and most generally, taking bets that future interest rates would be different from what &amp;ldquo;the market&amp;rdquo; was expecting.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Overall it was an interesting read, but some parts were a little slow, and of course, you have to have an interest in bonds.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homo Deus</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202206homodeus/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2022 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202206homodeus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tid-bits of history sprinkled throughout a synopsis of where humanity is heading.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Parts of the story were interesting, as history often is, but the general arc of the book took too long, and many of the ideas have been subject to too many recent podcasts that I tended to lose interest. On the flip side, for anyone who&amp;rsquo;s not come across these ideas before (i.e., do we have free will, what do humans value, the &amp;ldquo;story&amp;rdquo; that is currency, the internet of things, etc.), I&amp;rsquo;d suggest giving this book a read. For others, I&amp;rsquo;d recommend passing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Great Depression</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202206greatdepression/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202206greatdepression/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Going through a recession will never be quite the same again after reading this diary. Strange to see how many similarities exist in stock markets in such a different setting in time.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Humans love to speculate, and are quick to become greedy when the party is pumping. Those who like to party a little too hardy, leveraging their gains as collateral to buy more stock on margin, are almost always wiped out sooner or later.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Six Easy Pieces</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202205sixezpieces/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202205sixezpieces/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Parts were good, but overall, a lot has changed in ~60 years to make this book more of a historical piece than a superb physics text.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;bookmarked-ideas&#34;&gt;Bookmarked ideas&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;As molecules evaporate, they are leaving with more energy than the average motion of the liquid they depart. Conversely, when vapour from the air joins a liquid, there is a sudden great attraction as the molecule approaches the surface, resulting in energy added. Therefore, evaporation is the loss of heat, and consensation is the the generation of some back. When these are net equal, there is no heat exchange. However, this is a nifty thing to know when cooling hot liquids. i.e., blow on hot soup.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Carbon attracts oxygen (C-O) much more than O-O or C-C. So much so, that when they come together, they snap together with such force that excess energy is distributed to their surroundings. This of course is burning, and the sensation of heat. In certain circumstances, the excess energy is given off more than molecular motion of hot gas. The energy is so great, that it &lt;em&gt;generates light&lt;/em&gt;. This is how one gets flames!&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;What keeps electrons from simply falling in[to the nucleus]? This principle: If they were in the nucleus, we would know their position precisely, and the uncertainty principle would then require that they have a very large (but uncertain) momentum (and therefore energy). With this energy, they&amp;rsquo;d break away from the nucleus. They make a compromise: they leave themselves a little room for this uncertainty and then jiggle with a certain amount of minimum motion in accordance with this rule.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;cavendishs-experiment-aka-the-weighing-of-the-earth&#34;&gt;Cavendish&amp;rsquo;s experiment (aka, the weighing of the earth)&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;If there is a force between any pair of objects, we ought to be able to measure the force between our own objects&amp;hellip; It was first measured by Cavendish&amp;hellip; demonstrating the direct force between two large, fixed balls of lead and two smaller balls of lead on the ends of an arm supported by a very fine fiber, called a torsion fiber. By measuring how much the fiber gets twisted, once can measure the strength of the force, verify that it is inversely proportional to the square of the distance, and determine how strong it is. Thus, one may accurately determine the coefficient G in our gravitational force equation. By knowing G from this experiement, and by knowing how strongly the earth attracts, we indirectly learned the mass of the earth!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>There There</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202204therethere/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202204therethere/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some beautifully written passages that were thought provoking in the way good poetry often is; however the book overall wasn&amp;rsquo;t as captivating of a story as I&amp;rsquo;d hoped.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Unique storytelling in how the chapters were constructed, but I found it hard to build up empathy for any one character, and found myself loosing steam in the middle.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Power of Now</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202203powerofnow/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202203powerofnow/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A book about spirituality accessed by focusing your attention on the present. Written in the late 90&amp;rsquo;s, this book seems ahead of its time regarding the power of mindfulness. However, the author extends the benefits of mindfulness into the mystical realm of God, which might resonate with some folks, but harder for an atheist (like me) to digest.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Braiding Sweetgrass</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202107braidingsweetgrass/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jul 2021 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202107braidingsweetgrass/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Note: I only read ~50% of this book. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t captivated by the content my first time through, which might be why I only rated this a 3/5. I should like to try again one day, as I know many people who say this is one of their favourite books.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How I Invest My Money</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202012investmoney/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Dec 2020 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202012investmoney/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A collection of financial industry darlings speak openly about how they invest their money. Often aligning with the products they&amp;rsquo;ve worked on, but not always. It&amp;rsquo;d be nice to have more books openly discuss this topic to showcase the complexities of investing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
