<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Books on Will Cartar&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Books on Will Cartar&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <managingEditor>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</webMaster>
    <copyright>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2024 12:12:13 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://cartar.github.io./tags/books/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Where the Falcon Flies</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202409wherethefalconflies/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2024 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202409wherethefalconflies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Adam Shoalts is a wild man. In this book, he travels 3,400 km over 3 months to see where peregrine falcons nest. He does so on foot, and canoe. Paddling down the great lakes from his house on Lake Erie, past Toronto, up the Saint Lawrence through the many locks, past Montreal and Quebec City, all the way past Tadoussac to Saguenay, where he swaps his canoe for a backpack. He then hikes all the way to Labrador City (which Google maps says takes ~200 hours), where he buys a canoe, to paddles to the arctic to spot a falcon nest. After this, he paddles out to Kangiqsualujjuaq, which is just west of the Torngat Mountains. What sparked this epic journey? Perhaps a fundraiser, or a lifelong goal? It was neither; rather, in 2019 he spotted a peregrine falcon flying past his home, and was inspired to follow this migratory bird to its nesting place in the arctic. He&amp;rsquo;d have set out in 2020 if it weren&amp;rsquo;t for the pandemic. As soon as life settled down, he went in 2022.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Outlive</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202407outlived/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2024 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202407outlived/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Like successful aging, this book is a fascinating read that compiles the latest understandings about our bodies into a compendium of knowledge with many recommendations. Much of this book is summarizing studies about which molecules - proteins, hormones, types of cholesterol, and cellular processes are benefited by eating well, not too much (or too little), exercise, and sleep. However, unlike successful aging, the recommendations can be too specialized at times, and require too many resources (time and money) to execute properly. For example, the discussion about exercise requires a personal trainer, and many hours a week to carry out. Or, to hit the recommended protein levels, one needs to be having a good amount of meat twice per day, every day, on top of a protein shake, and high protein snack. This just doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem wise for the average person, or doable for the average household income. Having said all of this, the overall book was interesting nonetheless, and stacking this book with successful aging was enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultra-Processed People</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202403ultraprocessedpeople/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2024 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202403ultraprocessedpeople/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Oh boy, this book wasn&amp;rsquo;t so much anything new, as it was a compelling reminder to eat whole foods, or at the very least, purchase food who&amp;rsquo;s full list of ingredients you&amp;rsquo;d have at home. There is a slow, but steady, understanding of these so-called Ultra-Processed Foods (UPFs), and their negative health implications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Age of the City</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202402ageofthecity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Feb 2024 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202402ageofthecity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Even as someone who isn&amp;rsquo;t a city planner, I found many of the chapters somewhat obvious. The challenge of climate change in cities, or increased risk of novel viruses for example. However, I did enjoy the book; not dissimilar to a good economist article, the ideas were well written, and the story easy to follow. Just not enough &amp;ldquo;Aha&amp;rdquo; moments I suppose.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spark</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202401spark/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jan 2024 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202401spark/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As someone who knew very little Chinese history, this was a fascinating book. We follow various underground historians, or dissidents as the Chinese government would call them, set across the ages. Some, hundreds of years ago, but mainly, it is the story of people keeping the past 100 years of history alive, despite the best efforts of the Chinese government to forget. The mass starvation during the great famine of the late 50&amp;rsquo;s under Mao&amp;rsquo;s mismanagement, mass burials of the cultural revolution, and the many executions or lifelong detention of &amp;ldquo;dissidents&amp;rdquo; for simply speaking with an open mind. As the party has changed hands from Mao, to Deng Xiaoping, and now Xi Jinping, the country has seen massive change. Much of it for the better, but the need to control history has resulted in lost truths which are harrowingly kept alive by a select few.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Piranesi</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202312piranesi/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2023 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202312piranesi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This book had a lot of hype, both online and from my friend who recommended it. I&amp;rsquo;ll say, it took a bit to get into but then I was hooked. The non-spoiler description from Good Reads reads:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Piranesi’s house is no ordinary building: its rooms are infinite, its corridors endless, its walls are lined with thousands upon thousands of statues, each one different from all the others. Within the labyrinth of halls an ocean is imprisoned; waves thunder up staircases, rooms are flooded in an instant. But Piranesi is not afraid; he understands the tides as he understands the pattern of the labyrinth itself. He lives to explore the house.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Successful Aging</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202311successfulaging/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2023 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202311successfulaging/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Before I had even finished it, I&amp;rsquo;d bought 2 copies of this book: one for my parents, and the other for my partner&amp;rsquo;s. I admit, some chapters review much of what I already knew; exercise is very good for our brains and body (and you don&amp;rsquo;t need to be a gym rat - just get your heart rate up!); healthy eating isn&amp;rsquo;t prescribable, but it&amp;rsquo;ll include eating a range of unprocessed food (processed food is bad), eating in moderation, less sweets, and finding a diet that works best for you (without going to the extremes). But the many reviews of the latest neuroscience and how they apply to us as we age was fascinating. For example, a reason we &amp;ldquo;always have room for dessert&amp;rdquo; is the novel flavours (sweet after salty) pique your interest even though enough was several mouthfuls ago.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Brief Answers to the Big Questions</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202310briefanswerstobigquestions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202310briefanswerstobigquestions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A fun reminder of the wonders of our universe, guided by one of the most astonishing minds of the last century. My favourite parts were the forward, introduction, and prelude &amp;ldquo;why we must ask the big questions&amp;rdquo;, but that is because the reminder of the book reviewed ideas that I&amp;rsquo;m familiar with. It is remarkable that Stephen could write this book in his last year of life, given his limited ability to express himself (just some facial muscles by that point). That, mixed with his discussions about black holes, the beginning of the universe, and various other areas where our knowledge is incomplete were what made this book worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Team of Rivals</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202309teamofrivals/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Sep 2023 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202309teamofrivals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As someone with little knowledge of the American Civil War, or President Lincoln, this book was equally fascinating and well written. Lincoln&amp;rsquo;s name hasn&amp;rsquo;t gone down in history because of his superior military knowhow, or skilful &amp;ldquo;statesmanship&amp;rdquo;, but because of his superior &amp;ldquo;peculiar moral power and greatness of character&amp;rdquo;. It is truly a shame that politicians are not like Lincoln - who was so keenly aware of making the morally correct choice, at the opportune time, that he was able to craft a cabinet of rivals that balanced themselves on the whole. As is often touted today of top tier leadership, you want to foster trust, respect, and open disagreement that allows for the best ideas to flourish. Creating a leadership team of &amp;ldquo;yes-people&amp;rdquo; is never good in the long run. Lincoln was ahead of his time here, as that is exactly the atmosphere he was able to create and maintain through arguably the most trying times in all of America&amp;rsquo;s history. Comparing Lincoln (the first elected President of the Republican Party), to Donald Trump shows the alarming distance politicians have travelled into a world of short term exuberance. It is no wonder that democracy should suffer with America so divided.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Infinite Game</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202308infinitegame/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Aug 2023 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202308infinitegame/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This book is great for anyone leading a company, and good for those wanting to know if they&amp;rsquo;re a part of an organization that is in it for the long haul. The basic premise is that companies without a proper &lt;em&gt;Just Cause&lt;/em&gt;, and various other attributes, will at one point or another, succumb to their short sightedness, and fail. There are many examples to draw on, where companies prioritize profit over their purpose, and end up losing out to the inevitable innovation of competition.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mendeleyev&#39;s dream</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202308mendeleyevsdream/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2023 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202308mendeleyevsdream/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This book was the first time I came into contact with a history of chemistry, and it was absolutely fascinating. Histories of physics have been my default, due to their ongoing contributions to the origins of life, the universe and everything; but much of that history is the back and forth of military funded experiments, and intellectual genius. Chemistry, on the other hand, was funded by the wealthy in an attempt to create more wealth through transmutation (i.e., alchemy), as well as the mishaps of mad scientists tinkering with &amp;ldquo;the elements&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Future of AI</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202307futureofai/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jul 2023 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202307futureofai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This book has maybe two interesting parts to it. The description of how a new antibiotic was discovered by AI, and the modelling of protein folding by AI. Other than that, the book doesn&amp;rsquo;t go into much detail about AI, and instead focuses on ideas like the cyber threat of AI, and how it is that that cyber threat is different from say nuclear threat. I suppose those would be interesting topics to folks more politically inclined than me. I just wanted to explore cutting edge AI and its novel impacts, which I didn&amp;rsquo;t get from this book.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Death&#39;s End</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202305deathsend/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2023 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202305deathsend/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The cover of this book says: &amp;ldquo;wildly imaginative&amp;rdquo;, which is a perfect synopsys. I&amp;rsquo;ve not had my mind blow so many times over by a series, and I doubt I ever will again. It isn&amp;rsquo;t just the exotic physics of higher dimensions utilized by hyper advanced civilizations. It is the political interactions of those civilizations with one another, and a story arc that is truly captivating. I felt the full range of emotions in this book - from excitedly anticipating reunions, to battles outcomes, mind games, and love stories. This book had it all. I cannot recommend this book, or this series enough. The only downside is that the books are a little long, and take ~50-100 pages to really get into. But once you&amp;rsquo;re there, the length of the story becomes a blessing, as you&amp;rsquo;ll not want the ride to end.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Surely You&#39;re Joking Mr. Feynman</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202304surelyyourejoking/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Apr 2023 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202304surelyyourejoking/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This collection of stories from Richard Feynman&amp;rsquo;s life is a fascinating time capsule into life in the mid 1900&amp;rsquo;s. From his work on the Manhattan Project, to his inquisitive mind and child-like love of life, he truly is a magnificent character whose voice and adventures shine bright in this book.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Dark Forest</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202303thedarkforest/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202303thedarkforest/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With the story well underway, this second book is a masterpiece. Without giving too much away, we are transported to a future where Luo Ji is awake and well. Technology has progressed far enough to give humanity a sense of security, and that leads to some interesting plot development. We finally learn why Luo Ji had so many assassination attempts against him, and yet again, the story unfolds with unanticipated twists that make it hard to put down.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Five Most Important Questions</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202302questions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2023 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202302questions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A dated book that feels a little ahead of it&amp;rsquo;s time. Certainly still relevant today, it is full of anecdotes about why the 5 questions outlined below are so crucial to success for any organization (private, public, non-profit, etc.). But really, if you agree that the five questions are valuable, you don&amp;rsquo;t need to read the book so much as do the exercise. However, the book is a quick 2 hour read (or less), so you don&amp;rsquo;t lose much giving it a spin!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Three-Body Problem</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202301threebodyproblem/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2023 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202301threebodyproblem/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I found the narrative a little hard to follow at first, but by the end, I was hooked. This sci-fi adventure is inventive in the creation of the antagonist, and keeps you wanting to learn more about their story. Having not read any literature from China before, I found there to a weight behind the backstory that was new to me. The author spoke of cultural revolution in China in a way that was unexpected, and captivating. I&amp;rsquo;m excited to read the next 2 parts of the adventure!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flush</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202212flush/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2022 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202212flush/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;An interesting review of how useful our poop is, the current science of capturing that information, and what is going on on the inside to cause our stool to look the way it does.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The main takeaways are:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re constipated - you&amp;rsquo;re absorbing too much water, drink more.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If you have diarrhea - you&amp;rsquo;re losing a lot of water, drink more.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If your poop experience is poor, try&amp;hellip;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;eating more fiber, but ramp up slowly as you might not have the right mix of microbes at the start.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;boosting the diversity of your microbiome by eating plain yogurt (daily), and fermented foods like kimchi or kombucha.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;When you travel, expect to have a bad time - best to prepare your microbiome beforehand with the above tips.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-other-notes-i-took&#34;&gt;Some other notes I took:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;useful&#34;&gt;Useful&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Overuse of laxatives in general can decrease absorption of nutrients and other medications, cause electrolyte imbalances, create dependency and actually worsen constipation by interfering with the colon’s natural contractions.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Yellow and greasy suggest not digesting fat well; and that evaluation for celiac disease or another cause of malabsorption is warranted.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Green stool could be food passing too quickly and not giving your bile a chance to break down into brown colour;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Black could be bleeding in upper tract or black licorice&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Red could be beets or bleeding in lower tract - often hemorrhoids but sometimes more seriously colon cancer&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;White or clay-coloured / devoid of colour from bile suggests a blockage in a duct that carries bile from liver to gallbladder -&amp;gt; in infants is life threatening if not corrected&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Constipation can tear the main intestinal lining and cause anal fissures. Intense pressure on the colon can cause diverticulitis (inflamed or infected pouches of gut tissue), hemorrhoids (akin to varicose veins; also can be from prolonged sitting on the pot), to more serious conditions like defecation syncope (fainting on the toilet), or even a stroke.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Posture modification on the toilet can reduce strain and encourage a more complete evacuation.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;When ramping up on fiber, if you didn’t already eat a lot of fiber, you’ll need to ramp up slowly, to avoid stomach cramps (as it’s unlikely you have the right fiber-munching bacteria to begin with). Slow and steady can cultivate the microbiome you seek, and adding fermented foods / yogurt can do wonders too.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The bacteria sometimes take time to ramp up the right metabolic pathways or fiber-processing genes. In artificial guts, you see bacteria don’t degrade the fiber as much on the first day compared to the next.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Microbiome disruptions like: food poisoning, international travel, and dietary changes are all associated with shifts in gut flora.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Sometimes, these changes can introduce totally new species that sometimes wipe out weaker competition. However, it is usually the case that the system as a whole preserves their functionality - like digesting carbohydrates.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;This is where food sensitivity tests, and microbiome lab tests (stool testing) fall short. It’s an expensive snapshot of your current system that will need to be done again in the near future.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Eating a diet rich in fermented foods like: yogurt, kimchi, and kombucha tea for many weeks shows signs of improved gut microbiome diversity and reduced signs of inflammation compared to counterparts on a high-fiber diet.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;“The bacteria food alone isn’t enough; we need the bacteria that can eat it.”&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Caution: nothing is guaranteed. What works for others won’t necessarily work for you&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;less-useful-but-noteworthy&#34;&gt;Less useful, but noteworthy&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Constipation - colon absorbs too much water. 15 major classes of drugs can cause constipation, according to one tally, even tylenol can stop things up&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Many drugs cause diarrhea by increasing intestinal muscle movements that push everything onwards. Allergies, infections, contaminated or overly spicy food can trigger an immune response to flush out the system. Can be from IBS, lactose intolerance, diseases, drugs or damage can inflame or tear the intestinal lining, interfering with water absorption that makes matters worse.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Some researchers claim timing transit is more important than Bristol stool scale.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Median is 29 hours. Range is 4 hours - 10 days&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Longer transit time associated with greater gut diversity -&amp;gt; not sure how well studied this is&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And greater diversity isn’t always a good thing -&amp;gt; if that diversity includes an unfavourable mix.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;C-section + instant formula over vagina birth + breastfeeding alter microbiome in ways that increase the risk of asthma and allergies.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Babies exposed to a broader diversity of microbes are more protected and have lower risk of bad lifelong health outcomes&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Think of your microbiome as your mini ecosystem for which you are the caretaker. * If you eat poorly, don’t prioritise sleep, exercise, and a balanced lifestyle, your microbiome is likely to get out of balance.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;not-useful-but-cool&#34;&gt;Not useful, but cool&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;German made: Flachspuler - or flat-flush toilet, helps people examine their stool before being flushed&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;People in the US eat about 30-35% of the fiber that they should - which makes the average deposit in western toilets a fraction of what they should be&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Lots of applications for measuring specific biomarkers like proteins, carbohydrates, fats, and smaller metabolites that your microbes create. These have been used to predict childhood obesity and even intelligence. However, this research is beyond the scope of Gut Hub - and the research is very new. It’s unclear in which direction the relationship is causal; does measurable intelligence modify your gut biome, or the other way around?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3/5.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>naked statistics</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202211nakedstatistics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2022 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202211nakedstatistics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A masterpiece in fun-reading education; this book is accessible to everyone who&amp;rsquo;s goal is to learn statistics. And for those with a strong handle on the subject, it is a good reminder of the pitfalls of being too brash with the toolkit.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thinking in Bets</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202210thinkinginbets/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2022 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202210thinkinginbets/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The first half of this book is very interesting, and includes many fun anecdotes from the life of a professional poker player. The second half is classic psychology material that is found in many other similar books: diversity helps consensus, allowing for dissent within teams helps them move towards the truth, our remembered experience is different from our experience, and learning when you&amp;rsquo;re on &amp;ldquo;tilt&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Slicing Pie</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202209slicingpie/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202209slicingpie/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A very quick read. Lots of &amp;ldquo;supporting&amp;rdquo; stories up front. The pain points of issuing equity too early in a project, or too late. So what is the solution? dynamic equity. Everyone tracks their work, either per hour, or per day, depending on what is more appropriate. Everyone is given a hypothetical hourly rate. The pie is then split up based on the amount of hypothetical cash they are owed relative to the entire amount of cash owed to all participants.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Psychology of Money</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202209psychologyofmoney/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2022 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202209psychologyofmoney/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A collection of stories demonstrating that people aren&amp;rsquo;t crazy, but they do sometimes fail to make reasonable decisions with their money. Being rational with money can sometimes be the unreasonable thing to do after you&amp;rsquo;ve factored in human psychology. This book is a fantastic starting point for anyone wanting to improve their relationship with money.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum: Einstein, Bohr, and the Great Debate about the Nature of Reality</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202209quantumgreatdebate/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Sep 2022 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202209quantumgreatdebate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For anyone who loves physics, this is a must read. The magnitude of breakthroughs in theoretical physics between the late 1800&amp;rsquo;s and early 1900&amp;rsquo;s is staggering. Kumar takes you through those breakthroughs one at a time, carefully including personal anecdotes of the great scientists as their leaps of understanding changed the world.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Outliers</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202208outliers/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202208outliers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For those unfamiliar with how impactful luck is in our lives, this book is an eye opener. Malcolm sheds light on how societal outliers achieved (or failed to achieve) greatness, and the role of luck in their journey. He recounts the luck of entrepreneurs in America born in the 1850’s (?), Jewish lawyers born in the 1920’s, and software engineers born in the 1950’s. The role of language &amp;amp; culture in airplane crashes, and many more interesting stories that’ll make you appreciate just how random life really is.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Ride of a Lifetime</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202208rideofalifetime/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2022 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202208rideofalifetime/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A captivating recount of how Disney transformed over the past 20+ years. Bob reviews many acquisitions, and some near-misses (Disney almost bought Twitter before Disney +). A good read for anyone curious how big companies grow larger. Lots of lessons learned.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;highlights&#34;&gt;Highlights:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Avoid getting into the business of manufacturing trombone oil. You may become the greatest trombone-oil manufacturer in the world, but in the end, the world only consumes a few quarts of trombone oil a year!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s a hard thing to do, especially in the moment, but those instances in which you find yourself hoping that something will work without being able to convincingly explain to yourself how it will work - that&amp;rsquo;s when a little bell should go off, and you should walk yourself through some clarifying questions. What&amp;rsquo;s the problem I need to solve? Does this solution make sense? If I&amp;rsquo;m feeling some doubt, why? Am I doing this for sound reasons or am I motivated by something personal?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;A company&amp;rsquo;s culture is shaped by a lot of things, but this is one of the most important - you have to convey your priorities clearly and repeatedly. In my experience, it&amp;rsquo;s what separates great managers from the rest.&amp;rdquo;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;You can do a lot for the morale of the people around you (and therefore the people around them) just by taking the guesswork out of their day-to-day life&amp;hellip; This is where we want to be. This is how we&amp;rsquo;re going to get there.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;My job was to set our company on a new path, and the first step was to defuse this unnecessary struggle. The easiest and most productive way to do that was to recognize that what Roy needed, ultimately, was to feel respected. That was precious to him, and it cost me and the company so little.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;This is you making a decision about them - not them as a person but the way they have performed in their job - and they need and deserve to know that it&amp;rsquo;s coming from you. You can&amp;rsquo;t make small talk once you bring someone in for that conversation. I normally say something along the lines of: &amp;lsquo;I&amp;rsquo;ve asked you to come in here for a difficult reason.&amp;rsquo; And then I try to be as direct about the issue as possible, explaining clearly and concisely what wasn&amp;rsquo;t working and why I didn&amp;rsquo;t think it was going to change. I emphasize that it was a tough decision to make, and that I understand that it&amp;rsquo;s much harder on them.&amp;rdquo;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;If you respect the person, then you owe them a clear explanation for the decision you&amp;rsquo;re making. There&amp;rsquo;s no way for the conversation not to be painful, but at least it can be honest.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;the hardest but also the most necessary lesson to keep in mind, that wherever you are along the path, you&amp;rsquo;re the same person you&amp;rsquo;ve always been.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Pessimism leads to paranoia, which leads to defensiveness, which leads to risk aversion.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;If something doesn&amp;rsquo;t feel right to you, it won&amp;rsquo;t be right for you.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4/5&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Six Not-So-Easy Pieces</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202207sixnoteasypieces/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2022 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202207sixnoteasypieces/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This book introduces the reader to relativity, symmetry and space-time through Feynman&amp;rsquo;s eyes. He discusses features of our universe with engaging analogies, like how to distinguish right from left (which is a tricky business). Or why we have time dilation from gravity. However, I&amp;rsquo;d argue that there are better books introducing audiences to these topics nowadays, like black holes and time warps by Kip S. Thorne.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Lifecycle of Software Objects</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202207softwarelifecycle/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jul 2022 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202207softwarelifecycle/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A short story about what our digital future might hold. We follow an ex-zoo keeper turned digital pet trainer after the zoo she worked at closed down. The world her digi-pet grew up in becomes threatened, and we see the great lengths she&amp;rsquo;ll go, along with a small community of like-minded fanatics, to give these digital humanoids a better future.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Sovereign Individual</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202207sovereignindividual/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2022 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202207sovereignindividual/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I only skimmed this book, read about 1/3 of the content, but felt I got the gist. The authors outline what they think a future without government power will look like, as power shifts to individuals in the information age.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Individuals will be able to insulate themselves from governments in ways previously impossible. Work, communications, assets, and banking systems will be fully digital, allowing life to move wherever the individual desires.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Bond King</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202207bondking/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202207bondking/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;An interesting book for financial buffs. It reviews the origin story of active bond trading and goes through some of the details Pimco used to &amp;ldquo;generate alpha&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Some of the nifty tricks include:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;buying future contracts to meet risk requirements and then investing $ in short term bonds before the contract requires,&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;betting on future volatility of the markets (upper and lower bounds),&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;trading securities with itself (in differing accounts) to minimize fees,&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;pricing bonds more aggressively than the market to front-load performance within a fund,&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;and most generally, taking bets that future interest rates would be different from what &amp;ldquo;the market&amp;rdquo; was expecting.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Overall it was an interesting read, but some parts were a little slow, and of course, you have to have an interest in bonds.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homo Deus</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202206homodeus/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2022 01:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202206homodeus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tid-bits of history sprinkled throughout a synopsis of where humanity is heading.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Parts of the story were interesting, as history often is, but the general arc of the book took too long, and many of the ideas have been subject to too many recent podcasts that I tended to lose interest. On the flip side, for anyone who&amp;rsquo;s not come across these ideas before (i.e., do we have free will, what do humans value, the &amp;ldquo;story&amp;rdquo; that is currency, the internet of things, etc.), I&amp;rsquo;d suggest giving this book a read. For others, I&amp;rsquo;d recommend passing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Great Depression</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202206greatdepression/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202206greatdepression/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Going through a recession will never be quite the same again after reading this diary. Strange to see how many similarities exist in stock markets in such a different setting in time.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Humans love to speculate, and are quick to become greedy when the party is pumping. Those who like to party a little too hardy, leveraging their gains as collateral to buy more stock on margin, are almost always wiped out sooner or later.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Quick Fix</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202206quickfix/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202206quickfix/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A well researched review of the necessary skepticism established Psychology fads need. Chapters focusing on the implicit bias test, grit, the power of self-esteem, power posing, prime world (everything we do is the result of previous priming sensory input), fears over &amp;ldquo;superpredators&amp;rdquo;, and the ability for war veteran&amp;rsquo;s to overcome PTSD with mental training.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Glass Castle</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202205glasscastle/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 May 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202205glasscastle/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A memoir of an extraordinary childhood; one where quotes like &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;d gotten pretty good at shooting the revolver by the time I was 4&amp;rdquo; is but the tip of the iceberg. Parents who disliked &amp;ldquo;the system&amp;rdquo;, and thought their misfortunes were adventures to be had. Hard times were simply hard lessons, but not worth fussing over. A true look behind the curtain at some of America&amp;rsquo;s forgotten people.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Papillon</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202205papillon/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202205papillon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A wild ride through the early-mid 20th century Euro-America prison systems. Our autobiographical story is piloted by a Frenchman, who&amp;rsquo;s candour is contagious, often to his benefit, but at crucial moments, to his demise. Super fun to read; it&amp;rsquo;s a fantastical life story to be sure.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Six Easy Pieces</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202205sixezpieces/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202205sixezpieces/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Parts were good, but overall, a lot has changed in ~60 years to make this book more of a historical piece than a superb physics text.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;bookmarked-ideas&#34;&gt;Bookmarked ideas&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;As molecules evaporate, they are leaving with more energy than the average motion of the liquid they depart. Conversely, when vapour from the air joins a liquid, there is a sudden great attraction as the molecule approaches the surface, resulting in energy added. Therefore, evaporation is the loss of heat, and consensation is the the generation of some back. When these are net equal, there is no heat exchange. However, this is a nifty thing to know when cooling hot liquids. i.e., blow on hot soup.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Carbon attracts oxygen (C-O) much more than O-O or C-C. So much so, that when they come together, they snap together with such force that excess energy is distributed to their surroundings. This of course is burning, and the sensation of heat. In certain circumstances, the excess energy is given off more than molecular motion of hot gas. The energy is so great, that it &lt;em&gt;generates light&lt;/em&gt;. This is how one gets flames!&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;What keeps electrons from simply falling in[to the nucleus]? This principle: If they were in the nucleus, we would know their position precisely, and the uncertainty principle would then require that they have a very large (but uncertain) momentum (and therefore energy). With this energy, they&amp;rsquo;d break away from the nucleus. They make a compromise: they leave themselves a little room for this uncertainty and then jiggle with a certain amount of minimum motion in accordance with this rule.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;cavendishs-experiment-aka-the-weighing-of-the-earth&#34;&gt;Cavendish&amp;rsquo;s experiment (aka, the weighing of the earth)&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;If there is a force between any pair of objects, we ought to be able to measure the force between our own objects&amp;hellip; It was first measured by Cavendish&amp;hellip; demonstrating the direct force between two large, fixed balls of lead and two smaller balls of lead on the ends of an arm supported by a very fine fiber, called a torsion fiber. By measuring how much the fiber gets twisted, once can measure the strength of the force, verify that it is inversely proportional to the square of the distance, and determine how strong it is. Thus, one may accurately determine the coefficient G in our gravitational force equation. By knowing G from this experiement, and by knowing how strongly the earth attracts, we indirectly learned the mass of the earth!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dopamine Nation</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202204dopaminenation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202204dopaminenation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;An insightful perspective on our society today, the author weaves stories of addiction throughout to illustrate how we&amp;rsquo;re easily prone to it, and how we might pull ourselves out.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The most insightful lesson (for me) was that pain is in fact a pleasurable time-sink, due to the pleasure-pain balance our bodies strive for. Post pain, we are often flooded with euphoric hormones to compensate. Beware of becoming addicted to pain, but, when used correctly, it is a low risk powerful stimulant.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stolen Focus</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202204stolenfocus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202204stolenfocus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A must read for those itching to learn why they have a love hate relationship with technology. All ideas are presented alongside their empirical findings, including where the scientific community has a consensus, and where it does not.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Many of these ideas are present in other self help books, like: sleep more, eat well, work less, and make time for slowness (yoga, meditation, nature walks without audio) and play. But the studies and storytelling in this book make it worthwhile nonetheless for those who are already familiar with this list.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Bomber Mafia</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202204bombermafia/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Apr 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202204bombermafia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A masterclass in storytelling. I found it hard to put this book down from start to finish. As the title says, this book follows the evolution of America&amp;rsquo;s bomber mafia, a group of pilots who helped create the Air Force. We learn about their military decisions, shortcomings, success, and the ending of WW2. An interesting story told by one of the greatest storytellers of our time.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>There There</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202204therethere/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202204therethere/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some beautifully written passages that were thought provoking in the way good poetry often is; however the book overall wasn&amp;rsquo;t as captivating of a story as I&amp;rsquo;d hoped.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Unique storytelling in how the chapters were constructed, but I found it hard to build up empathy for any one character, and found myself loosing steam in the middle.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Power of Now</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202203powerofnow/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202203powerofnow/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A book about spirituality accessed by focusing your attention on the present. Written in the late 90&amp;rsquo;s, this book seems ahead of its time regarding the power of mindfulness. However, the author extends the benefits of mindfulness into the mystical realm of God, which might resonate with some folks, but harder for an atheist (like me) to digest.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Less Is More</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202202lessismore/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202202lessismore/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;How degrowth will save the world&amp;rdquo;. This book describes how we might move away from a constantly growing economy, to one that is decelerating, without harming the people who live in it, and in fact, improving their lives along the way.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To get us there, the &amp;ldquo;upper class 1%&amp;rdquo; will suffer; they won&amp;rsquo;t be able to consume at the current multiplier they enjoy. But they too will benefit from a healthier way of life, and a society that is more inclusive.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Educated</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202202educated/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202202educated/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A gripping story of being raised without traditional education, and the impact that had on Tara as she discovers a world beyond her childhood.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I found this book hard to put down. I highly recommend it to anyone looking for a non-fiction story that&amp;rsquo;ll transport you to another world.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noise: A flaw in Human Judgment</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202110noise/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Oct 2021 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202110noise/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This book opened my eyes to the differences between bias and noise, and how they are equally proportional to disrupting our desired outcome. That is to say, imagine missing a target by some random &amp;ldquo;noisy&amp;rdquo; amount, which widens the bell curve of outcomes. The distance, on average, away from the target result would be just as bad as an equal error magnitude in bias. The only difference being that the bias is easier to see, because it is clustering away from the target. Thus, bias is often the focus in reducing error for our desired outcomes, when really, it should be considered equally with noise, if our goal is error reduction.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Braiding Sweetgrass</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202107braidingsweetgrass/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jul 2021 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202107braidingsweetgrass/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Note: I only read ~50% of this book. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t captivated by the content my first time through, which might be why I only rated this a 3/5. I should like to try again one day, as I know many people who say this is one of their favourite books.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics of the Impossible</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202106physicsimpossible/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 May 2021 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202106physicsimpossible/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A physics book unlike any other I&amp;rsquo;ve read. Reality is distorted by the mind-bending possibilities of physics that are beyond our reach. Sometimes, the physics has been proven, but we&amp;rsquo;re missing technological advances necessary to bring it to life, other times, it&amp;rsquo;s physics that might truly be impossible. In either case, the idea&amp;rsquo;s themselves are delightful to consume. Some minds are truly special.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Delivering Happiness</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202105deliveringhappiness/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 May 2021 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202105deliveringhappiness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A dot-com winner, then loser, then back to the top story. Lots of building-a-business advice from a very unique person. A lot of his focus is on the customer, and internal culture. Sorta changed my perception of what a &amp;ldquo;head of culture&amp;rdquo; can even do at a company. Namely, they can facilitate an environment to help people connect, but that could be very different for each person, and at the end of the day, culture is what is &lt;em&gt;felt&lt;/em&gt; by each person. The collective average being that which is its core, but truly, it&amp;rsquo;s just a feeling.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shoe Dog</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202103shoedog/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2021 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202103shoedog/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A novel that&amp;rsquo;ll transport you back to a decade quite unlike today. Not only was there no Nike, there wasn&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;athleisure&amp;rdquo; or jogging for fun. The story on it&amp;rsquo;s own is hard to put down, but the way it&amp;rsquo;s told makes this a truly joyful read.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atomic Habits</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202101atomichabits/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202101atomichabits/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Very engaging book. In addition to learning about the power of habits, you&amp;rsquo;ll also learn to recognize what parts of your life are good/bad habits and how to build/break them. It&amp;rsquo;s a solid framework for everyone to understand, regardless of your goals. Best of all, this book keeps you engaged from chapter 1 with well told anecdotes and analogies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How I Invest My Money</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202012investmoney/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Dec 2020 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202012investmoney/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A collection of financial industry darlings speak openly about how they invest their money. Often aligning with the products they&amp;rsquo;ve worked on, but not always. It&amp;rsquo;d be nice to have more books openly discuss this topic to showcase the complexities of investing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Almanack of Naval Ravikant</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202012almanack/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Dec 2020 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202012almanack/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A collection of Naval Ravikant&amp;rsquo;s tweetstorms, discussions, and ideas woven into a digestible &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.navalmanack.com/&#34;&gt;ebook&lt;/a&gt;. The ideas focus on wealth on happiness.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Some of my favourite ideas:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;tweetstorm-about-wealth-creation&#34;&gt;Tweetstorm about wealth creation:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Seek wealth, not money or status. Wealth is having assets that earn while you sleep. Money is how we transfer time and wealth. Status is your place in the social hierarchy&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Hard thing about Hard Things</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202012hardthings/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2020 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202012hardthings/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A brutally honest take on the challenges faced when trying to build a company. A fantastic story of the compromises a CEO might face, and why being an entrepreneur is so hard.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4/5.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Alchemist</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202010thealchemist/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Oct 2020 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202010thealchemist/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A bit dated, this book remains a captivating story of the human condition. Seeking an outcome for fulfillment:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s the possibility of having a dream come true that makes life interesting, he thought, as he looked again at the position of the sun, and hurried his pace.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stamped From The Beginning</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202009stampedfromthebeginning/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202009stampedfromthebeginning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I agree with the book&amp;rsquo;s subtitle, this is definitely a mammoth overview of racist ideas in America. Starting with the racists ideas of colonial Europe that seeded the founding father, or white-religous-upperclassmen, as is more appropriate, up to Barack Obama, and some of the racist ideas he pondered aloud.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Silk Roads</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202006silkroads/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2020 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202006silkroads/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This book is an epic undertaking, showcasing world history up to the early 2010&amp;rsquo;s, through the lense of the silk road. History has many authors, and this book does well to capture their ideas in a cohesive framework. The thesis presented here outlines how resource transportation routes shaped our world history. Equally important to the goods flowing through commerce were new ideas, including religions, and a massive game of political chess. Short term policies crafted to maintain power at the expense of those without it, often led to self destruction through overreach (and over spending). Worse still was the long term instability created by dying powers&amp;rsquo; abrupt departure from battleground regions. The most shocking lesson I took away is how cyclical our world history is. The fight for power, and abhorrent disregard for others by those trying to maintain it, is the saddest trait we share.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alex&#39;s Adventures in Numberland</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202004alexadventurenumberland/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Apr 2020 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202004alexadventurenumberland/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This book was truly a wonderful read! If you want to learn about math&amp;rsquo;s history, you will love this book &amp;#x1f495;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You do not need to have a strong background in math to get the full punch from this story.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-favourite-takeaways&#34;&gt;My favourite takeaways&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;regression-to-the-mean&#34;&gt;Regression to the mean&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Regression to the mean is the concept that, over time, event likelihood converges on the average result. Said another way, whenever an outlier occurs, there&amp;rsquo;s a good chance that the next event will be closer to the main outcome.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Talking to Strangers</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202003talking2strangers/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202003talking2strangers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Using a mix of data and in-depth investigations around high profile human interactions, where human behaviour is interpreted terribly, we learn some very important lessons. As usual, Malcolm Gladwell delivers these stories in a wonderful read.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-favourite-takeaways&#34;&gt;My favourite takeaways&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Defaulting to the truth is OK. It is what created our society and it would be stupid to override this companionship generating trait.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The coupling of environment and action is so strong that it should always be taken into account when interacting with strangers.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t judge a stranger, judge their environment.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;We are bad lie detectors. We expect a liar to act one way, and a truth teller another. Our snap decision lie detection is never to be trusted.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;5/5.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Personal MBA</title>
      <link>https://cartar.github.io./books/202002mypersonalmba/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2020 11:40:14 -0400</pubDate><author>william.cartar@gmail.com (Will Cartar)</author>
      <guid>https://cartar.github.io./books/202002mypersonalmba/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed this book, but am hesitant to recommend it to others. The writing is only OK, and so much of the content felt somewhat common sense. However, I did find multiple nuggets worth keeping!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-favourite-takeaways&#34;&gt;My favourite takeaways&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;prototyping&#34;&gt;Prototyping&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When developing a business, iteration and feedback are key. Offering a pre-order with full access to the witten Prototype (description of what is being offered) is ideal.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
